<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">08 Conservation Plans for Modern Architecture: The Case of IIM. A Conversation with Brinda Somaya</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Alessandra Rampazzo, Brinda Somaya</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Interview by Alessandra Rampazzo (2 March, 2022)</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">Brinda Somaya is Principal Architect &amp; Managing Director of Somaya &amp; Kalappa Consultants (SNK), based in Mumbai, India.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">She is an architect and urban conservationist who has merged architecture, conservation and social equity in projects ranging from institutional campuses and rehabilitation of a village impacted by an earthquake, to the restoration of an 18th-century cathedral. She founded SNK in 1978. The office was selected in 2014 as conservation architects for the restoration of Louis I. Kahn’s buildings at the Indian Institute of Management in Ahmedabad (IIMA).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">Alessandra Rampazzo</strong>: Brinda, first of all thanks a lot for your time. 
In order to help us following the complexity of your assignment, could you briefly summarize how did the commission started and how did you get involved in the process of restoring the Louis I. Kahn’s buildings at the IIMA?</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">Brinda Somaya</strong>: So, everything I’m saying is to the best of my knowledge and my recollection because now it is almost eight years since we began this proposal. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">We first read about this competition in 2014. We applied for it and then we had to face a series of interviews. We had, of course, to submit our proposal first and then we were called to Ahmedabad for the interview. Earlier then this Request For Proposals (RFP) came out, the IIMA had already talked to Peter Inskip and Stephen Gee and they had prepared the initial report on what they saw and on the way to go ahead on the restoration of the Campus. During the interview we had them connected on Zoom (or whatever the platform used was) and they asked me several questions on our approach, on how we would go about it, etc. but, of course, the IIMA also had their own nominated jury.
Subsequently, at the end of 2014, we got to know that we had won the project, which included the Plaza with the three main buildings - the Library, the Classrooms Block and the Faculty Block - and 18 of the Dormitories. This was what we were told to deal with. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: From what you said, the jury of the competition was then composed by selected people from IIMA plus the Office who did the conservation report. Is that correct?</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: Yes. I don’t know how exactly the internal working happened but, as I said before, at the presentation of our proposal to the IIMA jury we were asked several questions by the architects from the United Kingdom. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: Talking about the condition report Inskip and Gee did: they were used to these kind of commissions, since they had worked on another Conservation Plan for the Louis I. Kahn Yale Center for British Art Building<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p> In the case of IIMA, was the report deeply going into the problem?</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: The one for Yale was a very detailed report because, in that case, they were much more involved in the process itself. In the case of IIMA it was more an initial report and then we were chosen as conservation architects. But still, it was an interesting document that the IIMA gave to us.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: After you won the competition, you were finally officially involved with the restoration plan. So then, how did you decide to proceed in the assignment, focusing on understanding the value of the building itself before suggesting any possible intervention? I know that you’ve been at the Louis I. Kahn Archive in Philadelphia.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: So, we first tried to find out what was available in Ahmedabad itself. I also contacted Anant D. Raje’s wife and his daughter but, at that time, they were in the process of giving the entire set of drawings to the University of Pennsylvania, to the Louis I. Kahn Archive. So I didn’t get the opportunity to see anything in Ahmedabad from them. However, I was able to get from IIMA whatever they had, which was a set of structural drawings from Sharad Shah and a limited amount of other documents, including the wonderful calendar, which I always talk about in my talks, with a specific note on the day Kahn actually died. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">But since I was not fully satisfied, I tried very hard to find more informations and I finally decided to go to Philadelphia and spend few days there at the Archive. It is an enormous Archive. Where to begin? This is actually a difficult question, you know. You have to take certain decisions, understanding the limitations we have in terms of so many issues. It is not so easy: we are in India, we have to work with different types of constraints, including the fact that IIMA is still a running Institution. Budgets were also there (as constraints). It was, again, fully occupied. So what was interesting to me was to understand Kahn - the man and his thoughts and his work - as well as I could. So it was more trying to intellectualize in a way, even if I don’t think this is the proper word to use, since I consider myself a professional, but certainly those ideas have to come in the picture, in order to better understand him and consequently the project. So I found some wonderful photographs, lots of Kahn’s specifications about the method of construction. So whatever we could afford, we bought, we took pictures of. At the Archive they were very helpful to us, especially the Head of the Archive<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>, who was very good to us (he is very involved with Kahn, of course). I brought back (to India) as much material I could. It helped in different ways, but mainly it helped my team to understand the project, the value of what they were doing and the importance of it, in terms of being able to restore a group of buildings that was so important in 20th-century architecture. I think that my going there, making this effort and coming back conveyed to everybody why this assignment was so important to us. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The other thing which I was able to do, which has been absolutely wonderful, is that I made friend with Nathaniel and Sue Anne Kahn and Alexandra Tyng. Nathaniel particularly has been a great support to me but I also spoke with his mother, the landscape architect (Harriet Pattison), who recently sent me the book they published on him<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>. So it became also a friendship with the family: getting Nathaniel and Sue Ann’s support for what we have done and what we are doing means a lot to me and helps me a lot especially considering the difficult road we have taken. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: Moving to the client – the IIMA Institution – and the commission: which were the main requests and how did you manage to combine the contemporary needs of an Academy such as the IIMA with the idea of just preserving the building and its value?</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: Regarding the client, when I started the reference was the Director Dr. Ashish Nanda, who was very clear on what he wanted to do. In 2018, after he returned back to Harvard (he teaches at the Harvard Business School), the IIMA appointed a new Director, Dr. Errol D’Souza, who has actually been connected to the Faculty as a professor for decades. Plus, they also have a Board of Governors, who takes some of these decisions. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">I’m sure you are aware of the big controversy that has been taken place and the resolution has still to be taken<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p>. My beliefs were very clear: I had been appointed to restore this group of buildings, this critical mass as a whole was absolutely essential to retain the thoughts and ideas that Louis I. Kahn had when he designed it. If any part of it would have been removed, it would have never been the same again. That was my belief. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">I think you are indeed aware of the situation about the Dormitories: there have been a huge amount of both global and national discussions and debates on this. I don’t have any answer, but my role here is very clear: I have completed the library building for which we won the UNESCO award of distinction<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>. The Jury Citation said: </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">“Through careful studies and extensive modelling, the conservation team has conquered a range of difficult technical challenges to extend the life of the composite brick and concrete structure with its distinctive geometric forms. The project has recovered configurations and uses of space in line with the architect’s original vision, while upgrading functionality to ensure that the library is ready to meet contemporary requirements and provide universal access”. </p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">And then what they say at the end is interesting: </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">“With Modernist heritage enjoying increasing acclaim, but still facing the widespread threat of demolition, this initiative promises to have major policy impact within Ahmedabad and throughout India”.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">We had already won this award at the time this controversy erupted. I hope that this – what UNESCO said – went to a lot of people who then would think about the future of this Campus. 
At this point in time we are in the process of beginning the restoration of the Faculty Building, which has been completely emptied out (the entire building). We are now actually studying the conditions. There are huge challenges, not just in the present condition of the building, but also in deciding how to bring it up to the codes – which are requirements nowadays, since Ahmedabad is in a heavy seismic zone of the Country - and still respect, to the best of our ability, what exists. For sure, there are always going to be people who will advise and who will tell us what was right, what was wrong, what we could have done or what we should have done differently. However I think that with our experience and with our knowledge we will try and take the best route to create a balance between all these different challenges that face us. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: Knowing that you were going on with the restoration process, the news about the possible demolition of part of the Campus was actually more shocking. It looked like the IIMA was completely changing its mind on the adopted approach. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: You are very right. I had absolutely no idea that this was even been contemplated, until they actually put it on the newspaper, so it came out as a big shock. The Institute knows that I was really surprised and shocked by the fact that they had gone on this route. We were worried as well, especially thinking that we were just in the middle of the restoration process. It was a difficult time, for sure, but now I’m concentrating on the Faculty Building. Whatever I can do, I will. The rest will have to be on the owner… the owner has to finally assume responsibility for decisions taken on what they have. This is much more than the physical presence of Louis I. Kahn’s buildings: the Institute is associated spiritually, physically and mentally with these structures. The image of IIM Ahmedabad has always been related to Kahn’s buildings and the Institution has greatly benefited by having this architecture in the Campus. This is an added value to their own institution (compared to the other IIMs) and it has considerably come from the architectural quality of Louis Kahn’s work on the Campus. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: And this was actually the reason why he was selected in the first place…
Regarding some practical issues within the assignment, how do laws and regulations work in Ahmedabad, especially concerning heritage preservation?</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: In Mumbai we have the Heritage Conservation Committee of which we have been members for many many years and I helped with the listing of the buildings. In Mumbai we have very clear listing of Grades 1, 2 or 3, in which Grade 1 stands for the buildings which are mainly reverential buildings, Grade 2 and 2b are the next line, buildings which have to be preserved, lastly Grade 3 puts together buildings where changes can be made. In Mumbai. I have restored several Grade 1 buildings, including the St. Thomas Cathedral which is an ancient church, the Rajabai Tower and Library Building and many more. For all of them we had to go through the Heritage Committee, we had to prepare a huge amount of documentation on the history of the building and on what we were going to do and on how we were going to do our restoration. Then the Committee would come and inspect the buildings and subsequently would give us the permission to proceed with the work. At the end of the process they would come and inspect again.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Strangely enough in Ahmedabad - I don’t know… maybe now things have changed - as a 20th-century building the Campus was not listed and there was no Committee I had to present what we were doing. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: So you are basically referring to the client only…</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: That’s correct. And to the codes, which is actually the most difficult part. Codes have been addressed more seriously now, even the government is realizing that for heritage buildings it is almost impossible to apply to these codes without destroying the essence and the spirit of the original building. So how do we balance? And that is one of the reasons why, a part from our own structural engineers, we went to the Indian Institute of Technology in Madras to Dr. Arun Menon, who is a specialist in heritage connected restoration of historical masonry structures. There is a big department for that in Madras. We worked very closely with him for the Library Building to try to create that kind of balance within the intervention. The problem is also that the stability certificate for the building had to be given by the structural engineer we used and certain things he was not willing to accept. That sort of discussion and debate is also difficult. How do you manage to convince the structural engineer that what we were doing would have been right? But, in the end, he is the one that has the responsibility on giving the stability certificate. Our profession is not so simple as sometimes people think it is from the outside, and, unless you are an architect who is actually executing projects after projects, you do not perceive the inherent complexities of each assignment.  </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: At the end, the project is a matter of finding the right compromise, which is everything but easy…
Are codes mainly related to stability requirements, or do other rules refer to specific needs in terms of spaces and uses?</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: We do have those codes as well (the National Building Codes), stating for example the number of fire staircases or the number of toilets you need, but because of the existing building we have and we can create that balance in order to avoid the alteration of the original geometry. As for example, since nowadays all public buildings need to be accessible to everybody, how could we insert an elevator within the shape of the building? In other words, the issue is: how do we put the elevator without hurting the building either in plan or in the exterior? </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">There are so many challenges like that, but the biggest issues are, for sure, the seismic conservation over years and the difficulty in being able to adhere to the recent codes. And then the other thing that the Client is always asking is “how long is this going to last?”. How does anybody have an answer to that? There are so many issues to take into account… 
If you think about the City of Ahmedabad, at the same time, we have brick buildings from the 20th century which are almost collapsing, RCC buildings in bad conditions all over the place, very strong 150-years-old colonial buildings and thousand-years-old temples that are still standing. You then realize that various issues have to be considered while talking about the life of a building: how do you look after it? How do you maintain it? What happened throughout the years or the centuries? Those are just to give examples about the complexity of the matter, but, of course, nobody has all the answers, and even if somebody is professing to have them, well, that’s questionable in my opinion.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: Did you have the chance to work on other buildings built up with the same technical solution, where you have the steel reinforcement directly put in the mortar joint?</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: No, this is actually so unique. We have the steel within the brickwork, the spoiling, the flaking, the lime… so many issues put all together! Sometimes it makes me think that the 150-years-old buildings we restored in Mumbai were much easier than the IIMA. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">AR</strong>: This is why it is important to understand how the entire process of both project and construction happened in order to be aware of what you would face during the restoration.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">BS</strong>: It is also important to remember that Kahn had the opportunity to experiment in Ahmedabad (the experimental arch is still standing inside the Campus). The quality of the materials - the brick and the cement - was indeed questionable at that time. There were so many issues even at that time.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">I just feel that I have to be strong and believe that my Team will do the best they can thanks to our experience and our sensitivity to Kahn. We, for sure, want to finish the restoration of the Faculty Building and then, let just see what will go on in the future. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">But the IIMA Institution needs to understand that these buildings are not easy to maintain. It is going to cost to maintain them, even after the restoration we did and we are still in the process of completing. This is actually part of the problem, because they need to find the funds also in order to look after the buildings for the next decades. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Unfortunately, it is not just the restoration and then chapter closed. </p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Rampazzo-Somaya_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. IIMA, Faculty Block: view from the Classrooms corridor (© Alessandra Rampazzo)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Rampazzo-Somaya_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. IIMA, Faculty Block: view from the Classrooms passage (© Alessandra Rampazzo)</figcaption>
</figure>
    
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: Inkip and Gee (2012).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: William Whitaker, curator and collections manager of the Architectural Archives of the University of Pennsylvania Weitzman School of Design.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Pattison (2020).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: She is referring to what happened on 23 December, 2020 when the Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad, through a letter to its alumni, made public plans to replace (demolish and rebuild) 14 student dormitory buildings on its Campus.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: The Vikram Sarabhai Library has been awarded the Award of Distinction at the UNESCO Asia Pacific Award for Cultural Heritage Conservation 2019. The awards were announced at Penang, Malaysia on 14 October, 2019. The library was inaugurated on 11 March, 2019 after a four-years restoration process.</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Inskip, P., &amp; Gee, S. (2011). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Louis I. Kahn and the Yale Center for British Art: a conservation plan</em>. Yale Center for British Art</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Pattison, H. (2020). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Our days are like full years: a memoir with letters from Louis Kahn</em>. Yale University Press</voce>
</root>