<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">05 &quot;L’argent est autre, le climat est autre, l’âme est autre&quot;. Le Corbusier Sanskar Kendra Museum in Ahmedabad</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Elena Sofia Moretti</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Università Iuav di Venezia</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">On March 10th, 1951, while Le Corbusier was in Chandigarh, or rather, while he was working on his project for the new capital of Punjab<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>, he received a letter signed by the mayor and the Municipal Corporation of Ahmedabad, a western Indian city and capital of the state of Gujarat<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">In the letter, the architect was informed of the intention to build a museum and the willingness to offer him the commission<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>. 
Specifically, those who suggested inviting Le Corbusier to the city were Surottam Hutthesing, Gautam Sarabhai and his sister Gira, members of Ahmedabad&#x27;s most important textile entrepreneur families<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p>. The latter stood out in the Indian panorama for their culture and elegance, believing that educating the population would help modernize the city. Their patronage and the dense network of international relations with relevant figures from East and West, contributed to making Ahmedabad, in the aftermath of independence (1947), a lively laboratory of ideas, projects, and artistic experiences. In particular, the commissioning of the museum triggers an important sodality between Ahmedabad&#x27;s industrialists and Le Corbusier, leading the city to host four works by the Franco-Swiss architect: not only the museum, but the Sarabhai and Hutthesing villas and the Mill Owners Association Building<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>.
Although it is not known whether Le Corbusier knew Ahmedabad<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">6</p>, it is not surprising that he reached the city and accepted the assignment. India was offering him, as it already happened with the city of Chandigarh - seen as a realization of the Ville Radieuse model - the precious opportunity to materialize an architectural idea he had been investigating for many years.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Among the twenty-seven projects for exhibition spaces in the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Œuvre Complète</em>, it is possible to identify a sort of prototype, whose definition Le Corbusier worked on for over twenty years and which was never realized: the square spiral museum with unlimited growth<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">7</p>. Between 1928 and 1939, Le Corbusier proposed four square spiral museums: the Mundaneum in 1928<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">8</p>, the Musée des Artistes Vivants in 1930<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">9</p>, the first version of the Pavillon des Temps Nouveaux in 1936<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">10</p> and the Musée à Croissance Illimitée in 1939<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">11</p>. The Mundaneum was part of a larger project to build an ideal city near Geneva - the &quot;world city&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">12</p> – that represents the genesis of Le Corbusier&#x27;s museum prototype in which all the elements, through continuous adjustment, will lead to defining the Musée à Croissance Illimitée in 1939. The latter, which can be considered as a sort of &quot;manifesto&quot; project of his museum, is characterized by a square spiral plan developed around a central void. As the use of the spiral suggests, one of the main opportunities offered by the prototype is the ability to grow over time, in successive stages, according to the needs of the site and the economic possibilities. Knowledge as much as the museum can keep expanding, as those Le Corbusier&#x27;s square spiral building called &quot;museums of knowledge&quot; from the 20s onwards. Raised on pilotis, the building is thus three floors high, and contains a technical floor between the roof and the exhibition rooms, with installations that optimize the building&#x27;s performance by allowing natural and artificial light to enter strictly in the zenith direction. The design of the façade is marked only by the overhanging beams to accommodate possible future growth of the building. The exhibition rooms on the first floor, reachable through a ramp in the central patio, are organized around four corridors that draw a swastika in the plan and repeated on the next level through four mezzanines. It is a model that finds its first partial realization in the Ahmedabad museum and then repeated, with some variations, in Chandigarh and Tokyo.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">We must turn our attention to the Ahmedabad museum<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">13</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">A handwritten note by Le Corbusier informs us that he reached the city on March 22nd, 1951, and returned to Paris the following day<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">14</p>. Particularly helpful in reconstructing the directions given to the architect during this first meeting with the clients is a letter from Gautam Sarabhai dated March 23, 1951, describing the Museum&#x27;s future program, assumptions, and areas for each activity<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">15</p>. The planned site is an irregularly shaped lot, wider to the west and narrower to the east, close to the Sabarmati river. Sargar Bridge stands in the east and Ellis Bridge up north, which connects the 15th-century city with this new urban agglomeration developed during the colonial era.<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">16</p>. The letter is significant because it shows how Le Corbusier is not simply asked to build a museum, but a cultural center for Ahmedabad, aimed at contributing to the education and social growth of the citizens. Gautam Sarabhai&#x27;s suggestions seem to echo Le Corbusier&#x27;s previous museum projects. The idea of the museum as a powerful educational tool, a catalyst for different topics, is similar; as well as the suggestion to design a building in successive stages, to which new exhibition sections can be added over time<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">17</p>. From the very beginning, a mutual understanding between architect and client is established.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">As evidenced by the numerous drawings and sketches conserved at the Fondation Le Corbusier, one of the issues that seemed to engage the collaborators of Le Corbusier&#x27;s Parisian Atelier was the &quot;adaptation&quot; of the museum model to the specific Indian territorial conditions. Ahmedabad, in particular, is characterized by very hot and dry weather alternating with violent monsoon rains during summer. The climatic response plays a key role in the definition of the project, converting what is a prototype into a unique building, embedded in the Indian dimension both technologically and symbolically. The work on the Museum demonstrates Le Corbusier&#x27;s desire to keep these two aspects together. Thus he writes: </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">&quot;On imaginerait peut- être avece légèreté que puor répondre aux besoins d’aujourd’hui, sur cet immense territorie peuplé de cinq cent millions d’âmes, des modèles existent partout sur le monde moderne, en Europe comme aux Amériques, prêts à être copiés et multipliés. Rien de plus illusoire! L’argent est autre, le climat est autre, l’âme est autre”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">18</p>.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">If not analyzing the project several development stages, it is useful nevertheless to underline how some of the drawings Le Corbusier brought to Ahmedabad during his fourth trip in November 1952, are particularly helpful for the understanding of the direction taken by the project. Among these, the masterplan, dated 9 November 1952 and published in the fifth volume of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Œuvre Complète</em>, featuring the Museum in its first phase of growth (50x50 m), located to the west of the lot to avoid flooding from the river<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">19</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Site&#x27;s drawing shows how Le Corbusier designed not a museum but rather a cultural center, a place where all the arts seem to find their expression<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">20</p>. The land appears almost entirely occupied by volumes placed between gardens, paths, and squares. Three pavilions protrude from the main body of the Museum to the north, south, and west respectively, equivalent to three additional sections planned for the Museum (History, Anthropology, and Archaeology). To the east, an experimental theatre eventualy called  <em aid:cstyle="italic">Boîte a Miracles</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">21</p> by Le Corbusier, a library with a conference room; to the north and west, ateliers for individual and collective artists; and finally the director&#x27;s house to the south.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In this first version, the Ahmedabad Cultural Centre is presented as a new part of the city, re-proposing what was imagined in 1928 with the World City project, where his idea of a museum first appeared. The project is conceived as a citadel of institutions where the Museum is the &quot;heart&quot; of a complex of activities. In addition, the master plan shows building&#x27;s ground floor, dotted with pilotis and a pool of water in the center. Additional drawings show other floors layout, the second one presents four openings at the corners of the central patio in axis with four openings around the outer perimeter, highlighting the swastika design of the plan<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">22</p>. This matches with four mezzanines on the upper level that create breaks and interruptions in the visitor&#x27;s spiral movement<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">23</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Finally, the roof plan shows a geometric design with forty water tanks, also imagined for the volumes to be annexed to the Museum<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">24</p>. The drawing, with a grid pattern composed by the repetition of squares, suggests that Le Corbusier presumably heard about the science of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Vastu-Shastra</em> in India<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">25</p>. This is an architectural theory of settlement principles characterized by a geometric grid on the four cardinal points which regulates the construction of houses, buildings, temples, and even entire parts of cities, according to the idea of connecting physical space and cosmic movement<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">26</p>. Through the swastika on the first floor and the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Vastu-Shastra</em> on the roof, Le Corbusier hints at the rotating circulation compared to his previous projects. The spiral, despite remaining implicit, keeps being the rule for the building&#x27;s organic growth.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">At this stage, the technical plan also emerges, presented in an earlier version that Le Corbusier calls &quot;No man&#x27;s land&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">27</p>. This floor, located between the roof and the exhibition halls, becomes a sort of second cover: it allows natural and artificial light to enter and, at the same time, an air chamber, an additional insulator to the water tanks on the roof.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">As in the previous versions, the façades are characterized by the extension of the beams, suggesting the subsequent growth of the Museum and also conceived as a possible anchorage point for plants supposed to better insulate the building<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">28</p>. Although it is not specified what material Le Corbusier planned to use for wall cladding, the fact that he draws a geometric system of rectangular slabs with aligned joints is a further element that pinpoints the character of the façade as a single applied and removable element.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the final drawings, sent to Ahmedabad in February 1953, although the floor plans do not change significantly, they are clarified by additional details<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">29</p>. The ground floor undergoes some adjustments: the water basin has a sinuous shape and is surrounded by a ring of pilotis of the same height as the ground floor, to which three more columns of greater height are added, reaching to the roof. When visitors enter the patio on a rainy day, the water – which falls copiously from the roof during the summer months – descends into the basin on the ground through three downpipes, shaping three further water columns, giving rise to the final layout of this space (fig. 2).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The roof is also defined<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">30</p>. In its final version, it is walkable through a platform that encircles the central patio and presents forty-five water tanks which Le Corbusier imagines covered with flowers and vegetation, offering a spectacle of multicolored pools that seems to evoke the Mughal gardens of Indian tradition<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">31</p> {fig. 3). It is relevant to emphasize that in Ahmedabad the constructions to collect water are different and very impressive: the arid climate has made it necessary to imagine solutions to catch and store water such as tanks, wells, and cisterns. Moreover, water also plays an important role in the Indian religious culture (Muslim and Hindu), characterizing numerous places of worship and prayer. During his travels, Le Corbusier was fascinated by the relationship between inhabitants and water, recognizing in the basins or in the river flowing through Ahmedabad, the city&#x27;s main urban space. The design of the roof allows to read Le Corbusier&#x27;s desire to offer the Museum visitors a collective place, a way to rediscover their unique relationship with water.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The drawings for the Museum give the idea of a building composed of several overlapping “skins”: plants, water, concrete, and finally the “No man&#x27;s land&quot;, which lets the building “breathe”. The solutions developed for the Museum show the architect&#x27;s response to specific territorial conditions, but also the building&#x27;s strong connection to the local tradition of a country like India, whose culture deeply influenced Le Corbusier’s imagery. The type around which he had been working since 1928 now appears deformed and reshaped for the Indian natural and cultural context. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Once the final plans were delivered on 27 February 1953, the correspondence at the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Fondation Le Corbusier</em> opens a new chapter in the history of the Indian Museum: its construction<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">32</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The construction site events are marked by the arrival of new protagonists. First, the young French architect Jean Louis Véret, who arrived in Ahmedabad in June 1953 to supervise the works designed by Le Corbusier; and later by Balkrishna Doshi, who from 1955 became the studio&#x27;s main interlocutor<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">33</p>. Véret had previously supervised the single projects for Ahmedabad while at the Atelier in rue de Sèvres, and his signature is on the final drawings for the Museum with collaborators Andrée Maisonnier and Kujawsky Oleck<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">34</p>. As proved by the correspondence available at the Fondation Le Corbusier, the beginning of the Museum&#x27;s construction was delayed, as a matter of fact the foundation stone is laid on April 9, 1953<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">35</p>). Anyway, the Museum one appeared to be the most easily managed by  Véret, at least in its phases. It is possible to suppose that the Museum&#x27;s prototype nature and its popularity in the Atelier, as well as Veret&#x27;s involvement in the production of the final drawings, helped to proceed with the construction with more confidence. Moreover, the use of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Modulor</em> model, theorized by Le Corbusier in 1948, proves to be one of the most useful tools the studio uses to &quot;governs&quot; the numerous construction sites from distance<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">36</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The number of correspondence related to the construction of the Museum is meager, as is the presence of detail drawings until 1955 (when the construction site came under Doshi&#x27;s supervision). However, some of Véret&#x27;s photographs taken in the summer of 1954 and preserved in the Archives of the Institut Francais d&#x27;Architecture in Paris (IFA) are particularly useful for reconstructing what was accomplished in this first phase. Photographs document the construction of the foundations and circular columns on the ground floor, cast with 1.40-m wide metal formwork, where the assembly creates staggered joints as in a stone masonry.<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">37</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The exchanges with the studio also make it possible to investigate the young Véret&#x27;s autonomy and the control of the site by the Parisian atelier. The correspondence reveals the difficulty of the collaborators and Le Corbusier in responding quickly to Véret&#x27;s doubts about the construction, even though there never was any independent initiative by the young architect. As a result, the construction site was sometimes suspended temporarily while waiting for answers from Paris. It is also possible to assume that many of the unreplied questions and requests in the correspondence, were resolved directly by Le Corbusier himself on-site during his travels.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">As already mentioned, Véret left Ahmedabad in January 1955 to return to Paris. Nonetheless, before his departure he makes another photographic campaign to document the progress of the work<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">38</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">A series of photographs taken in January 1955 show the ongoing construction of the building&#x27;s second level; others, dating from December 1954, testify to Le Corbusier&#x27;s visit to the site. Some of these capture Véret and Le Corbusier arguing in front of the building under construction, while others indicate the presence of Doshi, who is presumably being briefed on what has been done so far. This is a significant moment in setting the future development of the site, where Véret and Doshi are working closely together throughout January<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">39</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">On January 25, Doshi finally replaced Véret and proceeded with the next phase of construction, which included the building envelope and the installation of windows and doors.<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">40</p>. We also have information about the material chosen to clad the façade, that is local handmade bricks arranged end-to-end forming a regular grid with aligned joints, as Le Corbusier had imagined in previous projects. This solution enables the architect to formally mark the reinforced concrete load-bearing structure, which is also emphasized by the presence of beams protruding from the envelope in both the internal patio and the external façades.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The correspondence between the studio and Doshi at the Fondation Le Corbusier once again allows us to investigate the progress of the construction site and the independence granted to the young supervisor. If at first Le Corbusier exercised much control over Doshi&#x27;s work, later he will recognize his professional maturity, inviting him to take responsibility for the choices made on the site<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">41</p>. This is a decisive step in the history of the construction of the Museum. From now on, Doshi will have more autonomy in the construction phases, taking charge of designing specific solutions, always under Le Corbusier&#x27;s consent. From this point of view, the Museum seems to stand out from all the other buildings made in Ahmedabad and completed more quickly, offering a test bench for Doshi&#x27;s debut as an autonomous architect (although documenting and identifying his specific interventions is sometimes difficult)<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">42</p>. However, it is possible to suppose that the continuous delays suffered by the construction site, the Municipal Corporation&#x27;s desire to complete the Museum more and more independently, and the impossibility of shaping the entire urban project, also led Le Corbusier to gradually move away from the project. The lively plan presented to the authorities in November 1952 would not be realized, nor would the additional sections of the Museum be built.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the last communications between Doshi and the studio, Le Corbusier delegates to him all decisions about the building. This suggests, due to the lack of communication about the outcome of the construction, that Doshi completed the building alone in the first half of 1957<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">43</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">During the 1960s the Museum seemed to experience a fortunate period in its history, as a landmark in the life of the city. However, as early as the 1970s and 1980s it begins to experience a gradual decline, taking on uses unsuited to its original function. In the 1990s the building the Municipal Corporation finally decided to start a new layout project involving partial restoration<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">44</p>. But insufficient funds led to only occasional interventions, while the set-up project was made possible by donations from citizens themselves.  </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Today, the building exhibit is in a state of deep deterioration, as can be seen, for example, in the cladding and the remaining parts of concrete - whose reinforcements are partially exposed - 
and manifests the urgency of immediate action. </p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Moretti_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. Le Corbusier, Ahmedabad Museum, General Plan of the Complex, 1952, November 9 (FLC 6946). (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Moretti_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. Le Corbusier, Ahmedabad Museum, Roof plan, 1953, February 25 (FLC 6972). (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Moretti_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. Ahmedabad Museum, internal patio. (© MIT, photograph by G.E. Kidder Smith)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Moretti_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. Ahmedabad Museum, photo of the outside (FLC R3-8-67). (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
    
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: Kalia (1987), Papillault (2011).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: Leone (2013, pp. 7-16), Serenyi (1983, pp. 91-118), Pandya (2002), Doshi (2000) and Doshi (2012a).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Chairman, Recreational and Cultural Committée, Municipal corporation, Ahmedabad. (1951, March 10). [letter to Le Corbusier]. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P3-4-15/18), Fondation Le Corbusier (from now on FLC), Paris, France. 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: Gautam and Gira are two of the eight sons of Ambalal Sarabhai who have owned the Calico Mills since 1881. During their formative years, they traveled in Europe and America, developing and enriching their culture (Alessandrini, 2012, p. 161). On the peculiarities of the entrepreneurial class in Ahmedabad see: Curtis (1986, p. 202), Nanda (1991, pp. 26-38), Tripathi (1981), and Williamson (2016).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: There are actually five works designed by Le Corbusier in Ahmedabad. The fifth work, the Chinubhai Chimabhai&#x27;s house, was never built (Le Corbusier, 1952, pp. 163-164).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">6</p>: In Le Corbusier&#x27;s library there is a book that he received from his aunt Pauline in 1909 that contains three images of Ahmedabad (O&#x27;Byrne Orozco, 2015, p. 11).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">7</p>: On the museums see De Smet (2019).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">8</p>: Le Corbusier (1937, pp. 190-197).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">9</p>: Le Corbusier (1934, p. 72-73) and Le Corbusier (1931, pp. 25-28). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">10</p>: Published in the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Œuvre Complète</em> under the name of: &quot;Project C. Un centre d&#x27;esthétique contemporaine&quot; (Le Corbusier, 1939, pp. 152-155).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">11</p>: Le Corbusier (1946, pp. 16-21) and Ragot (1987, p. 267).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">12</p>: Gresleri and Matteoni (1982), Fagiolo (1978, pp. 22-29) and O’Byrne Orozco (2004).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">13</p>: The most recent studies on Le Corbusier&#x27;s Ahmedabad Museum have been conducted by Maria Cecilia O&#x27;Byrne Orozco in the third chapter of her Ph.D. thesis (2015).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">14</p>: Le Corbusier. (1951, March 17). [Handwritten note]. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P2-5-24), FLC, Paris, France. Le Corbusier&#x27;s trips to Ahmedabad correspond to his visits to Chandigarh, where he is contractually required to go twice a year. There are seven documented visits to Ahmedabad by Le Corbusier, although there is evidence in the correspondence of the organization of an eighth visit, see: Le Corbusier. (1956, March 6). [Letter to Doshi]. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P3-6-416/P3-6-422), FLC, Paris, France. However, there is no clear documentation about this trip. It is possible to assume that Le Corbusier did not spend more than one day in the city on this occasion.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">15</p>: Sarabhai, G. (1951, March 23). Proposal for the Municipal Museum of Ahmedabad. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P3-4-16), FLC, Paris, France. The Travel Carnets are also an essential source of Le Corbusier&#x27;s impressions during his first visit to Ahmedabad, in which he sketches and notes various types of information (Le Corbusier, 1981, E18-350 and 358).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">16</p>: Doshi (2000, p. 92). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">17</p>: The Museum would initially have seven sections: Archaeology of the region, Indian Art (painting and sculpture), the Art of Everyday Life, Natural History, Indian Anthropology, and a library. 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">18</p>: Le Corbusier. (1951, December 28). [article by Le Corbusier for &quot;Le Bulletin indien de l&#x27;Indépendance&quot;]. Variuos Essays, Article 1951 (U3-7-212), FLC, Paris, France. 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">19</p>: Le Corbusier. (1952, November 4). AM 4496. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (6946), FLC, Paris, France. In the early stages of the project, Le Corbusier planned to locate the Museum to the east of the lot, near the Sabarmati river. After studying solutions to contrast possible flooding, this option was abandoned.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">20</p>: The project for the Ahmedabad Citizens Centre was presented at the eighth Ciam in Hoddesdon, focusing on the topic &quot;the heart of the city&quot; (Le Corbusier, 1954, p. 52).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">21</p>: The Boite a Miracles is an external and internal theatre of the same time, which Le Corbusier published in the five-volume of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Œuvre Complète</em> and which we will find again in Chandigarh and Tokyo (1952, p. 161). On the Miracle Box see in particular: O&#x27;Byrne Orozco (2008).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">22</p>: Le Corbusier. (1952, November 9). AM 4518 Plan niveau 3. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (6948), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">23</p>: The figure of the swastika seems to be strongly re-proposed in the project, as a very ancient figure found in many cultures, India included. With its four arms extending towards the cardinal points, it represents the movement of the sun in the sky. Le Corbusier seems to reflect on this symbolic figure in his carnet (1981, 855).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">24</p>: Le Corbusier. (1952, November 9). AM 4520 Plan niveau 6. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (6950), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">25</p>: This is confirmed by Doshi to O&#x27;Byrne Orozco in his doctoral thesis (2015).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">26</p>: Shukla (1995).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">27</p>: Le Corbusier. (1952, November 9). AM 4521 Coupe. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (6951), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">28</p>: Le Corbusier. (1952, Nivember 9). AM 4522 Façade. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (6952), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">29</p>: Le Corbusier. (1953, February 10). AM 4565 Niveau 2. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (6953), FLC, Paris, France. 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">30</p>: Le Corbusier. (1953, February 25). AM 4623 Plan vue d’avion. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (6972), FLC, Paris, France. 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">31</p>: See Moynihan (1979). The volumes containing the lift systems appear on the roof like small pavilions in a garden.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">32</p>: The final drawings are twenty-one plans including the general plan of the complex, plans, sections, façades, and detailed drawings of the lift systems. On the construction see in particular: Gargiani and Rosellini (2011, pp. 379-389). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">33</p>: Jean Louis Véret (1927-2011) met Le Corbusier in Paris, probably at the end of 1951, when he was presenting his final project at the Ecole des Beaux-Arts. After starting and supervising construction work in Ahmedabad, he returned to Paris and in 1958 and founded the Atelier Montrouge with three colleagues, which he ran until 1981. Balkrishna Doshi was born in 1927 in Pune, in the Indian state of Maharashtra. His meeting with Le Corbusier took place at the VIII Ciam in Hoddesdon. After working in Le Corbusier&#x27;s studio in Paris, he was first sent to Chandigarh to supervise the High Court building, and then to Ahmedabad for the final stages of the construction of the architect&#x27;s four works. At the end of the collaboration, Doshi decided to settle in Ahmedabad to start his independent work. On the work with Le Corbusier see: Doshi (2012a), Doshi (2012b), and Doshi (2012c).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">34</p>: In the construction site correspondence between Véret and the studio&#x27;s collaborators, the figure of Jacques Michel also emerges. Michel who, with Maisonnier, will be the main person in charge of providing, under Le Corbusier&#x27;s supervision, solutions, plans, and drawings for the development of the site.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">35</p>: The telegram announcing the laying of the first stone was received by Le Corbusier on 12 April 1954. see: Chinubahi, C. (1954, April 5). [Telegram to Le Corbusier]. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P3-4-168), FLC, Paris, France. On this day, in the lot where the Cultural center would be built, Véret with Le Corbusier organized an exhibition with twelve explanatory panels, a model, and an informative brochure to present the project to the citizens.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">36</p>: The Modulor model, from the Unité d&#x27;Habitation in Marseilles (1949-1952), start to be used in all Le Corbusier&#x27;s subsequent projects (Le Corbusier, 1974; Curtis, 1986, pp. 162-174).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">37</p>: Gargiani and Rosellini (2011, pp. 379-389). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">38</p>: Véret, J.L. (1954, November 27). [Letter to Michel]. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P3-6-92), FLC, Paris, France. 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">39</p>: Doshi leaves numerous testimonies about his work with Le Corbusier, elevated to the figure of a &quot;guru&quot;, grateful for the work he had done with the architect first in Paris and then in India (Doshi, 1992; Pandya, 2002; Mellotto, 2014). Also, Véret will always keep this high educational experience in mind, so much so that he returned to Ahmedabad in the 1980s to visit the buildings again, as some of the photographs in the IFA&#x27;s collection betray.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">40</p>: These respond to the questions that had remained unresolved up until then, which mainly concerned the designs for the &quot;Pan de Verre&quot; and those relating to the volumes on the ground floor, such as the shop at the entrance to the Museum.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">41</p>: In a letter from Le Corbusier to Doshi dated 21 May 1955 he writes: &quot;vous etes très gentil de me demander tous ces détails mais ce sont des choses que vous pouvez liquider fort bien vous-meme, sur place, avec le gout de vos clients et votre gout, sans me trahir&quot;. Le Corbusier. (1955, May 21). [Letter to Doshi]. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (G2-18-463), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">42</p>: On November 12, 1955, Le Corbusier sent a letter to the city council, listing the missing work, and indicating that Doshi would be responsible for it. See: Le Corbusier. (1955, May 21). [Letter to City Council]. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P3-4-157), FLC, Paris, France. The last communications between Doshi and Le Corbusier about the Museum took place between December 1956 and April 1957. This leads one to suppose that it the presumably completed in early 1957.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">43</p>: The project for the Ahmedabad Museum had been published in the fifth volume of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Œuvre Complète</em> (Le Corbusier, 1952, pp. 160-161). The sixth volume also published the building with a series of photographs taken by Doshi in October 1956, at which time the Museum was still under construction, as opposed to the villas and the museum is named after Sanskar Kendra, the first mayor of the city of Ahmedabad (Le Corbusier, 1957, pp. 158-167).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">44</p>: The story of the life of the Museum was told by the architect Yatin Pandya in Ahmedabad in an interview given to the writer in April 2019. Pandya informs that he had been in charge of the restoration project of the building in the early 2000s. However, due to a lack of funds, these operations were limited to the severely deteriorated structures and the removal of all additions that did not comply with the original design, such as shutters and partitions. Pandya was also responsible for fitting out the Museum halls, which can still be seen today.</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Alessandrini, E. (2012). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Ahmedabad. Laboratorio di architettura moderna. Il National Institute of Design (1961-68) fra contatti internazionali ed echi della tradizione</em> [phdthesis]. Alma Mater Studiorum - Università di Bologna. https://doi.org/10.6092/unibo/amsdottorato/4715</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Curtis, W. J. R. (1986). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier: Ideas and Form</em>. Phaidon</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>De Smet, C. (2019). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier penseur du musée</em>. Flammarion. Retrieved April 12, 2022, from https://livre.fnac.com/a13545282/Catherine-De-Smet-Le-Corbusier-penseur-du-musee</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Doshi, B. V. (2000). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Architectural Legacies of Ahmedabad, Canvas of Modern Masters</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Doshi, B. V. V. (2012). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier and Louis I. Kahn. The Acrobat and the Yogi of Architecture</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Doshi, B. V. (2012a). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier. The Indian Incarnation</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Doshi, B. V. (2012b). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier’s Work: A Personal Reading</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Fagiolo, M. (1978). Mundaneum 1929, La nuova Babilonia secondo Le Corbusier. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Ottagono</em> (48)</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Gargiani, R., &amp; Rosellini, A. (2011). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier: Béton Brut and Ineffable Space, 1940-1965</em>. EPFL Press</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Gresleri, G., &amp; Matteoni, D. (1982). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>La Città Mondiale: Andersen, Hébrard, Otlet, Le Corbusier</em>. Polis Marsilio</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Kalia, R. (1987). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Chandigarh: In Search of an Identity</em>. Southern Illinois University Press</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1935). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier \&amp; Pierre Jeanneret, Œuvre complète: 1929-1934</em> (Vol. 2). Girsberger</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1937). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier \&amp; Pierre Jeanneret, Œuvre complète: 1910-1929</em> (Vol. 1). Girsberger</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1939). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier \&amp; Pierre Jeanneret, Œuvre complète: 1934-1938</em> (Vol. 3). Girsberger</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1947). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier \&amp; Pierre Jeanneret, Œuvre complète: 1938-1946</em> (Vol. 4). Girsberger</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1953). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier \&amp; Pierre Jeanneret, Œuvre complète: 1946-1952</em> (Vol. 5). Girsberger</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1954). Il cuore della città punto di incontro delle arti. In E. N. Rogers, J. L. Sert, &amp; J. Tyrwhitt (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Il Cuore della Città: per una vita più umana delle comunità</em> (pp. 52). Hoepli</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1957). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier \&amp; Pierre Jeanneret, Œuvre complète: 1952-1957</em> (Vol. 6). Artemis</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1981). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Carnets 2, 1950-1954</em>. Electa</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Leone, G. (2013). Ahmedabad. In M. Biraghi, &amp; A. Ferlenga (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Architettura del Novecento</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>: Vol. 2</em> (pp. 7–16). Einaudi</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Moynihan, E. B. (1979). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Paradise as a Garden: in Persia and Mughal India</em>. George Braziller</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Nanda, V. (1991). Urbanism, Tradition and Continuity in Ahmedabad. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Mimar</em> (38), 26–36</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>O&#39;Byrne Orozco, M. C. (2004). El museo del Mundaneum: génesis de un prototipo. In <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Massilia: annuaire d&#39;etudes corbuseenes</em>. Associacio d&#39;idees.</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>O&#39;Byrne Orozco, M. C. (2008). La Boîte á Miracles en el centro cultural de Ahmadabad. In <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Massilia: anuario de estudios lecorbusierianos. Encuentro de Granda</em>. Fondation Le Corbusier.</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>O&#39;Byrne Orozco, M. C. (2015). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>El Proyecto para el Hospital de Venecia de Le Corbusier</em> [phdthesis]. Universidad Politécnica de Cataluña</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Pandya, Y. (2002). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>The Ahmedabad Chronicle, Imprints of a Millennium</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Papillault, R. (2011). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Chandigarh et Le Corbusier: création d&#39;une ville en Inde, 1950-1965</em>. Éd. Poiesis-AERA</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Ragot, G. (1987). Musée à croissance illimité. In J. Lucan (Ed.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier, une encyclopédie</em> (pp. 267). Centre Georges Pompidou</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Serenyi, P. (1983). Timeless but of Its Time: Le Corbusier&#39;s Architecture in India. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Perspecta</em> (20), 91–118</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Tripathi, D. (1981). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>The Dynamics of a Tradition: Kasturbhai Lalbhai and his Entrepreneurship</em>. Manohar</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Williamson, D. (2016). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Modern Architecture and Capitalist Patronage in Ahmedabad, India 1947-1969</em> [phdthesis]. New York University</voce>
</root>