<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">07 Steel like straw. The Case of the Indian Institute of Management in Ahmedabad Designed by Louis I. Kahn</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Alessandra Rampazzo</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Università Iuav di Venezia</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">Designed by Louis I. Kahn (1901-1974) between 1962 and 1974, the Indian Institute of Management in Ahmedabad (IIMA) is considered to be one of the mature works of the Estonian-American architect.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">However, when Kahn first arrived in Ahmedabad in 1962, he was a mature architect at the height of his career and the city itself has already become a place of academic excellence for the Country thanks to important experiences of main protagonists of 20th-century architecture, such as Frank Lloyd Wright and Le Corbusier.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The particular setting, together with the properties of the available building materials and the nature of the professional assignment, which initially involved Kahn only as a consultant, challenged the architect with new and unparalleled questions particularly concerning the management of a &quot;remote&quot; construction site in a Country where he was not familiar with tradition and construction methods.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The geographical distance between India and the United States contributes to lengthen the time of the decisional process until it became the reason why specific solutions – technical more than compositive – have been adopted, being then the cause of the actual conditions of the buildings.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Looking at the Campus and its peculiar elements, the problem has indeed to be found directly within the construction itself, so then all recent make-up interventions on the exterior facades have been useless and not decisive (see fig. 2).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Considering this, in 2014 the IIMA decided to launch a significant restoration process with the publication of the Request for Proposals (RFP) and the consequent selection of Somaya &amp; Kalappa Consultants office from Mumbai as Conservation Architects with the task of protecting the integrity of the Louis Kahn Campus Complex.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The actual conditions of degradation of the buildings raise questions on responsibilities for design and technical choices taken during the construction phase, which suggest then to take a step back and deeply look into the entire process.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the aftermath of India’s independence conquered in 1947, the important entrepreneurial families related to textile industries, thanks also to their connections with the United States, brought to the Gujarati city of Ahmedabad significant cultural and educational institutions, born as part of a broader program of economic, political and cultural reorganization developed by Jawaharlal Nehru, Prime Minister of the new India. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">According to him, social progress was closely linked to the general level of education of the population which in turn depended on the offer guaranteed by the State. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The same interest in the topic of education as social problem indeed involved not only the Central state, but also the other protagonists – the State of Gujarat, the Ford Foundation and the Sarabhai’s and Lalbhai’s families – who played an important role in the process of founding the National Institute of Design (NID) that came first in 1960, followed the year after by the Indian Institute of Management in Ahmedabad (IIMA), inspired by the organization of the American Harvard Business School (HBS).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">All these things together ensure the involvement of the NID, established with the specific aim of training local architects through the collaboration of international professionals, in the design of the Institute of the Management. The commission was then assigned to the NID. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Elected Trusted Architect by the influential industrial families of Ahmedabad for completing the Le Corbusier’s Indian construction site, it was then Balkrishna V. Doshi, who suggested Louis I. Kahn as Consultant Architect<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Finally, in 1962, Gautam Sarabhai, president of the newly born NID, asked Kahn to participate as a Consultant Teacher in the project for IIMA financed by the Indian Government with the assistance of the Ford Foundation and HBS. As Gautam Sarabhai recalled, the project aimed &quot;to provide a useful learning opportunity not only in theory but in practice for the Institute’s staff and apprentices&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>. The letter sent to Kahn on April, 1962, specified the terms of the assignment in detail: the expected duration of three years would include three or four site visits, while the drawings were supposed to be made exclusively in Ahmedabad by the architects of NID.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">For Kahn, therefore, the commission is just a consultancy. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">But what has this meant for Kahn? This particular collaboration was so unusual for him to the point that he perceived it as a limit to his possibilities when compared to the working method already tested in his Philadelphia office.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The control during the construction phase has always been decisive for reaching the same Order that lays as the base of his architectural research.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Considering this, Kahn suggested some changes in order to carry out his service as architect in the best possible way. He stressed the importance of his constant involvement during the design and building process. For this reason, the number of visits provided for in the agreement should have been increased to at least six. In addition, &quot;the time of these visits and duration of stay&quot;, clarified Kahn, &quot;must be left to my judgement&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>.  </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">After this preliminary negotiation, the conception of the project started, revealing step by step Kahn’s difficult acceptance of the imposed role. During the entire process, he would work indeed in order to centralize within his figure all the decisions and responsibilities regarding the design of the IIMA.   </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Five months after the first proposed appointment received from NID’s President, Kahn finally made his first trip to Ahmedabad between 5 and 18 November, 1962 to work on the general layout of the Campus supported by the architects of the National Institute of Design.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The general idea of a new school was based on the distinction in three functional areas of the plan – the school, the dormitories and the residences –, followed the method adopted for the first time in the project of the Salk Institute<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p> and also later on in Dhaka<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">This solution responded to the idea of architecture understood as research about institutions, which Kahn presented in the closing speech of the CIAM Congress in Otterlo in 1959 and therefore took as a key principle in the design of the Ahmedabad Institute.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">After resolving the configuration of the central body as an educational fortress<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">6</p>, the dormitories for the students were then positioned precisely aligned along the north-south direction that came off at 45° from the school building, consequently allowing an adequate orientation of the rooms in the direction of the prevailing breezes. The buildings significantly stretched out towards the body of water that surrounded them in the plan forming an L-shape, separating the public life of the students from the private one of the professors. The housing sector dedicated to teachers and staffs is then closing the geometrical composition in plan on the opposite side of the lake.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Climatic factors together with the contrast between light and shadow became the real protagonists of the structure. On the occasion of his first trip to India, thanks also to Doshi’s advice, Kahn devoted himself to a careful research on the correct orientation of the single units of the complex so that these characteristics could be best exploited. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">This has been the reason why the masterplan rotated three times before reaching its final orientation in June, 1964.
From this moment on, the architects of the NID started detailing each building of the complex.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The Indian Institute of Management represents the synthesis of the architect’s work. Kahn’s projects stand out for the accuracy of the geometry that regulates plans and elevations, for the crucial role played by light in the definition of spaces and for the significance of the Institution as the founding idea of the project. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">More in detail, Kahn’s cuts through the volumes, following again a diagonal tracing, emptied the corners of the rectangular geometry metaphorically recalling the image of ancient ruins, in the same way as the power of the material used, the brick, together with the construction details.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Admittedly, at the time the use of brick as building material was a field not yet fully explored. In fact, until then Kahn used bricks almost exclusively as &quot;cladding&quot; material with limited structural capacity except those related to their own load, such as for the south wall of the Yale Art Gallery (completed in 1953), the service towers of the Richards Medical Research Building in Philadelphia (1960), and the outer shell of the Unitary Church complex in Rochester (1963). </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Also, those bricks had material and workmanship characteristics significantly different from what was available in India.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Indeed, the brick used by Kahn in the American structures mentioned above was a machine-cut, rectified and perfect product of an industry that in those years was already completely mechanized, in order to minimize dimensional and chromatic variations. Therefore, through the study of brick bonds and the right calibration of the joints, brick walls had a completely homogeneous form, which, in this case, was well suited to satisfy the demands of the poetics of architecture where nothing was left to chance and everything responded to the control of the project. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">According to these ideas, the identifying image of the Campus was then achieved through homogeneous masses of bricks, interrupted only by the concrete used for few horizontal elements, such as chain beams and slabs, and for the staircases. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Once this was defined, Kahn’s return to Philadelphia indicated the true beginning of this unusual collaboration marked by daily transmission of information using the means available at the time, which were letters, telegrams, annotated drawings and, more rarely, telephone calls<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">7</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In this complex process Doshi played a central role as he was responsible on behalf of both the client and the architect for the success of the project in its various phases. During the seven years (1962-1969) of collaboration with NID, the documents showed how Kahn continually turned to Doshi for a critical evaluation of the project.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The complex handing over of documents just described, together with the difficulties encountered by Kahn in transmitting his ideas in the absence of direct contact with employees, created a time expansion that marked the decision-making process. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">This was what the newborn Institute worried about the most since their concern was to be able to welcome the first students enrolled in accordance with the request of the central government which financed the project.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Despite these complications and delays, the construction started in October, 1964 with two buildings – one students’ dormitory (D12) and one staff’s house (Residence 501) – used as samples. 
Kahn waited until December, 1964, for his first site visit.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">It was undoubtedly of fundamental importance for the future development of the construction and, more generally, of the project. Indeed, crucial decisions were taken during that visit which represented a real turning point in the design process aimed at bringing together the theoretical assumptions with the practical aspects of a construction managed from a distance. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The construction had reached a height of about 2 m and had begun under the direction of the NID operative team with the collaboration of Doshi in the manner that was traditionally used on site. Moreover, Doshi had already had the opportunity to follow Le Corbusier’s construction site in Ahmedabad and therefore he started the works on IIMA’s building site with the methodology he had acquired during the construction he had followed alongside the French-Swiss master. </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">But the construction of the Indian Institute of Management appeared to be a completely new experience compared to the one he already had. In fact, Doshi described how: &quot;During the initial stages, not realizing that Lou is not Corbusier, we built all the brick foundations of the dormitory blocks in the manner we had done for Corbusier’s projects. On his arrival, he somehow concealed his disappointment on seeing our work. And he worked almost 18 hours a day for a whole week at the site guiding the masons how to make a brick wall or a brick buttress or a brick arch&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">8</p>.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">The result was therefore unacceptable for Kahn. Let’s go into detail. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">One of the major problems Kahn noticed when looking at the brick walls was the constant but irregular presence of a queen closer – a quarter of a brick – near the end of the wall. This technique was traditionally used to solve the gap between the header and the stretcher courses near the vertical edge of the wall (see fig. 3). </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">However, in the buildings in Ahmedabad the sequence of these smaller bricks emerged as a disturbing factor that altered the perception of the brickwork as a homogeneous <em aid:cstyle="italic">unicum</em> and expression of a single volume, undermining the researched Order.
In such a way an apparently visual problem became a technical one.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In this regard, the solution was found precisely with the construction of the Sample Yard<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">9</p>. For an entire week the architects in charge of NID worked on the design of the single parts that were to compose this explanatory model. What established in its construction had to be followed in detail on site.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The Sample Yard included two sections of 1½ brick wall built up to a height of one meter to show the correct method of execution for both brick bonds – English and Flemish – so as to avoid the presence of a queen closer placed at the end of the brick wall. Through the use of the ¾ bat it was possible to adapt the modularity of the brick to the dimensions of the project without altering the natural arrangement of the bond which maintained the characteristic alternation of header-stretcher-header on the same course. The Flemish-style bond, thus approved, became the new basic postulate and every single part of IIMA derived its own peculiarities from that. Each characterizing element found a place in the Sample Yard – the arch, the semicircular wall, the 10&quot; thick (about 25 cm) wall, the depressed arch with a reinforced concrete tie, the 1½ brick wall to enclose a rectangular space, the flat arch, a section of outdoor paving and also two electrical boxes- even the way to execute the mortar joint, in order to solve the issue of its substantial thickness due to the irregular shape and dimensions of the bricks, which were produced with a traditional handmade process in the surroundings of Ahmedabad. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The evident lack of homogeneity between the vertical and horizontal joints once again convinced Kahn to look for possible alternative solutions. He then took into consideration the American construction sites and, in particular, the American colonial tradition<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">10</p> where the use of mortar joints, both horizontally and vertically, was characterized by an incision made with a special metal tool, which he brought with him to India directly from the US.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The choice of module and material (and of the way of using them) led to a vocabulary that was decisive for the success of the project: &quot;Design demands that one understands the order&quot;, explained Kahn, &quot;when you are dealing, or designing in brick, you must ask brick what it wants, or what it can do&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">11</p>.
The experience of the Sample Yard was indeed a turning point in the design technique of the entire project. The dimensional data of the elements, in their most traditional form of proportions, disappeared from the tables – or when present they were just accessory data – in favor of indicating the number of courses or modular elements (the brick) and their exact position in the configuration.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The construction proceeded then according to the rules and language established during Kahn’s first visit to the building site, but the design of main school building (the Main Complex) was still in progress<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">12</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The initial forecast of concluding the project and the construction of IIMA by 1966 was thus eluded during the course of the events as inevitable consequence of a long-distance collaboration. Furthermore, the delay in the construction of the complex appeared to be caused by Kahn’s insistence to control every aspect of the project despite the geographical distance<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">13</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">However, the dedication to the work and the project did not fully satisfy the mainly economic needs of the client who in 1969, six years after making the assignment, decided to reconsider the method adopted until then in order to speed up the procedure to complete the Campus.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">This concluded the collaboration with NID and its staff of architects as well as the first phase of the project. The architect chosen by Kahn to complete the IIMA project was then Anant D. Raje, who had worked in Doshi’s Vastu Shilpa studio for several years, before going to Philadelphia for five years from 1964 to 1969, when he returned to Ahmedabad on Kahn’s request precisely to follow the IIMA project. A Site Office directed by Raje was established in the Campus and his presence thus inaugurated a new and different phase of the project. Despite the geographical distance that separated Kahn from the construction site, the already established relationship with Raje laid the foundations for a more relaxed collaboration.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Because of the geometrical and volumetric characteristics, the new buildings of the Main Complex required further checks from the structural point of view. The core, already defined compositionally, &quot;have large spans, are high, and have stretches of walls with large unsupported lengths and heights&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">14</p> and for these reasons it was necessary to structurally reinforce the walls to create a ‘monolithic’ behavior between the vertical elements and the horizontal floors, and to guarantee the whole system the necessary resistance to the horizontal forces generated by an earthquake.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The first hypothesis proposed by the engineers relieved the masonry from its initial load-bearing role and transferred the loads to a reinforced concrete frame structure which was then incorporated into the masonry. Although Kahn had adopted a similar solution in the Exeter Library<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">15</p>, in Ahmedabad he categorically refused to combine two different building systems preferring to preserve the nature of the masonry as a structural element. Therefore, the only effective solution consisted in building a reinforced masonry which meant to insert steel bars inside the brickwork.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Raje knew that this technique, in the way it was already used in the Indian context, appeared completely alien to the idea of honesty in the use of the material repeatedly expressed by Kahn<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">16</p>. Despite his awareness of Kahn’s mindset regarding this issue, he had to identify five different possible solutions, from the quickest and economic to make to the most coherent one, which, however, would have introduced a further problem, since the full exposure of the concrete frame underlined by the presence of the metal reinforcement, would have significantly changed the external appearance of the brick wall, comparing to what it was built until that stage. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">According to Kahn, technique, economics and other ‘circumstantial’ factors should have left space for Architecture. This had generally happened in Ahmedabad up to that moment thanks to the trust and respect the Indian architects showed towards Khan. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Considering this, it was unexpected that, in his answer to Raje, Kahn showed a new &quot;common sense&quot; accepting the cheapest solution even if less &quot;honest&quot; from an architectural point of view. He said: </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">&quot;Altogether, let me say that I am practical enough to see the point of view that the effectiveness of the steel within the wall begins to look to me like straw or cow-hair that reinforces old plaster and I am quite willing to give in to what would keep the job going without undue effort because we are already so far behind [the schedule]&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">17</p>.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">What appears here as a passive acceptance of the most advantageous solution in terms of money, and especially time, can probably be traced back to the particular moment when this decision was taken. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">If in the Dhaka construction site Kahn had proven to know the correct way of building reinforced masonry, the obvious time delay needs here to be taken into account and the pressure put by Lalbhai played a significant role in the decision to endorse a simpler technical execution while trying to assign to this technique the principles that had governed the project until then.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the letter to Raje cited above, Kahn accompanied the explanation with an explicit reference to tradition: &quot;the effectiveness of the steel within the wall begins to look to me like straw or cow-hair that reinforces old plaster&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">18</p>. According to this original interpretation, the masonry then again became a combination of only two elements, the brick and the binder, with a peculiarity. The latter had a reinforcing element just like straw in the plaster<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">19</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The technical choices related to the construction influenced the making of the Ahmedabad complex over time. Visible and considerable effects of deterioration began to appear since the 1990s, which means only 15 years after the construction of the buildings. Considering the poor-quality clay used to make bricks and their consequent high porosity together with the limited protection offered by the mortar joint to the steel reinforcement, the choice to reinforce the masonry that way seemed to be one of the main causes of that deterioration, such as to be defined &quot;the recipe for a disaster&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">20</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The issue lays within the construction itself and derives, as discussed above, from specific decisions taken during the process, which, despite the geographical distance, Kahn was always aware of. This raises considerations on how priorities could be defined and on which possible methodology could be applied in order to preserve the essence of the buildings. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">These appear to be inevitable questions addressed in the work of Brinda Somaya. </p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Rampazzo_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. IIMA, Ahmedabad, Main Complex and Louis I. Kahn Plaza. (© Alessandra Rampazzo, 2015)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Rampazzo_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. IIMA, Ahmedabad, Main Complex: the covering and the simulation of the brickwork as a pictorial work. (© Alessandra Rampazzo, 2015)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Rampazzo_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. IIMA, Ahmedabad, Dorm D12: change on the used bond. The picture shows the English bond in the lower part and the flemish bond in the upper one. (© Alessandra Rampazzo, 2015)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Rampazzo_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. IIMA, Ahmedabad, Sample Yard. (© Alessandra Rampazzo, 2015)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Rampazzo_img_05.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 5. IIMA, Ahmedabad, Sample Yard. Axonometric view of the elements (© Alessandra Rampazzo, 2015)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Rampazzo_img_06.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 6. IIMA, Ahmedabad. Evidences of the steel reinforcement within the mortar joint and consequent brickwork degradation. (© Massimo Carmassi, 2007)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: Doshi traveled to the US for the first time in 1958 to receive the Graham Foundation Fellowship for Advanced Studies in the Fine Arts. On that occasion, a friend from New York introduced him to Kahn’s work and accompanied him to 1501 Walnut Street in Philadelphia.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: Sarabhai G. (1962, April 4-5). [Letter to Kahn]. 030.II.A.113.24, Louis I. Kahn Collection (from now on LIK Collection), Architectural Archives, Philadelphia, US.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Kahn L.I. (November 10, 1962). Note given by Mr. Louis Kahn, LIK Collection, 030.II.A.113.3, Architectural Archives, Philadelphia, US.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: The initial plan was revised in order to introduce, in addition to the spaces of laboratories and residences, a third element known as Meeting House.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: The Assembly Building took on a separate connotation from the Supreme Court complex and the buildings devoted to housing for the members of the Assembly.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">6</p>: The volume of the school building emerged as a closed and central place that dominated the plan until 1966 – a courtyard surrounded by uninterrupted buildings in line with the strong typological tradition (the library, the classrooms, the administrative building and the canteen).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">7</p>: The making of this unusual method, built up specifically for the IIMA project, is extensively explained in Rampazzo (2020).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">8</p>: Doshi (2000, p. 19).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">9</p>: The Sample Yard is still standing today inside the Campus, on a common garden located in-between the housing for professors.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">10</p>: For example, the Independence Hall, a Georgian-style brick building, which was situated only ten blocks east of Kahn’s studio in Philadelphia.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">11</p>: L.I. Kahn, 1972, I love beginnings (Latour, 1991, p. 288). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">12</p>: Between 1963 and 1969, 22 project versions were developed for this building. Each of them was documented by an extensive corpus of drawings preserved in the Philadelphia Archive.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">13</p>: During the first 7 years of the assignment (1962-1969), Kahn made 12 visits to Ahmedabad, as reported by the documents, as follows: one visit in 1962 and 1963, four visits in 1964, two visits in 1965, one visit in 1966 and 1967, two visits in 1969.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">14</p>: Raje A. (1969, August 1). [Letter to Kahn]. LIK Collection, 030.II.A.113.6, Architectural Archives, Philadelphia, US.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">15</p>: At Exeter the perimeter masonry is combined with reinforced concrete to distribute floor loads.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">16</p>: &quot;Is it therefore too far-fetched to consider expressive brick of tension?&quot;. With these words Raje questioned Kahn before describing the different solutions proposed from a practical point of view. Cf. Raje A. (1969, August 1). [Letter to Kahn]. LIK Collection, 030.II.A.113.6, Architectural Archives, Philadelphia, US.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">17</p>: Kahn L.I. (1969, August 13). [Letter to Raje]. LIK Collection, 030.II.A.113.6, Architectural Archives, Philadelphia, US.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">18</p>: 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">19</p>: Straw, like animal hair and other vegetable fibers, was traditionally used as a structuring additive to the plaster mixture.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">20</p>: Satsangi M.S. (one of the NID architects involved in the project) (2015, March 9). [Interview with author]. New Delhi, India.</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Doshi, B. V. (2000). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Architectural Legacies of Ahmedabad, Canvas of Modern Masters</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Latour, A. (1991). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Louis I. Kahn: Writings, Lectures, Interviews</em>. Rizzoli International</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Rampazzo, A. (2020). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Steel like straw. Louis I. Kahn and the Indian Institute of Management in Ahmedabad</em>. LetteraVentidue</voce>
</root>