<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">06 Le Corbusier&#x27;s architectural work, an exceptional contribution to the Modern Movement, a serial and transcontinental inscription on the World Heritage List</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Bénédicte Gandini</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Fondation Le Corbusier</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">As the universal legatee of Le Corbusier and owner of three emblematic works, the Fondation was at the heart of the process undertaken since 2002 by seven countries wishing to have the universal character of his creation recognized and to have his architectural work inscribed on the World Heritage List.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Recognized by a decree of 24 July 1968, the Fondation was born from Le Corbusier&#x27;s desire, without heirs, to avoid the dispersal of his collection, works and archives and to entrust them to an organization whose mission would be to conserve and disseminate them. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Since its creation, the Fondation has devoted all its resources to the accomplishment of the missions defined by its creator, one of the most important and complex of which consists of watching over the architectural work. The Fondation Le Corbusier monitors the conservation and restoration of his architectural work, both for the works it owns and for buildings owned by other public or private bodies. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The Fondation now has almost all the plans and documents (estimates, contracts, correspondence, etc.) concerning the projects and worksites carried out throughout his life by Le Corbusier and his collaborators. These archives are digitalized and are available to project managers and owners who wish to undertake work. The Fondation responds to requests for information on all buildings and puts in touch various experts, specialists or project managers dealing with similar problems. It also keeps a considerable amount of personal papers, notes, letters, diaries and notebooks, which can also be very useful in the context of restoration studies.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The Fondation has set up a system that allows it to benefit from the best possible information on the state of the buildings and the work projects likely to affect the works and their environment (restorations, extensions, destruction, substantial modifications of all kinds, woodwork, colors, etc.). The Fondation is in regular contact with the entire network of owners and has a network of correspondents in all the countries concerned who inform it of any threats that may endanger all or part of a work. It is also in contact with the national and regional heritage services, which seek advice and opinions when restoration projects are submitted to them. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Each restoration is an opportunity to enrich the material understanding of the work, to understand its genesis, the processes used, the details of its construction, etc. This is why it is fundamental that the Fondation be associated with the preliminary studies and the work carried out during the restoration. The research undertaken, the new materials uncovered and the documents discovered, feed the history, scientific research and the understanding and knowledge of the work.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The conservation of current and future archives has become a matter of the utmost importance for architects and owners: it avoids wasting precious time, serves to verify the assumptions of the preliminary studies and even helps to avoid irreparable mistakes. All these elements will contribute to a better knowledge of the building and facilitate its long-term maintenance. They also add to the general knowledge of the work, its creation and its transformations. The indispensable articulation between historical sources and living archives and the role played in this respect by the Fondation Le Corbusier was highlighted by the World Heritage Committee in its July 2018 opinion: </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">&quot;Welcomes the dynamic reconciliation clarification adopted by the Standing Conference to take into account the potential impact of development proposals and standards for conservation work across the series and the establishment by the Fondation Le Corbusier of a Committee to inform decisions on conservation, restoration and development projects&quot;. </p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Also: </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">“welcomes the creation by the Fondation Le Corbusier of a restoration archive, which represents an essential contribution to the harmonization of technical and methodological approaches to the conservation of Le Corbusier&#x27;s buildings, particularly in view of their potential to guide the rehabilitation or replacement of materials and elements...&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>.  </p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Any restoration or development project, or even any project for the realization of an element or an entire unrealized work by Le Corbusier must be submitted to a committee of experts coordinated by an architect-art historian within the Fondation. Its role is to verify the conformity of the project with the work of Le Corbusier, to issue recommendations and to inform the Foundation&#x27;s Board in order to authorize the project, express its reservations or even express its possible disagreement. The importance of the work carried out by the Fondation Le Corbusier was underlined by the World Heritage Committee when the Series was inscribed in July 2016: </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">&quot;The contribution of the expertise of the Fondation Le Corbusier -which holds moral rights to Le Corbusier&#x27;s work- is also crucial for the proper management and conservation of the nominated series, especially in cases where the properties are privately owned other than by the Fondation. In these situations, the effectiveness of the protection is highly dependent on the will of their private owners. Since 2003, the Fondation Le Corbusier has tried to establish closer contacts between the owners of Le Corbusier&#x27;s buildings. The Fondation also has an important archive of recent worldwide correspondence with private owners and governmental organizations. The nomination procedure has strengthened the exchange of information between stakeholders. In the additional information provided by States Parties, the intention to employ a full-time architect is mentioned, as well as a project to improve the Fondation&#x27;s data collection with the idea of forming an observatory. In view of the special problems associated with the conservation of 20th-century architecture, continued involvement of (inter)national specialists in the field of conservation of modern architectural heritage is also essential”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">At the request of all the States Parties, Argentina, Belgium, France, Germany, India, Japan and Switzerland, the Fondation therefore coordinated the preparatory work for the submission of the nomination and, as such, was responsible for the material management of the dossier. In the framework of the international management plan, the Fondation was entrusted by the project&#x27;s sponsor countries with the responsibility of the secretariat of the International Permanent Conference, which is in charge of managing the Series of seventeen buildings or sites inscribed as World Heritage in July 2016<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">6.2 The World Heritage Series of Le Corbusier</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Compared to other architects (Frank Lloyd Wright, Alvar Aalto, Oscar Niemeyer, etc.), Le Corbusier built few buildings. Although he studied more than 300 projects, between 1906 and 1965 he built only 78, but in eleven countries and on four continents. While the majority of his works are in Europe, particularly in France and Switzerland, some buildings, and not the least, are located in Tunisia, Japan, Argentina, the United States and particularly in India.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The buildings are very different in nature and size: villas and individual houses, religious buildings, collective housing, administrative buildings, gymnasiums, stadiums, etc. The owners also have very different statuses: public authorities, associations, private owners, co-ownerships, etc. while legislation or practices concerning the protection of heritage differ widely between the various countries. Many works were already protected during the architect&#x27;s lifetime, notably in Stuttgart, Chandigarh, Marseille and Poissy, and just after his death, notably in France (La Roche and Jeanneret houses, Ronchamp, etc.). </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The aim of the project was to reflect Le Corbusier&#x27;s contribution to the modern movement by bringing together in a series not only the &quot;masterpieces&quot; of his work, but also significant but lesser-known buildings that are representative in one way or another of his contribution to modern architecture without forgetting the geographical and transnational dimension of his work. Beyond an ideal list drawn up by the working group, made up of various experts and the Fondation, each of the works chosen had to meet the conditions set by the World Heritage Committee in order to be eligible.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">It should be remembered that only properties that are already protected by their national legislation can be considered for nomination, and it is the States that propose these properties by including them on the tentative list, prior to any other step towards a nomination file. As part of a proactive and consensual approach, the eleven countries that are currently custodians of at least one work by Le Corbusier were associated with the very first meetings and invited to participate in the project. They were then kept constantly informed of the progress of the project. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">This selection led to a relatively broad list, with Le Corbusier&#x27;s buildings enjoying total or partial protection in many countries, with the exception of the USA, Tunisia, Iraq and Russia. As for the works in Ahmedabad, India, Villa Shodan, Villa Sarabhai, the Mill Owners&#x27; Building and the Museum, built in the 1950s, which are recognized as major works by Le Corbusier, could not be included in the list. Indeed, according to the legislation in force, could not be protected until one hundred years after their construction. The lack of protection for Le Corbusier&#x27;s buildings in Ahmedabad poses a real risk for some of them, such as the museum which is currently in a serious state of decay. The conference organized by the Getty in Ahmedabad in 2018 and dedicated to the three Museums built by Le Corbusier in Ahmedabad, Chandigarh and Tokyo aimed, among other things, to raise awareness among local governments about the value of the works present on their territories.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">This identified corpus was then to form a coherent whole and meet the criteria for the definition of outstanding universal value retained for the third nomination file around the notion of &quot;influence&quot;, taking into account also the authenticity and integrity of the work and the carrying out of a complex mapping (delimitation of each constituent element and its buffer zone) and local management plans.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">All these exchanges have led to an ideal list of 17 elements with the following characteristics:</p>
<ul aid:pstyle="ul">a transnational, transcontinental series of a category under-represented on the World Heritage List: twentieth-century architecture
it brings together elements of various types and uses: collective and individual housing, public facilities, museums, places of worship, factories, etc., most of which have retained their original use;
of varying dimensions: from the immense esplanade of Chandigarh with its three buildings symbolic of power, to the Unité d&#x27;habitation de Marseille and its 1,200 inhabitants, to the Cabanon de Roquebrune-Cap-Martin;
with very different statuses: private, state, regional, communal, associative properties;
whose image, reception and recognition also vary greatly: alongside the icons are modest, lesser-known, smaller works...
</ul>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">It should be remembered that all these buildings or sites are now connected. They are a single property for which each of the elements contributes by its attributes to the universal value of the Series. From the Purism of the 1920s to the sculptural forms of the 1960s, via Brutalism, the series illustrates the evolution of modern architecture over nearly half a century, and attests to Le Corbusier&#x27;s ability to renew contemporary architectural aesthetics. Tense between two poles, that of a monumental architecture with exceptional forms on the one hand, and, on the other, that of an architecture of standards, sometimes of modest dimensions, but learned and exemplary of a desire to offer quality architecture to the greatest number, the series fully testifies to all the issues and the internationalization of the Modern Movement. It is a permanent work of research and innovation conceived over a period of almost fifty years.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The outcome of this application, in July 2016, was possible thanks to a collective effort which has raised awareness and interest in Le Corbusier&#x27;s work among a wide range of partners who were not very interested in it or had changing perception. The inscription on the World Heritage List of a series of 17 works or sites by Le Corbusier connected the countries concerned, federated initiatives in the countries, and brought together owners and managers, specialists and amateurs of this living work.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">After the failures of the bid in 2008 and 2011, the mobilization of the inhabitants and communities played a decisive role in the decision of the seven partner countries to relaunch the bid. The same attention is still being paid by many of the owners and the heirs of the sponsors, such as the Suhrid Sarabhai family and the Shodan family, who take care of the works entrusted to them and are committed to preserving them.  Although these works Le Corbusier built in Ahmedabad cannot be part of this World Heritage Series for the time being, they have been reported to the UNESCO World Heritage Centre as among the only ones eligible for extension of the Series inscribed in 2016.</p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini1_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. Proposal for inscription on the World Heritage List. (© Fondation Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini1_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. Chronological list of components. (© Fondation Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini1_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. Le Corbusier and Balkrishna Doshi (© Fondation Le Corbusier / Vastu Shilpa Foundation / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini1_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. Anand Sarabhai, Balkrishna Doshi, Le Corbusier and Suhrud Sarabhai (© Fondation Le Corbusier / Vastu Shilpa Foundation / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: Decision of the World Heritage Committee, July 2018, in response to the recommendations of July 2016: https://lecorbusier-worldheritage.org/documents/.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: Decision of the World Heritage Committee, July 2016, report to the nomination: https://lecorbusier-worldheritage.org/documents/.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Les Maisons La Roche et Jeanneret, Paris, Île-de-France, France ; la Petite villa au bord du lac Léman, Corseaux, Vaud, Suisse ; la Cité Frugès, Pessac, Aquitaine, France ; la Maison Guiette, Anvers, Flandre, Belgique ; les Maisons de la Weissenhof-Siedlung, Stuttgart, Bade-Wurtemberg, Allemagne ; la Villa Savoye et loge du jardinier, Poissy, Île-de-France, France ; l’Immeuble Clarté, Genève, Suisse ; l’Immeuble Locatif à la Porte Molitor, Paris, Île-de-France, France ; l’Unité d’Habitation, Marseille, Provence-Alpes-Côte d’Azur, France ; la Manufacture à Saint-Dié, Saint-Dié-des-Vosges, Lorraine, France ; la Maison du Docteur Curutchet, La Plata, Province de Buenos Aires, Argentine ; la Chapelle Notre-Dame-du-Haut, Ronchamp, Grand Est, France ; le Cabanon de Le Corbusier, Roquebrune-Cap-Martin, Provence-Alpes-Côte d’Azur, France ; le Complexe du Capitole, Chandigarh, Penjab, Inde ; le Couvent Sainte-Marie-de-la-Tourette, Éveux, Auvergne-Rhône-Alpes, France ; le Musée National des Beaux-Arts de l’Occident, Taito-Ku, Tokyo, Japon ; la Maison de la Culture de Firminy, Firminy, Auvergne-Rhône-Alpes, France.</p>

</root>