<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">09 Ahmedabad: Architecture within Spirit and Body</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Giovanni Leone</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Architect</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">The reference to spirit in the title is not esoteric or transcendental.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">It is rooted in the experience of reality, and in the historical-cultural as well as the physical-perceptual foundation because it reveals meaning through the convergence of senses and intellect. The spirit enlivens the body, whether it is natural, social, or individual. Although by definition spirit has no body, it is thanks to the body and mind that we can perceive and conceive it. On the other hand, in art, architecture and literature, the living body of the work itself the repository of the spirit.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">9.2 Living architecture</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Architecture is the art of transforming the environment according to the life necessities of every living form (no matter if plant, animal, or mineral). It progressively refines the ability to shape space by adapting it to the needs of the evolution of individual species and environments, which are the scene of plurality/diversity and various kinds of forces that come into play. Both the environment and the species influ<em aid:cstyle="italic">ence each other in their continuous change. *Living architecture expresses a dual meaning, both that of architecture that is alive, and at the same time *living architecture</em> as the action of living in and with it. The more architecture is lived, the more vital it is. The environment and the species influence each other under the influence of the forces at play, generating an infinite variety of combinations of form: life changes a particular habitat, and vice versa. The result is a plural unity, an amalgamation of diversity and variety. The habitat, whether urban or rural, is the mirror of the community, objectively and sincerely reflecting what it has in front of it to those who want to see. Inside and around, container and content, text and context... it is not a given to have one without the other; we in the West bind them together with rational thought. In India, on the contrary, this is the function of rituals that bind together different aspects in a holistic perspective. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">“First, we shape our buildings, afterwards our buildings shape us”. This quote by Winston Churchill refers to the indissoluble relationship of mutual influence between the individual and the surrounding environment from which derives the responsibility of the architect, who has great psychological and social power in his ability to affect the well-being of the inhabitants: in architecture you can feel good or you can stay feeling bad. The first source of discomfort is a lack of ‘dialogue’ and interaction between the inhabitants and the place they inhabit. These actors condition each other, generating a multiform unity that forges the spirit of the places and the identity of the inhabitants. It is not a rigid unit, defined once and for all, because it has a variable structure that is constantly modified as circumstances change. For this reason, it must be adaptable and continuously adapted, to the  individual body in the house, the social body in the territory and the natural body of the environment. Beyond the aesthetic qualities (composition) and the technical-material characteristics (project), the purpose of architecture is to provide space for living. Thus, architecture must first and foremost be welcoming, an inhabited space to be worn like a tailor-made dress that fits well and makes the wearer feel comfortable. Living architecture therefore has strength in its &quot;weakness&quot; and finds stability in the acceptance of impermanence and unpredictability. The more elastic and dynamic architecture is, the more it animates, moves, changes, experiencing crisis and discontinuity as an opportunity, cultivating resilience and thus being reborn. If, on the other hand, it becomes rigid, proving to be incapable of denying itself to go beyond what it is, it is destined to become a lifeless corpse - like those who have looked into the eyes of the mythological Gorgon - remaining lifeless, motionless, ...petrified. All this is irreconcilable with the ill-concealed aspiration of many architects to see the fruit of their labor remain unchanged over time. Many architects, but not all. </p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">9.3 Living architecture: B. V. Doshi</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">I remember that when I went to visit Aranya, a settlement designed by Doshi in Indore, I had a hard time locating it, with so many variations having been made by the residents to personalize their homes. Back in Ahmedabad, I told Doshi this, something  that would have been a source of frustration for many architects. Not for Doshi, who rejoiced at the circumstance, stating that it was confirmation of the work&#x27;s success; the addition of an important share of freedom allowed the residents to feel at home in this exemplary project  where architectural design becomes a participatory process. The appearance has changed, but not the founding principles of the settlement’s model, which remain intact and indeed are strengthened by the thematic variations introduced by the inhabitants to adapt the settlement to their way of life. The configuration of space has been decisively modified with the introduction of a plethora of exceptions that only confirm the rule: life should not be contained but facilitated. For the Indian master, the inhabitant taking possession of the architecture (modifying it and adapting it to his own needs) is not cause for annoyance but, on the contrary, satisfaction, unlike what usually happens with architects who are annoyed by every modification made to their works. Chapeau. Doshi steps to the side and overcomes the swamps of his ego by putting himself at the service of the community.  </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The peculiarity of his work is methodological, not linguistic or stylistic. Each project is unique, the result of listening and reading places and people that leads to a synthetic and synchronic interpretation. The approach of the Indian master is based on acceptance and welcome, a practice and philosophy of life that leads to considering differences and variety as a value to be absorbed and merged into a composite unity of a higher order. There are no firsts or precedents to respect. What counts is action, as Iannis Xenakis, engineer and composer of contemporary music, reminds us: “Dans la vie, il y a deux manières d’agir: l’une est de faire des choses, l’autre est de les analyser. Mais la meilleure analyse est, pour moi, de faire des choses&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The primacy of action is the basis of karma yoga (the yoga of action), and for Doshi the philosophy of architecture is not thought but action, not intellectual speculation but a theory in practice that does not derive from abstract studies and analyses of reality. It is applied science, experienced in practice and lived: it is <em aid:cstyle="italic">forma mentis</em> and lifestyle. The principles that underlie his production come from life and are acquired through experience that becomes knowledge with the decisive contribution of consciousness. Doshi&#x27;s architecture is not immediately recognizable in its results. His style is methodological in nature and operational in character, based on the appreciation of variety and respect for the other, for the differences without which there would be no alternatives and we would all be uniform, deprived of choice and prevented from searching for identity. Doshi observes life as it unfolds and thinks about it freely, without judging; rather, he tries to learn by catching the positive in an action. He observes the how, the where, the when, and then asks himself why. He reflects, and sees himself in that reflection, a bit like what happens in front of a mirror that combines figure and background.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">His is not a detached vision, but one anchored in the search for the Self, not his personal Self but the universal one. With his work, he shows us a destination towards which to direct ourselves. The goal is not a foreseen result but a direction that only indicates an orientation. The proposed solutions are always open to change in which the inhabitant plays a leading role. The inhabitant’s action of transformation contributes to the configuration of the appearance of the landscape, the character of the territory, and the nature of the environment as a faithful expression of the relationship between the individual and the social spheres in their various declinations (from family to neighborhood, from local and national communities to international ones). </p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">9.4 Living architecture: habitat</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">It is the exercise of living that builds a habitat, an inseparable union of man and environment, the result of the interaction between living species that changes the planet upon which we all (co)live, although man often forgets this and abuses it. In ecology the habitat is the set of environmental conditions in which a specific species lives, while in botany it is the place where a species finds favourable environmental conditions for its development and so establishes itself there. These are scientific definitions, but there is also a humanistic interpretation: <em aid:cstyle="italic">habitat</em> is, in fact, the third person singular of the present indicative of the word <em aid:cstyle="italic">habitare</em>, therefore it means to inhabit, an expression that includes both the action and the subject who performs it. If we go back to the source, we find the Latin verb <em aid:cstyle="italic">habeo</em>, which strictly speaking means to have, in oneself, on oneself or with oneself. Thus we can deduce that in essence, <em aid:cstyle="italic">having</em> is an intimateform of <em aid:cstyle="italic">being</em>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">To live is to wear one&#x27;s own house, just as clothing is an expression that represents more than a simple dress. In fact, it reflects being in a broad sense, our ways of behaving, what and who we are, nullifying the sense of the phrase &quot;the dress does not make the monk&quot;, which is a way of saying &quot; appearances deceive&quot; (somewhat akin to “you cannot judge a book by its cover”): in this case the dress is integrated with the body of the monk, as it is his skin. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Over time, architecture must follow the needs and changes of the body that inhabits/wears it. When necessary, we must shorten the sleeves, widen the waist, or take in the legs, without forgetting that architecture itself, besides the inhabitant, has its own life and destiny. Therefore the transformations must be compatible, requiring effort but not causing excessive suffering to oneself and the environment. We often forget this, just as we forget that architecture is not only the product of voluntary actions but also the result of involuntary influences that first affect the level of energy, since even walls, stones and plants absorb and release energy. There is no such thing as inanimate matter. Everything has its own life and finds its highest outcome in the energetic reality and in the spiritual dimension. On the energetic level matter is complex, subject to forces related to the presence of certain materials. Then there are the energetic reference elements on the cosmic scale, starting with the sun and moon, male and female, along with the fundamental forces or interactions (gravitational, electromagnetic, weak and strong nuclear, the nature’s most intense force, which acts in the vacuum inside the nucleus to keep protons and neutrons together). There are also local charges and forces that are variable from place to place. Finally, there is the energy contribution introduced by human presence and action, variable and changing. One can believe in the sedimentation of energy or not, but, regardless of the causes, the variation in the detection of the sign of the charges and waves is an instrumentally demonstrable reality. To give a scientific basis to the identification of the energy characteristics of places, , instruments such as Lecher&#x27;s antenna<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>, still widespread today and used both for the diagnosis of diseases and in green building, have been used since the beginning of the twentieth century to measure electromagnetic and thermal fields, that is the vital vibrations present in every form of life. The energetic framework, understood as an endemic quality of the place and the assets of the situation is not a factor placed exclusively upstream of the process of optimal organization of spaces and their proper use. The energetic dimension is a dynamic factor that changes not only by means of possible canonical corrective expedients (standardized in India by Vastu and in China by Feng-shui), but it is also and especially a consequence of the energy that such actions and those who perform them produce, release and deposit in the places they manipulate. Space is a geometric entity, but it is the way of using it that makes the difference between one space and another. A place derives character thanks to the energetic qualities that remain suspended or are absorbed in the context, intangible but perceptible to those who have developed the aptitude to feel subtle spiritual solicitations.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">9.5 The breath: <em aid:cstyle="italic">genius and prāṇa</em></h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Let&#x27;s return to the idea of spirit. This essay of mine is more than an intervention - in fact it is a spiritual session in which I will try to evoke:</p>
<ul aid:pstyle="ul">the <em aid:cstyle="italic">genius loci</em> (the spirit of the place)
 the <em aid:cstyle="italic">genius seculi</em> (the spirit of the time, defined in Romanticism by Hegel, Goethe, etc. as zeitgeist. The concept of <em aid:cstyle="italic">kunstwollen</em> - artistic will - introduced by Alois Riegl can be considered its legitimate offspring).
</ul>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">In Roman religion, the Latin term <em aid:cstyle="italic">genius</em> denotes a tutelary deity who is the individual instance (God) of a general divine nature (divinity) present in every person, place or thing. It is the essence, the intimate nature: the soul. <em aid:cstyle="italic">Loci</em> is the plural of <em aid:cstyle="italic">locus</em> (place) and is a mentally or materially determined spatial entity. From a scientific perspective, however, it is a precise place, identified by longitude and latitude. In a humanistic perspective, however, a place is a precise lived space inhabited by the senses and emotions.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Spirit derives from Latin <em aid:cstyle="italic">spiritus</em> and from <em aid:cstyle="italic">spirare</em> which means to expire or exhale, an image that conveys a sense of lightness. For this reason the term came to express any incorporeal substance such as the soul, but also angels, demons, goblins, and even the shadow of a dead person. For the Romans to expire was to emit the last breath that the next of kin receives, because Romans believed that this final breath carried the soul, and not to disperse it, but for the next of kin to receive within himself.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">We use a lot of energy, more than necessary, and we waste so much energy because we do not take the time to recognize and value it, whatever its sign, positive or negative. In the Indian culture the life force is called <em aid:cstyle="italic">prāṇa</em>, energy that manifests itself in the breath, the metabolization of an airy nothingness that becomes inner energy through absorption in the organism. Such is also the case for architecture: it is an organism. The breath is not only that of the animal, but also that of the environment, manifested for example through the breezes that cross the space and the building, enlivening it.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">9.6 Expanded_text (inspiration): Bharat</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">In the second half of the twentieth century, Ahmedabad (and the whole of India) was a laboratory<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p> that produced extraordinary architectural works of the most advanced research, from the poetic and technical point of view in function of a &quot;new construction&quot;. In Europe we measured ourselves with the reconstruction after the destruction of war, while in India we are dedicated to the new foundation, the construction of the bases upon which to build a present understood as a past reinterpreted for the future. Two perfectly set works of foreign hand and universal mind well represent this season: LC&#x27;s Open Hand and Tower of Shadows in Chandigarh.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The open hand (1952) represents hope in a better future, a discreet but meaningful sign. In a letter to Nehru, LC, after having recalled the successes achieved &quot;in one hundred years of scientific and technical conquests&quot;, expresses the hope that &quot;the fission of the atom is about to revolutionize the sources of energy and, consequently, production&quot; and that therefore </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">&quot;human suffering, famine, can be, in the future, put aside [...] Abundance appears as the sign of our age. The open hand to receive and to give can be chosen as a symbolic materialization of many victories! [...] India will be able to value the opportunity to raise on the Capitol of Chandigarh, currently under construction, in the middle of the buildings hosting institutions and power, the symbolic and evocative sign of the &#x27;Open Hand&#x27;: open to receive the riches of creation, open to distribute these riches to its people and to other people [...] The open hand will affirm that the second era of the machinist civilization has begun – the era of harmony&quot;.<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p></p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">On page 10 of his introduction to the volume <em aid:cstyle="italic">Œuvre Complète 1946-1952</em> Le Corbusier writes: the hand </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">&quot;turns according to the wind on a ball bearing: the &#x27;hand&#x27; will be oriented according to the wind of the day. A phenomenon that does not symbolize an opportunistic banderole. On the contrary: it is the symbol of the consideration of facts and daily reality [...] the phases of the game played by man with the cosmic elements: man, and nature. A game of numbers, a game of the calendar and the solar day, a game of the sun with its light, its shadow and its heat. This game was precisely my life’s work from the beginning&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">The tower of shadows is a celebration of light and <em aid:cstyle="italic">prāṇa</em>, and has deep relationships with the palace of the spinners, a palace permeated by breezes and the modulated relationship with natural elements such as sun, air, water and the earth that rises through the ramp and penetrates the building until it reaches the sky on the terrace. The common thread is emptiness and a configuration that inspires us to reflect on the thin border that both separates and unites the notion of container and contents.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">9.7 Local con_text (exhalation): Ahmedabad</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">The expanded notion of con_text (physical, geographical, morphological, political, social, economic, cultural...) is indispensable to the understanding of places. Personal and family events, geographical position, economic and social circumstances, and epochal events take place in the city of Ahmed, determining the physiognomy of one of the most industrious and advanced cities in India. It is the commercial capital of Gujarat and an important productive center of post-colonial India, animated by a capitalism of an exquisitely Indian type, the far-sighted promoter of an enlightened patronage that has sought, without prejudice and preclusion, the most useful contributions to economic and social progress. In architecture, the recourse to leading exponents of the international scene, including Le Corbusier and Louis I. Kahn, was not an end (as it often happens today, even in Italy, with forms of provincialism or cultural neo-colonialism) but was functional to professional training, research, and interaction with the most advanced thinking the international scene proposed. Thus it was the birth of a new liberal and progressive bourgeoisie<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">6</p>.</p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">&quot;Individuals founded industries, which gave birth to and supported institutions, which in turn formed individuals. Hence in Ahmedabad, economic and educational activities, arts and crafts, culture, architecture, and administration have been symbiotic. The reciprocity of their interdependence and sustenance is one of the specificities of the city. [...]</p>
<p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">This is the reason why the city cannot be seen in the light of any single dimension. Although it was known as the &#x27;Manchester of the East&#x27; it would be wrong to classify the city only as a center of the textile industry. [...] Machines and manual skills can, therefore, coexist. This coexistence of the modern with the traditional is yet another peculiarity of the city where traditional foundations are stable; yet, the experimentation-adaptation of the new comes naturally to the business community. This process of continuous adaptation and intertwining of culture, art, and commerce describes this aspect of citizen initiative and involvement in civic affairs. The city, in various ways, has been for, by, of its people.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">Therefore, Ahmedabad cannot be understood with a chronology of its historical events or any other specific structure of references. Even its history has been an ongoing process - an alchemy of the many faces of life. An authentic historical account of the city must, therefore, take a holistic view that encompasses all aspects - the place, its people, and their ways of life&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">7</p>. </p></blockquote>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">9.8 Text and con_text</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Let&#x27;s now take a dip into the architectural text with two examples that once again feature Doshi, and are excellent examples of the literary-narrative component of architecture: the Palace of the Spinners (which he worked on for Le Corbusier) and the Indian Institute of Management (which he designed with Louis Kahn).  </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Although they are based on the Ville Savoy type, appropriately revised and corrected, the villas and palaces designed by LC on the Indian subcontinent have affinities with the numerous archaeological and architectural &quot;remnants&quot; that time has stripped of every superstructure until they reach the threshold of pure spirit. The palace of the spinners seems to have already been born as an archaeological find, deprived of walls whose collapse it was not necessary to wait for. It is a perfectly finished ruin, ennobled until it becomes a matrix of modernity in an exquisitely poetic process. The building is stripped of its clothing and gives itself for what it is: space and place. The resulting emotional impact is remarkable. Inside the building it is the void that prevails, in a process of subtraction that hosts the volumes with the internal environments closed, autonomous, distinct. The sense of emptiness seems to contrast with the strong and precise perception of the envelope, a volume without decorations but adorned by a structural sign that is paginated (on the plane) and a Cartesian grid (three-dimensional). The simultaneous exaltation of fullness and emptiness is not a contradiction; on the contrary it denotes the unitary ambivalence of the space that is a container of content. The overall perceptive experience is enriched by the ramp, which forces a slow approach, gradually raising the visitor&#x27;s point of view and accentuating the experience of space before allowing him to penetrate the wall of shadows and welcoming him inside. Another recurring presence in India is water, a symbol and a precious asset. In the palace of the spinners it is taken into account at a distance, by its placement along the river to enjoy the relief of the breezes that form between land and water. Those who stay in the palace can contemplate the river im-mediately from a facade that disappears in the perception of those behind it, designed to acquire shape only when observed tangentially, from the sides. The photographs of this façade show a building stripped bare, a vivisection that puts its internal organs on display, but these are photo_graphs: it is impossible to overcome the penumbra in which the building is immersed, except in the morning and with the aid of a zoom lens from the opposite bank or with the naked eye from a boat for a few brief moments as it passes. For the rest, the sun highlights the septa seen from the side and their delicate luminous graphics that stand out against the background of shadow. The baffles of the eastern elevation are orthogonal to the river, making the building totally permeable to breezes. The opposite façade, facing west, is bent in the direction of the prevailing winds, and closed towards the city. On the roof terrace the prevailing winds meet. The sunscreen in reinforced concrete is close to the elevations, eloquently detached from the building thanks to small joints that make it a classic element, the facade of a building that is perfect in form and precisely imperfect in surface, celebrating air and light, the aesthetic expression of a philosophy of nature.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the case of the Indian Institute of Management, recently the subject of a scandalous affair<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">8</p>, the agreement between the state client and Kahn called for the employment of engineers and architects from the NID (National Institute of Design) for the design, offering them an opportunity for top-level professional training. In charge of coordination and interaction with the local reality were B.V. Doshi and Ananth Raje (1929-2009), Indian architects trusted by Kahn and his design associates. The contributions of these Indian Masters of Architecture and engineering ensured quality and control in the on-site work and at the same time offered an original contribution thanks to their knowledge and experience. The results of this involvement are tangible. For example, in the residences, where the forms of Kahnian poetics are organized in such a way as to stimulate the formation of community at multiple levels, thanks to the definition of private and public spaces for relationships. Elements that stand out in this regard: the internal distribution and the veranda of the housing units; the large corridors marked by stairs and tea rooms, opportunities for meeting and social relations; the open spaces for neighbors between buildings; sports fields; the market; the large square. Among the aspects of Indian derivation there is the constant presence in the plans of numerous small dots, part of the design since the first of the various versions of the project, and the existing trees, carefully surveyed to be preserved. Last but not least, the local wisdom is documented by the rotation of the entire complex by 90° towards S-E according to Doshi&#x27;s indications, in the direction of the prevailing winds, to allow the buildings to be crossed by the breeze. The sections with the staff&#x27;s residences are also from the same period. These areas made use of vaults and a roof (rainroof) in which we see light wells and devices for ventilation, and water flows to the opposite directions in which there are a basin and a garden, agents of cooling. The breath of life or <em aid:cstyle="italic">prāṇa</em> is manifested in the environment by the breezes that pass through the building, making it come alive. This is the theme of the dormitories of the Indian Institute of Management. The dialogue with nature that permeates the space reminds those who deal with a subject such as economics, that is likely to be distant and abstract, arid and greedy, of the natural dimension, the importance of life, emphasizing how the economy must be at the service of life for the achievement of well-being, which is not comfort, but being well. We find the same message in the Indian Institute of Management in Bangalore, where nature creeps into the spaces between the classrooms, a luxuriant and bursting nature, the face of authentic wealth. These are spaces for education not only because they host institutes of higher learning, but also because they convey a strong and clear message, becoming spaces of involuntary teaching, whose experience is deposited in the depths of the learners. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">On the subject of breath, Amdavad ni GUFA is an exemplary work, significant and extraordinarily effective in every aspect, which in some ways seems to be generated by subtraction of matter (as were the caves of Ellora, Ajanta, etc.) but in other ways seems to be born from insufflation, somewhat like the master glassmakers who create vases by blowing air into incandescent glass, giving it lightness like air and transparency like water. Well, GUFA is the miracle of a space in which the breath of life dwells, together with the spirit of the artist Maqbool Fida Husain (who envelops the building, inside which dancing spirits and figures of color dwell in the cobra&#x27;s coils) and of the architect B. V. Doshi, who renounced the use of force in the construction and let the forces cancel each other out, sliding on the surface of the artifact, as is typical of martial arts. The history of this work bears witness to the evolution, or rather the involution, the beginning of the reversal of the trend: Husain died in 2011 in self-exile in Qatar, where he took refuge in 2006 to escape death threats from members of the nationalist right following the controversy over his 1996 exhibition of paintings featuring nudes of deities, offending religious sensibilities. The void left by Husain, exiled together with <em aid:cstyle="italic">satyagraha</em> (a term that is translated as non-violence or passive resistance but that means &quot;insistence for the truth&quot;, which in Sanskrit is <em aid:cstyle="italic">satya</em>) is a gap in the contemporary Indian cultural panorama, a void of absence.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">9.9 Conclusions, a new beginning</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Evaluating the quality of architecture rarely takes into account an assessment of the quality of life of the inhabitants and their perception of architecture. Architects seem to think that if the inhabitants complain it is because they have not understood. In architectural discourse, life remains on the margins, neglecting the fact that it is precisely this element that constitutes the attribute of vitality of architecture itself. In the essays, works and authors are compared, relationships with history and places are investigated, but only on the level of ideas and theory; that is, in a scenario in which the user is considered as a perturbation that corrupts and de-forms what the architect has formed. On the contrary, the experience and its transformative power, with the modifications and adaptations made over time to harmonize space and action, are what allows architecture to reach a complete form, making it a ripe fruit ready to be picked, tasted and appreciated. Even imprecise execution is considered a defect, as if it were not the result of coincidences and vital circumstances: corrosion, encrustation, contamination, transformation of the primal idea humanizes architecture and should be considered its completion: the realization is not the execution but the appropriation by the user/inhabitant that brings architecture from the ideal to the plane of reality, perfectly imperfect, as is life itself.</p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Leone_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. Ganesh, the sacred in Doshi&#x27;s house, Ahmedabad. (© Giovanni Leone, 2008)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Leone_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. Amdavad Ni Gufa, Ahmedabad. (© Giovanni Leone, 2006)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Leone_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. Rooftops during the international Kite festival in Ahmedabad in January. (© Giovanni Leone, 2008)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Leone_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. Indian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad. (© Giovanni Leone)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: “In life there are two ways to act: one is to do things and the other is to analyze them. But the best analysis is, for me, to do things”. Iannis Xenakis’s statement quoted by Stan Radu in program notes for the Hommage à Iannis Xenakis, Radio France 5-8 June 2001, reprinted in Xenakis (2008).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: Here is some information translated from Italian websites containing offers of Training Courses for the use of the Lecher antenna. “All kinds of energy matter vibrate and radiate. The same is true for the human body whose radiant balance can be measured through the electromagnetic and electric fields that run through it. The natural radiant field is also the basis for the genesis and preservation of life. But today in addition to natural radiations (Atmospherics or Spherics), there are the artificial ones (Technics), which might bring possible negative interferences on living beings. Even beverages and foods, homeopathic, isotherapeutic and allopathic remedies, stones and other substances absorbed or brought into contact with the body give off vibrations that may affect the human body acting positively or negatively on physical and mental level. The Lecher antenna, a manual well perfected radiesthetic instrument, can measure these energetic vibrations. It allows to distinguish the frequency and intensity of the two polarities of an electromagnetic field present in the biosphere or emanating from a living being, plants, stones and so on. The Lecher antenna is used in the bioremediation of a house, in the realization of a diagnosis for the evaluation of the different electromagnetic frequencies that organs emanates, and for testing medicines, food, stones and so on.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Cf. Leone (2013, pp. 7-16).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: Le Corbusier. (1959, September 29). [Letter to Nehru]. Fonds Pierre Jeanneret, 156-002-0, Canadian Centre for Architecture, Montréal.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: Le Corbusier (1954, p. 10).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">6</p>: After the Kutch earthquake in January 2001, local newspapers reported numerous statements from the most fundamentalist Hindus who claimed that the earthquake was a divine punishment due to the excessively loose morals that disrespected traditions.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">7</p>: Doshi (2002).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">8</p>: Leone (2021).</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1953). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier \&amp; Pierre Jeanneret, Œuvre complète: 1946-1952</em> (Vol. 5). Girsberger</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Leone, G. (2013). Ahmedabad. In M. Biraghi, &amp; A. Ferlenga (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Architettura del Novecento</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>: Vol. 2</em> (pp. 7–16). Einaudi</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Leone, G. (2021, January 4). Demolizioni. In India tocca a un capolavoro di Louis I. Kahn. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Art Tribune</em>. https://www.artribune.com/progettazione/architettura/2021/01/demolizioni-india-louis-kahn/</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Pandya, Y. (2002). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>The Ahmedabad Chronicle, Imprints of a Millennium</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Xenakis, I. (2008). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Music and Architecture</em> (S. Kanach, Trans.). Pendragon Press</voce>
</root>