<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">Part 2. Research studies and restoration works</h1>
<h1 aid:pstyle="H1">12 Restoring the interiors of Le Corbusier&#x27;s apartment-studio: conserving intimacy</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Bénédicte Gandini</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Fondation Le Corbusier</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening"><em aid:cstyle="italic">&quot;Le ciel est radieux et nous vivons depuis quinze jours dans des nouvelles conditions miraculeuses: un logis qui est céleste, car tout y est ciel et lumière, espace et simplicité&quot;</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><em aid:cstyle="italic">&quot;L’appartement de Molitor est devenu un paradis. Quand ce sera meublé, alors…&quot;</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Le Corbusier moved to the apartment-studio on rue Nungesser et Coli in 1934 with his wife Yvonne on the top two floors of the Immeuble Molitor, designed and built with Pierre Jeanneret, between Paris and Boulogne-Billancourt (fig. 1). Le Corbusier lived and worked there until his death in 1965: he arranged and modified its spaces over time, as testified by the photos of different periods (by Salaün, Willi, Rizzo, Burri)<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In his apartment, Le Corbusier associated some of the furniture he designed at the end of the 1920s with P. Jeanneret and C. Perriand, with fixed and mobile furniture purposely created for these spaces, and with serial objects, such as Thonet armchairs (fig. 2). In his studio, on the other hand, we also find furniture from La Chaux-de-Fonds. Some elements disappeared after the architect&#x27;s death, and many changes have been made since, to solve various degradations. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The Fondation Le Corbusier, universal legatee of the architect, and therefore owner of the apartment-studio, initiated numerous studies that have allowed to retrace the history of this place and its transformations in view of its restoration<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p>. This latest restoration work, carried out between 2014 and 2018, also had as its objective the restoration of its interiors and furniture. This work has given rise to numerous publications, and also a documentary film. But rarely has the question of the restoration of furniture of this Corbusian interior, a place of life and creation, been the subject of an in-depth study. As if the furniture, fixed and mobile, had a different status in relation to the architectural work that contains it, without being part of it.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">12.2 Interiors modifications and furniture inventory</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">On the top two floors of the building at the Porte Molitor, Le Corbusier designed an apartment and a painting studio<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>. These interiors, created for his couple and for his personal work after &quot;seventeen years in the Rue Jacob in the old&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">6</p> have not been the subject of specific research and are no longer in the state left by the architect. Indeed, if his art collection and his <em aid:cstyle="italic">private collection</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">7</p> are now in the reserves of the Fondation Le Corbusier, many elements of the furniture have disappeared (carpets, lamps, the many rattan chairs, garden chairs, Indian chairs, Strafor shelves, for example) since the architect&#x27;s death. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">During the last restoration undertaken by the Fondation Le Corbusier<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">8</p> to resolve numerous degradations, it was necessary to identify the transformations of these interiors, open to the public since 1991. This project for the restoration of this intimate space of the architect has been the opportunity to deepen the material knowledge of the modern Corbusian interior, thanks to studies commissioned to many specialists<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">9</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">If the works of art, in particular his paintings, are moved between the spaces, the furniture, and also the &quot;personal&quot; objects<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">10</p>, do not seem to change place (fig. 3). Important modifications can be noted from the archives, and in particular the author&#x27;s photographs, at the level of the interior façades, the floor remaining unchanged. Indeed, the walls and ceilings are partly covered with oak plywood from 1939 in the living room, his bureau and the high ceiling of the studio and the guest room<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">11</p>. But also at the level of the polychromies, which are not identifiable in the black and white photos, but which are partly documented by the archives and whose changes have been revealed by the soundings carried out by Marie-Odile Hubert, painting restorer. More than three hundred soundings carried out, cross-checked with archive documents and laboratory analyses, have in fact made it possible to identify the pictorial layers carried out during the architect&#x27;s lifetime and afterwards, highlighting in particular a first layer made up of Salubra wallpapers, then covered by three other repaintings (with a change of color only for certain walls) desired by Le Corbusier (1939, 1948-50, 1960-1965). </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Among the furniture installed in 1934 in the living room<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">12</p> the Grand Confort armchair, large model (which changes place as soon as the sofa arrives), was designed in 1928 with Pierre Jeanneret and Charlotte Perriand<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">13</p>.  The researches concerning the origin of the conception by Le Corbusier of a program &quot;<em aid:cstyle="italic">casiers</em>, tables, chairs&quot;, followed by the &quot;Studies on the different ways of sitting, to which our seats should adapt&quot; in April 1927, and its development by the three co-authors in the &quot;Interior equipment of a house&quot; presented to the Salon in the Autumn of Paris of 1929, were largely developed by E. Koering<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">14</p>. The latest studies commissioned by the Foundation have made it possible, on the other hand, to clarify the material history of this work, making it possible, for example, to document the original two-tone polychromy: a glossy lacquer in the color of <em aid:cstyle="italic">terre d&#x27;ombre</em> for the seat (L-shaped profile, latticework and springs), and green for the tubes. 
The dining room table also appears in early photos, and is a variant of the curved living room table in the Swiss Pavilion, also designed by Le Corbusier, Pierre Jeanneret and Charlotte Perriand<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">15</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The painted tube sofa<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">16</p>, a unique example made by Le Corbusier for his salon (fig. 4), arrived in November 1934, accompanied by a small table that has now disappeared. The search for polychromy for the sofa allowed us to identify the original glossy cream-gray lacquer covered by the current gray. 
Later, Le Corbusier will add the table <em aid:cstyle="italic">trunk of tree</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">17</p>, made in the 1940s, and in 1952, a reissue of the chaise longue made by Whonbedarf<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">18</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The fixed wood and metal furniture created for her apartment (in the bedroom: the bed fixed to the wall and the storage spaces, wardrobe - lockers - revolving door as well as Yvonne&#x27;s <em aid:cstyle="italic">coiffeuse</em> and in the kitchen the storage cupboards) and in the workshop (at the level of the office: table and various shelves) have not evolved. It has also been the subject of polychromy surveys to identify colors and varnishes. All the metal elements have been identified<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">19</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In his atelier, we find older furniture already at 20 rue Jacob, coming from the move of his parents from the Maison Blanche (La Chaux-de-Fonds) (fig. 5): </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">&quot;I repeat here the list of furniture to be sent to us (as far as I am concerned, a list that I had given when I left: a white layette; another layette, a diploma frame of expo, a galley, a lectern, an oval table yellow room, a chest of drawers yellow room, table workshop Edouard, an armchair workshop Edouard, [...] a spinet, a Greco photo, two Byzantine panels (of the lingerie). All the frames with their glasses, a few quinquets (as many as possible)”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">20</p>.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">It is about the oval table and the two pieces of furniture of watchmakers (<em aid:cstyle="italic">layettes</em>), which arrive in Paris on February 8, 1918. </p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">12.3 The conservation of a Corbusian interior, a global approach from the façades to the furniture</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">The restoration of this Corbusian interior, certainly among the most intimate, which preserves the last arrangements wanted by the architect and part of the furniture <em aid:cstyle="italic">in situ</em>, came to complete the intervention on the facades and roofs (vaults and terrace)<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">21</p>. For the interiors, very degraded by years of infiltrations and use, the opening to the public was also an important part of the project, requiring for example the implementation of safety lighting. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The reference state wanted by the experts of the Fondation Le Corbusier and accepted by the Regional Conservation of Historic Monuments, being that of 1965, the conservation of all the existing works and the changes made by the architect was envisaged. However, some restitutions were identified as necessary, in particular those of the polychromies of the 1960s and the carpet of the dining room, which has now disappeared but is documented by the archives and by color photos. In addition, some restitutions already made in previous years have been preserved. No other restitution has been proposed, privileging the presence of the authentic furniture – but also the works of locksmiths, as the windows, as well as all the elements in metal as door handles, and also the personal objects, as the Vase Savoy<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">22</p> – always existed in this place (fig. 6). </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">If the walls were effectively repainted, as well as the fixed furniture considered as a continuity of the interior facades (revolving doors, cupboards, openings) with oil emulsions, the whole of the soundings remained visible so as to testify to the evolution in time of the Corbusian choices as regards color and to show the approach adopted for the restitution of the polychromies of the apartment. The superimposition of the layers of paint is also a testimony of the thickness in time of the occupation of the place, which it materializes the stratification<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">23</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The oak plywood paneling and other fixed wood furniture were simply cleaned, refixed if necessary and treated. The floor was cleaned, no replacement being desired, also concerning repairs made after the death of the architect. The same choice was made for the stone wall of the atelier, which was left untouched – result the intervention made in the 1980s - to avoid any further deterioration of the stones, instead of attempting a return to the original facing and joints. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Concerning the furniture (old furniture, furniture created by Le Corbusier, industrial furniture<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">24</p>), it was decided to preserve it in its original state without any repainting or removal of the original layers. For these unique works, a simple cleaning was preferred, completed by a treatment of the oxidized elements and in certain cases a refixing of the layers of paint or plywood by preserving the degraded material or the lacunar paint. The polychromatic surveys carried out on the tube furniture also remain visible, as on the walls, in order to show the original color.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">This approach seems very different from other interventions that privilege the restitution of the original state of &quot;iconic interiors&quot;. Several well-known examples can be cited as the Villa Cavrois<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">25</p> by Mallet-Stevens and more recently the Villa E-1027<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">26</p> by Eileen Gray and Jean Badovici in Roquebrune Cap-Martin.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">These interventions can require the removal of part of the history of works and successive contributions, without reason related to the strict conservation. Moreover, the restitutions made from the iconography, privileging the old photographs, most often in black and white, without plans nor details of construction, can lead to errors of interpretation. Often the project of restitution, for the history of the building itself, can be completed by the purchase of &quot;original&quot; furniture or by the setting up of new reissues, creating objects with a hybrid status. Rich in partial restitutions or complete replacements, these projects are driven by the search for coherence linked to a reference state or a certain &quot;authenticity&quot; without really taking it into account. The economic investment necessary for this kind of intervention also seems to be linked to the interest aroused.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The decisions taken for Le Corbusier&#x27;s apartment-atelier have privileged the authenticity of this unique place among his works. This choice guides today the future restoration of the building&#x27;s façades<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">27</p>. The conservation of all the windows implemented under the supervision of Le Corbusier between 1956 and 1965, was preferred to replacement. This makes possible to safeguard the building restored by Le Corbusier and in part in the state desired at the time of his request for protection among the Historic Monuments in 1962 because &quot;in full danger in front of the vandals of the condominium&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">28</p>.</p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini2_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. Façade of the Immeuble Molitor (FLC L2-10-5. (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini2_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. Photos of the bedroom after restoration</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini2_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. Carnet De Franclieu 1-015. (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
        <Image href="File:///Gandini2_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. Le Corbusier on the sofa (FLC L4-9-17). (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini2_img_05.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 5. Atelier furniture</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Gandini2_img_06.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 6. The vase Savoy, by Alvar Aalto, since 1937 on the table of the apartment of Le Corbusier (FLC L2-10-106. (© Fondation Le Corbusier / ph. Peter Willi, 1965 / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
    
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: Le Corbusier. (1934, Mai 28). [Letter to Mme Jeanneret]. R2(1)203, Archives Fondation Le Corbusier (from now on FLC), Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: Le Corbusier (1934, April 9). [Letter to his mother]. R2-1-257, FLC, Paris, France. &quot;Ma chère petite maman. Rude semaine. Déménagé tous les tableaux, tous les papiers. Dix-sept années de papier ! [...] Partie morale gagnée avec Yvonne. L’appartement lui a été présenté fini, rideaux, la plupart des meubles (nouveaux) [...] L’appartement est bien. C’était un péril pour moi d’aller habiter ma propre architecture. Au vrai, c’est magnifique. C’est une vue pleine de campagne avec aucune notion d’être perché au septième et huitième étage, grâce à des stratagèmes architecturaux. Pas de vertige ainsi&quot;: Le Corbusier (1934, April 29). [Letter to his mother]. R2-1-258, FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Gandini and Mengin (2018); Desmoulins (2018).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: This article does not address the question of windows, strictly related to the interiors, developed in the study commissioned by the Fondation Le Corbusier Graf and Marino (2014); Graf and Marino (2017); Gandini, Mengin and Richard (2017).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: Sbriglio (1996). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">6</p>: Le Corbusier. (1934, April 29). [Letter to his mother]. R2-1-258, FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">7</p>: &quot;Il y a ce que j’appelle ma collection privée : ce sont des bouts de bois, ce sont des éclats de pierre, des épines, une pigne de pin. Ce sont des briques de bâtiments qui servent de socle à des statuettes. Ce sont des coquillages entiers ou cassés par la mer qui sont très intéressants et même, je vous signale, des os de boucherie pour ceux qui aiment ça, des os de boucherie que la mer renvoie devant les pensions de famille devant les au bord des océans. Ce sont des outils extraordinaires de méditation physique, de résistance des matériaux, d’harmonie et de beauté de forme. Je ne vous cacherai pas que j’appelle ça ma CP, c’est-à-dire ma collection particulière et j’en ai une véritable délectation&quot;. Le Corbusier. (1951, January 26). [Radio interview]. FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">8</p>: This restoration followed by François Chatillon, Architecte en chef des monuments historiques, between 2014 and 2018, received the DOCOMOMO Rehabilitation Award in 2021 as &quot;Open House&quot;.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">9</p>: Hubert, Hall and Schroeter (2015).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">10</p>: Within the framework of the research for this restoration, we have rediscovered the inventory carnets of the objects which were in the apartment in 1965 carried out by Françoise de Franclieu, curator who had made the first inventory of the drawings and paintings of Le Corbusier during the life of the master (FLC, Paris, France).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">11</p>: &quot;Ma chère petite maman. Nous voici ‘hors d’ouvriers’. Les peintres sont partis. Nous avons réaménagé et ça va ! Ça va fort bien et maintenant mon appartement a l’air d’être fini. Le problème c’était la noirceur due aux suies de Boulogne : le plafond tout bardé de noir, les murs vert pâle idem. J’ai fait plaquer au plafond des lambris de chêne naturel. Idem sur le mur vert. Idem sur la cage d’ascenseur. Le mur jusqu’ici gris où était la petite cheminée est maintenant d’un rouge vermillon un peu assommé. La salle à manger a été repeinte en blanc (murs et voûte)&quot;: Le Corbusier (1934, April 8). [Letter to his mother]. R2-1-253. FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">12</p>: &quot;Ce que vous appelez pompeusement mon salon et qui n’est qu’une toute petite chose&quot;: Le Corbusier (1951, January 26). [Radio interview]. FLC, Paris, France. 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">13</p>: On the work of the three co-authors and the notion of team, Charlotte Perriand testifies: &quot;[...] justement ces meubles je ne les ai pas conçus seule, je les ai conçus avec Le Corbusier et Pierre Jeanneret. Et chez eux j’ai découvert que le travail d’équipé était enrichissant&quot; (<em aid:cstyle="italic">Du côté de chez Fred, Charlotte Perriand</em>, 1989). FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">14</p>: Koering (2010); Koering (2020); Koering (2015).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">15</p>: Ruegg (2012).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">16</p>: &quot;Grand évènement ce matin : on a monté, non sans combine, le grand divan du coin de feu. Et tout a pris un air pépère, ‘comme chez les gens’. Yvonne est ravie. Enfin, nous aussi pourrons offrir le café sur un canapé. Comme quoi il faut acquérir par une longue route, ses droits à entrer dans la société bourgeoise !!!&quot;. Le Corbusier. (1934, November 26). [Letter to his mother]. R2-1, FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">17</p>: &quot;La table est assez drôle [...] c’est un guéridon dont la hauteur est de [...] 54 centimètres [...]. Le tablier sur un trépied de fer est fait d’un tronc d’arbre d’Afrique que j’ai choisi dans ce que j’appelle l’écurie des éléphants que l’on trouve rue de Charonne et dans le quartier des meubles. [...] C’est chez certains marchands de bois, ces troncs gigantesques [...] qui occupent des hangars en bois.[...] Un de ces marchands m’a dit : ‘je vous en offre, coupez une rondelle pour vous’, comme il m’aurait offert un rond de saucisson. [...] J’ai pris un tout petit mais ce petit est coupé je lui ai laissé la forme arrondie par accident du tronc [...] Il a une épaisseur qui rempli la main d’un honnête homme [...] 10 cm d’épaisseur. L’angle arrondi a été fait non pas par un architecte mais par un artisan qui a donné le coup de râpe nécessaire. Pour que ce soit sensible, que ce soit un outil que la main recherche, auquel elle offre ses caresses&quot;: Le Corbusier. (1951, January 26). [Radio interview]. FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">18</p>: Wohnbedarf. (1952, September 12). [Letter to Le Corbusier]. F1-3-244-001, FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">19</p>: Annick Texier, Aurélia Azema &quot;Analyse et identification du mobilier métallique&quot; Rapport provisoire, pôle métal du LRMH, 2017 (FLC, Paris, France).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">20</p>: Le Corbusier. (1919, October 8). [Letter to his father]. R1-6-72, FLC, Paris, France. &quot;Meubles arrivés en gare mais non encore livrés&quot;: Le Corbusier. (1919, November 16). [Letter to his father]. R1-6-77, FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">21</p>: It should be remembered for the roofs, the repair of a waterproofing was carried out in order to resolve the numerous degradations and the insertion of an insulator following the realization of a thermal study; and on the façades all the locks have been preserved and restored. Only the non-original glass brick sections have been returned.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">22</p>: Le Corbusier owned a Savoy vase by Alvar and Aino Aalto, which he saw when he visited the Finland Pavilion at the 1937 International Exhibition of Arts and Techniques in Modern Life in Paris: &quot;Hier en passant au Pavillon, j’ai demandé le prix d’un vase [...] Mon ambition serait d’avoir pour hommage un de ces vases [...]. Ce vase placé chez moi pourrait être d’une publicité éventuelle pour vous&quot;: Le Corbusier. (1937, October 12). [Letter to Mister Harl, architecte c/o Pavillon de Finland]. E1-4-7-001, FLC, Paris, France. The Artek company, founded by Alvar and Aino Aalto in order to publish their own creations, furniture, lighting, responds to Le Corbusier: &quot;avec votre permission ce serait un plaisir pour la société Artek et pour Aalto de pouvoir vous offrir gratuitement le vase en question, seulement les frais de douane seraient à votre charge&quot;. ARTEK. (1937, October 22). [Letter to Le Corbusier]. E1-4-6-001, FLC, Paris, France. This vase will never leave the dining room table.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">23</p>: The work on the choice of the colors and restitution of the oil emulsion paintings is accessible in the documentary film: Lemaire (2018).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">24</p>: Among the series furniture, it is necessary to quote the Thonet armchairs in curved wood: the old ones which are with the right of the dressing table of Yvonne and the office, and the more recent ones around the table of the dining room.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">25</p>: &quot;La première phase de travaux, livrée en septembre 2013, portait sur le corps central qui comprenait, notamment, le vestibule, le hall-salon, la salle à manger des parents et l’escalier d’honneur. Nous devions répondre à deux principaux objectifs : restituer et restaurer le décor en s’attachant aux vestiges existants, et ce, pour éviter de réaliser un pastiche, et intégrer au mieux les adaptations liées aux règlementations d’une établissement recevant du public (ERP), afin que le visiteur ait la sensation de rentrer dans une habitation plutôt que dans un espace patrimonial&quot; (Goutal 2014).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">26</p>: Arthur Ruegg: &quot;Pour E 1027, après les premiers tâtonnements, c’est le principe d’une reconstruction à l’identique qui a été retenue et cela débouche sur une scénographie totalement convaincante pour les visiteurs&quot; (2012). See also the article with the inventory by Renaud Barrès allowing to identify the elements of furniture and of second-oeuvre completely or partially restored (2021, p. 255 and 228).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">27</p>: Studies for the restoration of the Immeuble Molitor‘s façades are in progress and the work should begin in 2022, under the control of Pierre-Antoine Gatier, architecte en chef des Monuments historiques. 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">28</p>: &quot;en plein danger devant les vandales de la co-propriété&quot;: Le Corbusier. (1962, October 25). [Letter to André Malraux]. E2 14. FLC, Paris, France. The apartment-studio was protected in 1972 and the Molitor building since 1990, and since 2016 it is on the WHL with sixteen other architectural works of Le Corbusier. </p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Du côté de chez Fred, Charlotte Perriand</em>, Perriand, C..  (1989, December 15). Antenne 2</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Barrès, R. (2021). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>E-1027, Renaissance d’une maison en bord de mer</em>. Editions du Patrimoine</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Desmoulins, C. (2018). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>L’Appartement-atelier de Le Corbusier</em>. Carapace Édition</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Gandini, B., Mengin, C., &amp; Richard, M. (2017). Le Corbusier : l’œuvre à l’épreuve de sa restauration. In <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Actes des XIX Rencontre de la FLC</em>. Edition de la Villette.</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Gandini, B., &amp; Mengin, C. (2018). L’appartement de Le Corbusier, au 24 {NC}. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Monumental – “Dossier Le patrimoine des années 1925-1935”</em> (2), 16–19</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Goutal, M. (2014). La restauration des intérieurs de la Villa Cavrois, Croix. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Monumental</em></voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Graf, F., &amp; Marino, G. (2014). L’appartement-atelier de Le Corbusier, 24 {NC}, 1931 – 2014, étude patrimoniale et recommandations. In  (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Rapport d’étude. Laboratoire des Techniques et de la Sauvegarde de l’Architecture Moderne</em> (pp. 16–18). </voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Graf, F., &amp; Marino, G. (2017). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Les multiples vies de l’appartement-atelier de Le Corbusier</em>. Presses polytechniques et universitaires romandes</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Hubert, M.-O., Hall, C., &amp; Schroeter, J. (2015). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Étude des polychromies, bois et éléments métalliques du mobilier, appartement-atelier de Le Corbusier 24 {NC}</em>. Fondation Le Corbusier</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Koering, E. (2010). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Eileen Gray et Charlotte Perriand dans les années 1920 et la question de l’intérieur corbuséen. Essai d’analyse et de mise en perspective</em> [phdthesis]. Université Versailles-Saint-Quentin-en-Yvelines</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Koering, E. (2015). Le Corbusier et la construction d’un intérieur androgyne. Taylorisme domestique et mesure féminine dans l’intérieur corbuséen de la seconde moitié des années 20. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Histoire de l’art</em> (76)</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Koering, E. (2020). L’intérieur moderne corbuséen dans les années 1920. Théories et programmes. In <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier. L’art de se loger et de le dire</em>. Presses Universitaires.</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (2011). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier : Correspondance. Tome 1: Lettres à la famille 1900-1925</em> (R. Baudoui, &amp; A. Dercelles, Ed.; Vol. 1). In-folio</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Lemaire, O. (2018). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Chez Le Corbusier</em>, Coproduction Imagissime/Fondation Le Corbusier. https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ldBCotxOtY8</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Ruegg, A. (2012). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier, meubles et intérieurs, 1905-1965</em>. Scheidegger &amp; Spiess</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Sbriglio, J. (1996). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Immeuble 24 N.C. et appartement Le Corbusier</em>. Birkhäuser</voce>
</root>