<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">11 Innovative Conservation Policies for 20th-Century Architectural Heritage</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Ugo Carughi</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Former President of Docomomo Italia</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">The forms of protection of 20th-century architecture provided for by Italian Legislative Decree no. 42/2004 are part of the more general regulatory conditions concerning the listing of assets that can be defined as <em aid:cstyle="italic">cultural</em>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In article 10 of the Code of Cultural Heritage and Landscape, the diverse list of very specific categories interposed with more general categories (almost as if they were only examples), with various adjectives of cultural interest, is confusing, misleading or incomprehensible, particularly for users, who must comply with regulations regarding assets that pertain to them or are their property; it is also limiting, since it is always the case that in specifying too much one risks forgetting something. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Simple <em aid:cstyle="italic">interest</em> is attributable to immovable and movable property belonging to public entities or non-profit private legal entities; to villas, parks and gardens; to public squares, streets, roads and other urban open spaces; to rural architecture. <em aid:cstyle="italic">Particularly important interest</em> can, on the other hand, be attributed to privately owned immovable and movable property, paradoxically relating the absolute value of cultural interest to the contingent market mechanisms of the property system. Finally, <em aid:cstyle="italic">exceptional interest</em> has always been limited to book collections belonging to private individuals and to collections or series of objects. However, the law of 4 August 2017, paragraph no. 175, introduced in article 10 of the Code the new paragraph 3 d-bis, inserting among cultural assets “those things, no matter to whom they belong, that have an exceptional artistic, historical, archaeological or ethno-anthropological interest for the integrity and completeness of the Nation’s cultural heritage”. Unlike most of the other categories, for which the seventy-year rule applies, fifty years are specified as the protection limit for these assets.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">These different classifications would suggest different ways or degrees of protection and enhancement, which are not, however, contemplated. To these are added, increasing the confusion, the <em aid:cstyle="italic">particular artistic value</em> introduced by article 37 of the same Code and the <em aid:cstyle="italic">important artistic character</em> contemplated by Italian law no. 633/1941.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">11.2 The problematic regulations concerning the protection of 20th-century heritage</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Within this general framework, the protection of 20th-century works suffers from three additional limitations. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The first limit lies in the threshold of historicization for the so-called &quot;intrinsic&quot; restriction, set at 50 years by the Nasi law in 1902 and restated by the Rosati law in 1909 and the Bottai law in 1939. This was increased to 70 years only for publicly owned works from 2011 and extended to privately owned works in 2017 by Italian law 04.08.2017 no. 24, article 1, paragraph 175. This limit is accompanied by another concerning the author of the work who, if still alive, renders the ‘intrinsic’ restriction inapplicable. This last regulation, which is understandable for movable works associated with commercialization and, therefore, with the author’s rights, does not hold true for immovable works, whose author is generally not the owner, but, while alive and not dead, can be very helpful in guiding new interventions on the work. Consider, for example, the Sydney Opera House, commissioned to Jørn Oberg Utzon in 1956, started in 1966 and completed in 1973. In 1993, the NSWG commissioned Australian architect James Semple Kerr to carry out a restoration project. In 1996, the Conservation Council of the Sydney Opera House was established. However, the master plan prepared in 1997 would have irreparably altered the work. In 1998, following the dissolution of the Conservation Council, the renovation plan was entrusted to architect Richard Johnson, who brought in Utzon in 1999. In 2002, two documents were drafted, a short-term plan by Johnson, <em aid:cstyle="italic">Venue Improvement Plan</em>, and a long-term plan by Utzon and Johnson, <em aid:cstyle="italic">Utzon Design Principles</em>. Another example is Walter Gropius’ house, built in Massachusetts in 1938 and inhabited by Gropius until his death (1969), by his wife Ise and his sister until 1983, the year of Ise’s death. Ise transferred ownership to the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Preservation of New England Antiquities</em> in 1974, while continuing to live there. Her contribution, which can also be attributed to her husband’s legacy of ideas, was fundamental in adapting to the new function<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The second limit consists of the narrow and limited, as well as often improper, application of the restriction – also direct – referred to as ‘external relational’ (article 10, paragraph 3, letter d), in which neither the time nor the name of the author counts (e.g. the balcony from which Garibaldi spoke, or the Greco bar, in Rome, frequented for a certain period by important artists). Law tends to consider the work eligible for restriction when it is connected to a specific historical episode or figure rather than to a particular cultural climate, or to a school of expression, or to a construction technology, as the regulation would more directly suggest. In this regard, think of Nervi’s works for the 17th Summer Olympics in Rome, which are connected to this historic event. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">But even this is not always the case. Often the work is listed in relation to architectural culture, as the regulation dictates. However, these are almost always cases that would have merited the restriction because of inherent interest, which was not applied due to the time limit. Consider, for example, the bridge over the Basento river in Potenza by Sergio Musmeci, built at the end of the 1960s and listed by the Ministry of Culture on 2 December 2003, a little more than thirty years after its construction (fig. 1). The restriction report states: &quot;The uniqueness of the work is evident ... and it can certainly be considered one of the most representative works of Italian architecture&quot;. Uniqueness pertains to an &quot;intrinsic&quot; restriction which, however, was not applicable because of the time threshold of 50 years that was in force at the time, while the second pertains to a ‘relational’ restriction, the only one possible.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">A similar case is that of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Casa alle Zattere</em>, built in Venice from 1953 to 1958 by Ignazio Gardella (fig. 2). After an attempt to obtain a restriction between 1993 and 1995 under the copyright law, a protective measure was finally granted on 14 March 2001, forty-three years after its completion, <em aid:cstyle="italic">due to its value as a testimony to contemporary architectural culture</em>. This value did not prevent the addition of two openings on the top floor of the façade.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Similar considerations apply to Giancarlo De Carlo’s former Colonia Marina (summer camp complex), built in Riccione between 1961 and 1963 (fig. 3), which was restricted in June 2009, after forty-six years. The detailed restriction report comprehensively highlights the work’s connection with the history of Italian architecture, framing it within the most significant period of De Carlo’s career, with &quot;references to Franco Albini’s precision, Ignazio Gardella’s compositional elements, Carlo Scarpa’s volumes freely arranged in relation to the outside world, etc&quot;<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The third limit is article 20 of Italian law no. 633 of 1941 on &quot;Copyright&quot;. It is now settled case law that the author, during his/her lifetime, is entitled to review the integrity of the work. However, the heirs can only claim authorship without being able to make any changes. Nevertheless, this is a law that protects the rights of the author and only indirectly those of the work, which, by extension, is given temporary protection while the author is alive.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Finally, a fourth limit relates to the Code. Recently, article 55 bis of Italian Legislative Decree no. 76/2020 converted into law 11.09.2020 no. 120 has been enacted, which makes it possible to proceed by way of exception to articles 10, 12, 13, 136 and 140 for the sole category, it should be noted, of sports facilities. This provision was the premise for introducing, for this type of work, an exception to the already adopted declarations of cultural or public interest.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">By decreeing that &quot;the need to preserve the testimonial value... takes precedence over the ... functionality ... for the purposes of public safety, health and security&quot;, article 55 bis establishes, by way of legislation, a hierarchy between constitutionally protected values such as, on the one hand, <em aid:cstyle="italic">public health</em> (article 32 of the Italian Constitution) and, on the other, <em aid:cstyle="italic">cultural interest</em> (article 9 of the Italian Constitution). Balancing public interests is however a primary concern of the Public Administration and must be resolved in the specifics of individual cases, not in a legal text. Considering, moreover, the precedence of cultural interests over other public interests, sanctioned by countless judgments of the Council of State.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The Ministry is limited to specifying the parts of the work that should be preserved or reproduced, including &quot;in shapes and sizes that differ from the original&quot;: an implicit form of self-conditioning of the Public Administration, which should be entitled to express its opinion with total autonomy.</p>
<h2 aid:pstyle="H2">11.3 Some possible solutions</h2>
<ol aid:pstyle="ol-numbers"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">‘Serial assets’</strong>. The term ‘serial assets’, which appeared in the 1970s in official UNESCO documents, but remained absent from national legislation, was consciously formulated in 1980 when the guidelines of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Intergovernmental Committee for the Protection of the World Cultural and Natural Heritage</em> were drawn up following the creation of the World Heritage List in 1978: &quot;serial assets may include interconnected [...] elements [...] provided that the complete series – and not necessarily the individual parts of it – has exceptional universal value&quot;. After the creation of the DOCOMOMO association in 1988, the 1992 inventory promoted a list of 20th-century architecture and in 1997 a proposal was submitted to the <em aid:cstyle="italic">UNESCO World Heritage Center</em> containing assets that were not individual, but grouped into the works of F. Ll. Wright, Le Corbusier, Alvar Aalto and L. Mies Van Der Rohe. Thus, at a time when the number of requests for the inclusion of groups of assets was increasing, rising to around one-third of the number for individual assets, at the 2006 conference in Ankara, DOCOMOMO International proposed the criterion of organizing a series no longer from a geographical (route) or typological standpoint but, more generally, from a thematic approach. Among others, ten works by F. Ll. Wright and seventeen by Le Corbusier, most recently Italian architecture in Asmara, etc., have been included as UNESCO heritage<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>. ‘Intrinsic’ interest and ‘relational’ interest directly refer to the three principles of Historiography: ‘Uniqueness’, which relates to the first; ‘Causality’ and ‘Selectivity’, which relate to the second<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p>. ‘Causality’ can establish a work’s connection with related external circumstances, including other works that can be linked to it. ‘Selectivity’ determines the selection of those external circumstances and works. It is often possible to attribute cultural interest not to individual works of architecture, but to groups of them, which, since they are comparable in terms of common features and the fact that they are no longer being built, form closed ‘series’ in the sense intended by G. Kubler<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>. Consider, for example, Riccardo Morandi’s standardized cable-stayed viaducts. Or Nervi’s works for the Olympics (fig. 4); or those of the same engineer from Sondrio with their vaulted or domed roofs; or the museum installations of the 1950s and 1960s by Scarpa, Michelucci, Albini, etc.; or the residential architecture of Ponti, Albini, Gardella, and so on. Each work can be linked to others in a kind of ‘network’ in which recognition of the interest of each one can recall that of all the others, reverberating through a ‘protection of the whole’, rather than of a specific work. The ability to consider the reciprocal relationship between several works would allow their contemporary historicization, excluding abstract time barriers. A number of advantages could be gained from this. The regional offices of the Italian Ministry of Culture, for example, when issuing measures on works that have been recognized as having common values, even though they were built in distant places and under different circumstances, could refer to criteria for conservative intervention or renovation that have already been adopted and tested for some of them. It would thus be possible to ensure a consistent approach that mitigates the inevitable discretionary nature of opinions expressed on a ‘case-by-case’ basis and of self-referential recovery and/or restoration projects. A kind of evolving technical/administrative literature would be gradually developed, closely linked to critical/historical aspects, which are essential references for institutional action. Heritage would also be perceived by public opinion as being more aware of the relationships between different expressions of the same cultural identity.
</ol>
<ol aid:pstyle="ol-numbers-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">The Conservation Plan.</strong> With respect to Italian legislation, as well as that of other countries, the conservation plan should be considered an intermediate step between the <em aid:cstyle="italic">declaration of cultural interest</em>, which is limited to indicating why the property should be protected without generally giving operational guidance, and the recovery and restoration project, which, in the absence of preliminary guidelines, is subject to conditions arising from the specific circumstances and the discretion of the institutional bodies. For many stadiums, it appears that the time has come to either pull the plug or make an irreversible transformation in the face of the economic and management pressures that now dominate the sector. From an economic standpoint, which can have a significant impact on their fate, “three attributes characterize cultural assets [...] in a comprehensive manner: I) materiality; II) the fact they constitute historical evidence; III) non-reproducibility <a aid:cstyle="span">…</a> relates to the uniqueness of the asset”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">6</p>. From this standpoint, the public interest of an asset does not derive from its ownership status, but from its <em aid:cstyle="italic">non-rivalry</em> and <em aid:cstyle="italic">non-excludability</em> from consumption; the former meaning that public assets can be consumed by several individuals at the same time; the latter meaning that it is not possible to limit their benefits to just a few people. The case of stadiums, as with theaters, museums, etc., has its own distinctive aspects: <em aid:cstyle="italic">non-rivalry</em> and <em aid:cstyle="italic">non-excludability</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">7</p>, which would determine their purely public character, are limited by the capacity of these facilities. However, ‘exteriors’, which are often the most representative part in the relationship with the city, can indeed be considered entirely public because they can be appreciated by everyone without exception, such as the façade of a monumental building, a statue, an obelisk, etc. Formulating the Conservation Plan requires, first and foremost, knowledge of the work and its history by assessing the original design and execution, the work actually carried out and all subsequent alterations, as well as a survey of its current condition. Guidelines for the correct restoration and adaptation of the structures can then be defined. It would therefore be highly desirable for the conservation plan to be included in the national protection regulations as an indispensable reference point for a coherent policy of intervention and management of cultural assets, balancing out the <em aid:cstyle="italic">community values</em> that can be attributed to these structures.
</ol>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Carughi_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. S. Musmeci, Bridge over the Basento, Potenza. Late 1960s</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Carughi_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. I. Gardella, Cicogna Condominium (Casa alle Zattere), Venice, 1953-58</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Carughi_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. G. De Carlo, former Enel summer camp complex, Riccione, 1961-63</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Carughi_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. Pier Luigi Nervi’s works for the 1960 Rome Olympics</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: Carughi (2017, p. 28).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: See Carughi (2012, pp. 53-92).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: d’Orgeix (2012, pp. 27-36).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: De Fusco (1970).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: Kubler (1972, pp. 67-76).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">6</p>: Di Maio (2019, pp. 16 ff.).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">7</p>: Di Maio (2019, pp. 99 ff.).</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Carughi, U. (2012). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Maledetti Vincoli. La tutela dell&#39;architettura contemporanea</em>. Allemandi</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Carughi, U. (2017). Contemporary Architecture and the Idea of Protection. In U. Carughi, &amp; M. Visone (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Time Frames: Conservation Policies for Twentieth-Century Architectural Heritage</em> (pp. 23–33). Routledge Taylor &amp; Francis Group</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>De Fusco, R. (1970). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Storia e struttura: teoria della storiografia architettonica</em>. Edizioni Scientifiche Italiane</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Di Maio, A. (2019). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Economia del patrimonio e delle attività culturali: Stumenti e analisi</em>. Hoepli</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Kubler, G. (1989). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>The shape of time</em>. Einaudi</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>d’Orgeix, È. (2012). {SerieMania} ou comment repenser la mise en série du patrimoine du {XXe} siècle. In M. Casciato, &amp; È. d’Orgeix (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Architectures Modernes. L’Emergence d’un Patrimoine</em> (pp. 27–36). Mardaga</voce>
</root>