<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">Part 2. Art and visions</h1>
<h1 aid:pstyle="H1">18 My House is a Le Corbusier</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Cristian Chironi</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Artist</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening"><em aid:cstyle="italic">My House is a Le Corbusier</em> is a project featuring the numerous domestic structures around the world designed by Le Corbusier, in which the artist resides for a period.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Both a work in progress and a crucible of ideas, research and exhibition – not to mention a living experience – <em aid:cstyle="italic">My house is a Le Corbusier</em> is intended to evolve over the long term and culminate in the totality of all the experiences that Cristian Chironi will undergo while actually living for variable periods of time in the many homes designed by Le Corbusier around the world.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The long-term project (which will unfold over the potential arc of 30 habitable homes by Corbusier in 12 countries) is a performance, stretched out over time, house after house. “Pilgrim houses”, inextricably tied to the movement and the intersection of diverse geographies and cultures.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The point of departure is a real historical episode: in the late 1960s, the Sardinian artist Costantino Nivola, who enjoyed a great friendship and collaboration with Le Corbusier, stopping by his hometown of Orani (also Chironi’s birthplace), entrusted his brother’s family with the construction of “Chischeddu” on a design by the great architect, with the hope that he and his sons, masons all of them, would scrupulously follow the plans. But they failed to understand the importance of this. Sometime later, returning from Long Island, Nivola discovered that the house they had built did not correspond at all to the specifications which, as the entire family protested, “had neither doors nor windows and looked more like a shack than a house”. Nivola reacted by seizing the plans, which have since been lost. The house, which still stands today in Orani, built with a preference for low-brow functionality over the modernist vision of the architect, reflects only the ‘mood’, if that, of the original concept.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Taking inspiration from this episode, Chironi identifies the narrative potential for an analysis of a series of relationships in the contemporary, tied to the concepts of communication, reading and interpretation, with the consequent linguistic and socio-political implications. Falling, in this historical period of precarious economic stability, in the impossibility of owning one’s own home, bartering the freedom to live in the houses designed by Le Corbusier around the world.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Chironi turns these houses into “privileged vantage points” to better understand how the legacy of Le Corbusier is perceived today, and in what condition the “home of man” currently finds itself. A reading of architecture through storytelling and the direct experience of its spatio-temporal dimension, where one can discuss and see the artist at work, partake in events, consult the assembled material or simply drink a coffee.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Chironi lived in the Esprit Nouveau Pavilion in Bologna, in the Studio-Apartment in Rue Nungesser et Coli in Paris, with two passages in the city to the Swiss Pavilion and La Cité de Refuge, in Apartment 50 at the Unitè d&#x27;Habitation in Marseille, Curutchet House in La Plata, in Chandigarh in one of the rooms of Pierre Jeanneret&#x27;s house, now converted into a museum, in apartment 258 of the Unitè d&#x27;Habitation in Berlin, at Villa Perret-Jeanneret in La Chaux de Fonds.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">For Chironi, living the architecture of Le Corbusier is like living in a work of art. It is through living that a benefit is brought to the house, restoring its right climate. The inhabitant is the thermometer that protects the house by living it.</p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Chironi_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>figs. 1-2. *My House is a Le Corbusier (Esprit Nouveau)*, 2015. The first stop in this geography of habitation is the Esprit Nouveau Pavilion in Bologna. In the image the first phase of the residency with the creation of works of art and live events within the architecture. (© Cristian Chironi and FLC for the work of Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Chironi_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. *My House is a Le Corbusier (Studio-Apartment), 2015*. The second stage of this geography of habitat settles in Le Corbusier’s apartment-workshop which occupies the top two floors of the Molitor building. Chironi tried to get in touch with the living conditions and individual stories of the neighbors of the apartment, discovering how they adapted the dwelling to their way of life and raising the question of living together. (© Cristian Chironi and FLC for the work of Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. *My House is a Le Corbusier (Cité de Refuges)*, 2014. Series of photographs taken by the artist during the demolition and restoration of the Cité de Refuges. (© Cristian Chironi and FLC for the work of Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_05.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>figs. 5-6. *My House is a Le Corbusier (Appartement 50 - Unité d’Habitation)*, 2015. Appartement 50 is the third stage of Chironi’s geography of inhabitation. Looked at through the present time, the Unité d’Habitation acquires further significance. Today there is a sense of detachment between architecture and society, the tendency is to invest in spectacle rather than essential living necessities. Living in the Unité d’Habitation in a time of forced migrations and asylum seeking, becomes even more valuable to the artist. He calls for architecture and politics of construction to take an active role and think about new and affordable housing solutions. (© Cristian Chironi and FLC for the work of Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_06.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_07.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 7. *My House is a Le Corbusier (Casa Curutchet)*, 2016. The design of Casa Curutcher is contemporary and in continuity with the ideas developed with the Unité d’Habitation in Marseille. Chironi adopted the same approach used in the previous events by focusing on the relationship between house and visitor, on the confrontation between different languages, on the impact of direct experience on the artist’s work acting thus as a measure and thermostat of the present. By repeatedly redefining his lifestyle, challenging the linguistic and cultural codes he is used to, exceeding the distinction of static and mobile living, Chironi research will start from the notions of hospitality of and interaction with the audience, and aim at finding a way to live the world. (© Cristian Chironi and FLC for the work of Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_08.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 8. *My House is a Le Corbusier (Pierre Jeanneret Museum)* 2017. The house is located in the fifth sector of the city of Chandigarh and was designed by Pierre Jeannette, cousin of Le Corbusier. It is now converted into a museum. Chandigarh blends all of the architectural studies carried out by Le Corbusier in his travels and is considered his masterpiece, an environment in which the primacy of the public upon the private space is eliminated in the construction of a work of art on an urban scale. The residence in Chandigarh aims to overcome that last remnant of the frontier that separates permanence from mobility. House and city, corridor and street, interior and exterior are all on the same level. Walking about the city therefore creates an entrance into a new context, an adaptation to the culture and to the environment, absorbing it, transforming it and re-recreating it. A vision of the house in the form of a city and vice versa, to which corresponds the daily creation of documents, artifacts, actions, and interventions. Chandigarh’s future is in the hands of its inhabitants, and in their ability to fathom living in a space that offers no further possibility for development without risking its disfigurement. (© Cristian Chironi and FLC for the work of Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_09.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 9. *My House is a le Corbusier (Apartment 258 – Unité d’Habitation type Berlin)*, 2019. Apartment 258, now owned by Henrik and Natalia Svedlund, is the result of some changes made by the architect Philipp Mohr between 2016-18, with the intention of respecting the original plans of Le Corbusier. The building and its rooms were repainted by combining the architectural polychromy proposed by Le Corbusier in 1931, a range of colors composed of 43 “architectural colors” in 12 atmospheres. The same palette was used by Chironi to customize his Chameleon, Fiat 127 Special car so called because of its ability to change color according to the building in front of which it stops. The work accompanies the artist in his movements. He was invited by the owners to live with them for a specific time, wanted to include the spouses Svedlund in the work-project giving him an active role and transforming them, Henrik artist-musician and Natalia brewing engineer, as real instruments, inspired by them for the realization of his works. (© Cristian Chironi and FLC for the work of Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_10.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>figs. 10-11. *My House is in Le Corbusier (Villa Jeanneret-Perret)*, 2021. The Villa Jeanneret-Perret is Le Corbusier’s first independent project. Built in 1912 in La Chaux-de-Fonds for his parents, clock face enameller father and pianist mother, who lived there for five years until 1917. Chironi has chosen to live in the attic of the house where he will have a simple bed and a work table, for a deliberately humble stay and as a return to the sources of the project. The musical performance My sound is a Le Corbusier was born from a sound laboratory which involves three musicians, Diane Frutschi, Capucine Seuret, and Francesco Brasini. The first two musicians proposed a piece played on the piano which belonged to the architect&#x27;s mother. An unpublished score was written by converting the measures of the villa into frequencies, and then into music. At the same time, Francesco Brasini created a collection of sound samples of clock sounds with which he plays and interacts live with the pianists. (© Cristian Chironi and FLC for the work of Le Corbusier)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
<Image href="File:///Chironi_img_11.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
</figure>

</root>