<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">13 Carlo Scarpa, the House for Loredana Balboni in Venice</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Roberta Martinis</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Scuola Universitaria Professionale della Svizzera Italiana</h5>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Francesco Magnani</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">architect</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">The house Carlo Scarpa worked on in 1964 to a commission from Loredana Balboni is set in one of the buildings owned by the Balboni family, Ca’ Marioni-Mainella<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">The neo-Renaissance palazzo designed by Ludovico Cadorin (1858) stands on the Grand Canal at the corner of the Rio di San Trovaso.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Loredana Balboni (1920-2013), collector and art dealer, was active in cultural circles in Italy in the sixties. For her Venetian home in the family’s palazzo, an apartment on two levels with an independent entrance on the ground floor, Loredana Balboni initially chose the Venetian architect Paolo De Marzi. In 1962 he drafted a first project, obtaining the necessary building permits for the work, which envisioned a large spiral staircase connecting the ground and first floors.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Balboni wanted a home that would represent her appropriately in the social circles she moved in, and showcase her collection of artworks. In 1964, Loredana Balboni turned to the most illustrious Venetian architect and the one most qualified to take over the commission: Carlo Scarpa, at the peak of his career.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The work involved tackling an irregular area traversing the building, measuring some 9.5 meters wide with a depth of more than 18 meters, extending between a private garden giving access to the house, and the view to the east over the Grand Canal, while taking advantage of the pre-existing structures and the provisions of De Marzi’s project. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">From the first drawings Scarpa focused on the principal axis connecting the two extremities of the house. He conceived it as a freely and plastically configured spatial sequence. It was immediately clear that he intended to create a perspective vista pointing towards the water, anticipating for the visitor the shimmering glow that fills the living room (fig. 1).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In Venice, as a rule, the ground floors are not inhabited. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">During the years when Scarpa was designing the Balboni apartment, the <em aid:cstyle="italic">acqua granda</em>, the floodwaters that rose 194 cm high and devastated the city in 1966, still lay in the future. And the possibility of being able to live at water level and enjoy all its most surprising effects must have seemed a rare opportunity to be explored and grasped.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The new project is announced by a composite avantcorps, in which two short wings frame the entrance to the house in a negative recess. From here, all the service rooms are arranged on the left, which in turn have an independent entrance, and on the right the dining room: a space enclosed in itself, initially conceived as an elongated octagonal form, and overlooking the garden with a bow window, which is nevertheless responded to by the lateral erosion of the mixtilinear window according to a tension between opposites - rough and smooth, heavy and light, dark and bright - which suggests the strategy governing the interior. The theme is making broad what is cramped, and Scarpa’s approach to the design of Casa Balboni focuses on this need.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">On the ground floor, Scarpa studied an access sequence through a vestibule squeezed in between the wing of the service rooms and the dining room and leading to a richly designed longitudinal passage. After this dark and compressed space, Scarpa inserted, as a counterpoint, a short interval at double height to mark the start of a <em aid:cstyle="italic">promenade architecturale</em>, which models the movements, forming the prelude to the experience of the upper floor. In this way, the height of the low corridor below this interval, with a surprise move, was extended to 5.20 meters, so making it possible to channel quantities of natural light into the most shadowy part of the house. And there is more to it than this because, while the gaze from the entrance is drawn towards the Grand Canal, the device introduces a counterpoint to the dynamics of vision (fig. 2). </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The removal of matter entered into a dialogue, always in a mutual resonance of soft forms, with the device connecting the floors themselves: the monumental circular staircase, already ideally prepared, but studied by Scarpa as a plastic and dynamic object in Lasa marble, modeled as a classical sculpture and resting on a circular stylobate, in which the countercurrent steps fan out around a massive cylindrical post. Midway in the longitudinal passage, the helical staircase, introduces a spatial comment transversal to the direction indicated (fig. 3). But, what should remain firm - the post of the staircase - appears split, and from the top of this a rotating sculpture emerges (from the Zanon workshop), while at the base the revolution is paradoxically accentuated by the thin slabs of the treads of the steps, from which the risers are eliminated, curving and continuing to scroll towards nothingness. In this way, by corroding its figurative sense and tectonic quality, the extremely fluid path of the staircase, in its perfectly regular progress within a circular perimeter, appears unequivocally undermined at both ends.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In a continuous dialogue between different scales during the design, the space on the first floor is defined as a single organism between the garden and the Grand Canal, rich in events at the center, which expands and compresses in height and depth, with the sloping planes and uprights of the floor, and extends towards the two large, luminous extremities. Taut mobile panels with multiple apertures, like scenic backdrops, define different intervals and different fields of vision; probing the fleeting boundary between form and its possibilities adding further mutability to a space of movement (fig. 4).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The walkway appears as a slender cutout element, its outline replicating the form of the lobed canopy in the Sculpture Garden of the Biennale (1952), though here the play of gravity is made emphatic and gradually more mobile by the large spiral staircase. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the many drawings of the internal lightwells at Casa Balboni, which are investigated both separately and together with the other presences that interact with them – the circular staircase, the shape of the steps leading to the rooms – we see sculpture, modeling prevail in an attempt to literally give form to the movement in space, enveloping and accompanying it. 
Initially Scarpa explored the possibility of dividing the long arch in two, within a single continuous perimeter, until each of the two “voids” was endowed with its own form, in the quest for the “right lines”, for a three-dimensional device, one capable of accompanying the compressions and dilations of the gaze and movements towards the two extremities of the route. The space is in this respect conceived as a solid body, therefore modelled, with its sculptural compendium in the use of refined polished surfaces through the use of marmorino and smoothed plaster.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In his lecture <em aid:cstyle="italic">Arredare</em>, which was held while he was designing the Balboni house (1964), Scarpa openly raised the question of the relationship between mass and space. </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">“The sense of space is not conveyed by a pictorial order but always by physical phenomena, meaning by matter, by the sense of heaviness, by the weight of the wall. For this reason I affirm that it is openings, gaps and transitions that create the spatial relations”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>. </p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Ten years later the reasoning remained equally taut. </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">“Within a physical space one enters a spatial world, one that is tactile, harmonic. To begin with, one could imagine that that space is a solid parallelepiped and we are going to hollow out its inner parts to take advantage of its mass”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>. </p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">Ludovico Quaroni recalled how Scarpa:</p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">“measured thicknesses and caressed surfaces with his eyes and hand, to get to know their roughness and grain intimately, even tactilely, with the palm of his hand open placed on curved surfaces, to be accompanied in their convex turns, or with the back of the fingers when the surfaces were concave”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p>.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">On the ground floor, the tension in the sequence of spatial compressions and expansions dissolves into the void of the living room towards the canal. A single interior, open for the entire width of the front, it receives light reflected from the water before it. The space of the living room, elegant and reflective, is extended outside, almost duplicated, in the large terrace on the canal, provided with the same kind of floor as the interior of the house. The Grand Canal is also the space of the project, replacing with an infinite quantity, naturally sonorous, those pools of water that Scarpa usually placed at the foot of his private houses.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">And it is with the water and its reflections that the whole ground floor of the house has its most intimate relationship. Loredana Balboni described the house as “vibrant with light and gold”, a glorious space, dematerialized through light and in constant change. The materials and their installation contribute to this quality of the space: the stucco lustro on the walls and ceilings, ivory white, velvety and translucent, described by Scarpa “as shiny as silk”. In this way empty space was signified by a vibrant chromatic modulation with the variations in time and light, with iridescent and mysterious tones, until it became soft and tremulous (fig. 5).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The clear, very smooth material of the masonry and ceiling is set off by the stone paving, rough and colored. Slabs of Prun stone are arranged in courses parallel to the Grand Canal and with the joints staggered to mark the central axis of the corridor, with a broken line that creates an intermittent rhythm. They form a series of “carpets” encrusted within shaped profiles in Lasa marble that graphically organize the space of movement.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the place where the vertical planes of the walls meet the horizontal planes of the floor, where the modeling and carving join, a skillful pause is inserted: a horizontal groove in the form of a scotia molding hollowed out of the border in Lasa marble. The discontinuity introduced by the scotia molding in Casa Balboni speaks of Scarpa’s ability, “a master of the Byzantine age, who accidentally lived in the twentieth century”, to be “anciently modern&quot;.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In 1968, with the construction work begun and after the episode of high water in November 1966, which certainly flooded the house, damaging what had been done up to that moment, an intense ideological discussion arose on Scarpa’s project, following the severe judgments of the client’s Roman friends. This created a situation that saw on one side a group of politically engaged artists, on the other a <em aid:cstyle="italic">Byzantine master</em>, and in the middle a client who was perceptive but perhaps not sufficiently prepared.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The slackening of Scarpa’s interest in this commission, as witnessed by the correspondence preserved, led to Loredana Balboni&#x27;s decision to commission the young Giovanni Soccol, a recent graduate of the IUAV where he presented his thesis with Scarpa, to finish the house that the latter had abandoned, and which he would never again visit. It is quite likely that Scarpa in his heart needed to feel like the architect of the Katsura Imperial Villa, Kobori Enshu, who, according to the legend: “accepted the commission on three conditions: no budget limit, no deadline and no interference until the building was completed”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Towards the end of 2017, it was possible to carry out the first surveys to start defining the project for the restoration of Casa Balboni.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The state of preservation of Carlo Scarpa&#x27;s intervention was unfortunately very bad at the time. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">All the walls and ceilings of the house, apart from those of the cloakroom, the service areas on the ground floor and the toilets, were originally finished with ivory-white Venetian-style stucco lucido (smooth and shiny stucco), made to the special recipes developed on several occasions by Carlo Scarpa with the Eugenio De Luigi workshop. The result was a setting that it was not difficult to imagine as magically bright, reflecting the light from the Grand Canal to create a continuously varying effect at different times of the day. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Unfortunately, over time the surfaces had undergone an inexorable yellowing, due to the nature of the components of the recipe used to make them, and the presence of constant tobacco smoke, so much so that the original color was actually appreciable only in a few limited areas. Added to this was irreparable damage to the internal surfaces of the living room, due to consolidation work on the condominium facade of the building on the Grand Canal, carried out with little attention and respect for the uniqueness of Casa Balboni.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Once overcame the astonishment at the precarious state of preservation of the building, which nevertheless retained its fascination and extraordinary quality intact, was possible to begin a study in depth of the extent of the original work, to organize the project of renovation and restoration as correctly as possible. Carlo Scarpa had designed the house using building techniques and technologies typical of the mid-sixties. The preliminary investigations made it possible to identify their characteristics. A complex reinforced concrete structure supports the distributive mezzanine level, characterized by two large irregular openings (fig. 6). In correspondence with the cloakroom and the dining room, the decking rests on point-to-point supports on the load-bearing brick walls of the whole building; these are consolidated at the base, above the foundational system, by a series of reinforced concrete bond beams. On the side opposite the entrance corridor, since the service area belonging to the kitchen is defined by a simple screen of closet walls and partitions of flimsy masonry, the structure is taken all the way to the facade of the building, with slender beams concealed by the false ceilings. The impost level of the ground floor is set 1.53 meters above mean sea level, and was created by superimposing a layer of pebbles on the existing floor system of the cellars, which originally occupied the ground floor of the building. Smoothed lean concrete was poured over it, then it was waterproofed with several layers of bitumen, over which was laid a bedding screed for the Prun stone slabs and the strips of Lasa marble used for the floor. The upper level concrete and masonry floors were made using prefabricated joists laid, as it was possible to verify with a cover meter, with a center distance of about 60 cm, and reinforced with longitudinal bars of 8–10 mm with a concrete cover 30–50 mm thick. The floors rest on the load-bearing walls, with the exception of the living area on the ground floor, where the original masonry spine was removed to create a large single room. Instead of this masonry, a system of four paired steel beams, probably IPE 140, was used as intermediate support for the joists, revealed by the presence of the coupled steel columns close to the facade towards the Grand Canal on the ground floor. The completion casting brought the load-bearing package of the floor to about 21 cm, and then a layer of about 4 cm of loose sand was laid on it to accommodate the piping of the utilities, as well as a completion screed in sand and cement of the same height. Given the limits of the analysis with the cover meter in tracing all the structural components, and since it was obviously impossible to carry out invasive investigations to gather more information, it was considered appropriate to carry out load tests to verify the state of conservation of the system’s performance, given that it was more than fifty years old. Testing on the two floors with the largest span in the living area consisted of filling two tanks with water to a height of 30 cm (with the total overload equal to 300 kg/sqm divided into load phases of 100 kg/sqm) and monitoring the degree of displacement with transducers located on the ground floor. The load tests gave positive results, but suggested it would be advisable to lighten the finishing package on the upper level, to reduce its weight and comply with the parameters required by current regulations, given the operating overloads. These assessments, together with the need to reinstall from scratch a large part of the utilities which were irreparably deteriorated, meant rebuilding the floors on the upper level. (The original solution, however, was apparently not completely resolved and was the source of some disagreement between Carlo Scarpa and Loredana Balboni). The finishing screed was laid a few millimeters from the edge of the shaped skirting boards in Lasa marble and forced the owner, when Scarpa abandoned the work without leaving any instructions, to lay carpeting, later replaced on the garden side only by a modest linoleum covering. The mediocre quality and state of preservation of these fittings led to examine the need to rethink the floors of the bedrooms, sitting rooms and closet on the first floor. After numerous exploratory studies, the design solution involved the use of a handcrafted parquet in solid oiled pear wood, with planks 10 cm wide, interspersed with 6 x 6 mm pure silver rods, refined inserts that mark their variable length in accordance with the installation, while they receive and reflect the light coming from the Grand Canal and the garden, which shimmers on their surfaces. In addition, on the restored shaped skirting boards in Lasa marble, a silver sealing strip defines a joint between the new floors and the original elements. In the closets this solution is embodied in a more highly articulated way, since these are transitional spaces with a reduced surface area, by using geometric elements specially designed, also in handcrafted parquet of oiled solid pear wood, combined with the use of smaller linear rods. The recomposition of the new flooring, now consisting of a “dry” substrate made from a layer of expanded clay and a double Sialite and OSB paneling, made it possible to reduce the permanent loads by about a hundred kilograms per square meter. Upgrading the system of utilities serving the home was also one of the most complex problems. The original construction technology left little margin for movement and interaction to create a new backbone cable routing. This made it necessary to reuse the existing routes, limiting the areas of intervention to a minimum, using some ducts made over time in the walls – whose original finishes had been damaged – to make good serious deficiencies in circuits no longer accessible. Fortunately, the house had been equipped with state-of-the-art systems for the day: in addition to a gas boiler serving a hot water winter heating system with cast iron terminals, housed in a low niche in the kitchen, a true equipment room had been designed near the cloakroom, which contained an air conditioning system ducted within the walls and serving the ground and first floors. The renewal of the system was therefore based on the decision to associate a refrigeration plant with a water heat pump with a new air exchange and treatment system, with the twofold objective of improving the comfort and preservation of the building’s structures, furnishings and art objects and controlling humidity. During construction, this strategy of updating the systems was combined with the necessary replacement of all the piping for the water supply and sanitation, which had reached the end of their life cycle. This entailed the careful dismantling of whole portions of the toilets, faced with Lasa marble on the floors and partly on the walls. All the slabs made and laid to a special design, as well as the edge moldings towards the surfaces finished with marmorino, were surveyed and numbered to restore them to their original positions after the work was completed. Some that were beyond recovery were necessarily replaced to the original design, also thanks to a careful search conducted by the craftsmen who worked on the stone, to find a suitable block of marble and provide slabs with the right shade of color and veining. The non-original bathroom fixtures were replaced, except for the three large pentagonal ceramic bathtubs on the first floor, and the hexagonal one in cast iron in the service bathroom on the ground floor, which are no longer available on the market. In the bathroom of the master bedroom on the first floor, accessible both from the rear closet and the bedroom, a prefabricated fiberglass cell with an assisted shower was installed in the place of the original bathtub. In this case it was considered appropriate to remove an artifact that is no longer necessary and create a specially designed new full-height shower, equipping it with a linear service niche on the rear wall, with built-in lighting and metal containers. This restored the original contrast between the part of the room lined with pear wood, with wooden boards and grating panels incorporating the shielded light sources, and the part completely faced with Lasa marble in continuity with the floor. The most extensive part of the work in terms of surfaces and the most complex, given the variety of types, was the recovery of the wall finishes. In addition to the ivory white stucco lucido (smooth and shiny stucco) that characterizes most of the rooms in the house, a dark stucco lucido finish was used on the walls, ceilings and cabinets of the cloakroom, applied to wooden panels instead of masonry; calce rasata (smoothed lime-plaster) was used in the kitchen and laundry, while marmorino was used in the toilets. With the exception of the 30 x 30 mm ceramic tiles lining the walls of the kitchen, fittingly restored and integrated, unfortunately it was impossible to preserve the original finish in any of these cases. In the sitting rooms, bedrooms and the living areas on the first floor, the stucco lucido finish was irreparably compromised; in some parts it was damaged and the color was permanently lost, in others it had been damaged by the mold produced by surface condensation. However, the small surviving portions were useful to verify the original color of the surfaces, though all the attempts at cleaning were useless. Keeping the modest portions of the original finishes as isolated patches would have contradicted the character and continuity of the walls, conceived to make the interiors glimmer with an inexhaustible play of reflections. Even the marmorino finishes in the bathrooms re-sisted attempts to clean them and so they had to be completely relaid. Small additions were made to mend fragmented situations, or to restore the surfaces in Prun stone on the ground floor, worn by recurrent episodes of tidal flooding, now prevented by adopting discreet removable stainless steel barriers. The recovery of the stone slabs made it possible not to lose the irregular scored finish on the surfaces and the polished banded edges of the Prun stone which, together with the linear inserts in Lasa marble, are among the most distinctive features in the main rooms on the ground floor. It was necessary to listen carefully to the “voices” of the house itself to attain an adequate awareness of the appropriate design strategies. When was possible to dismantle the cladding, sketches made rapidly by Carlo Scarpa during his visits were found on the walls behind or on the backs of the panels, to suggest some constructional solutions or explain the sequence of the assembly to the craftworkers present on site. An architecture of exceptional quality like Casa Balboni, when it risks being permanently lost raises endless questions. This challenge is implicit in the profession of the architect, but it becomes even more evident and pressing when it involves working in a wonderful city like Venice, the setting of Casa Balboni, and what is more, guided by Carlo Scarpa, one of the most gifted contemporary interpreters of this city.</p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Martinis-Magnani_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. Casa Balboni, view of the facade towards the garden after restoration. (© Claudia Rossini)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Martinis-Magnani_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. Casa Balboni, view from the living room towards the entrance from the garden. (© Claudia Rossini)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Martinis-Magnani_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. Casa Balboni, the helical staircase after restoration. (© Claudia Rossini)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Martinis-Magnani_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. Casa Balboni, first floor. View of the passage to the sitting room after restoration. (© Claudia Rossini)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Martinis-Magnani_img_05.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 5. Casa Balboni, view from the living room towards the entrance from the garden. (© Claudia Rossini)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Martinis-Magnani_img_06.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 6. Casa Balboni, ground and first floor plans. (© MAP studio)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: For a more comprehensive version of this study refer to Martinis, Magnani, Pelzel, 2021. In this paper Roberta Martinis is the author of pages XX-YY and Francesco Magnani of pages ZZ-JJ.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: Scarpa (1984, p. 282).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Scarpa (2010, p. 65).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: Quaroni (1984, p. 254).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: Sottsass (2017, p. 158).</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Martinis, R., Magnani, F., &amp; Pelzel, T. (2021). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Carlo Scarpa. The House on the Grand Canal</em>. Electa</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Quaroni, L. (1984). Le &#34;lezioni&#34; di Scarpa. In F. Dal Co, &amp; G. Mazzariol (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Carlo Scarpa. Opera completa</em> (pp. 252–255). Electa</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Scarpa, C. (1984). Arredare. In F. Dal Co, &amp; G. Mazzariol (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Carlo Scarpa. Opera completa</em> (pp. 282). Electa</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Scarpa, C. (2010). Piccoli particolari, valori spaziali, riferimenti letterari. In F. Semi (Ed.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>A lezione con Carlo Scarpa</em> (pp. 65–74). Cicero</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Sottsass, E. (2017). Katsura, villa imperiale a sud-ovest di Kyoto. In  (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Per qualcuno può essere lo spazio</em> (pp. 153–159). Adelphi</voce>
</root>