<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">Part 1. Ahmedabad. Laboratory of Modern Architecture</h1>
<h1 aid:pstyle="H1">02 Architects and patrons: Gira and Gautam Sarabhai</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Elisa Alessandrini</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Architect</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">The subject of this paper is about the work of the Indian architects Gira and Gautam Sarabhai, a sister and a brother particularly noted as patrons of many architectures in the city of Ahmedabad, but still little known as architects.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">This is a short extract from my PhD thesis<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p> developed in 2009-12 based on archival documents traced in Ahmedabad, US. and European archives in a research that enlightens their pivotal role in the modernization of entire India. Along with the other members of their family, they were visionary actors in Ahmedabad, a city that became a laboratory of new architectural ideas.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Gira (1923-2021) and Gautam (1917-1995) Sarabhai, two of the eight siblings of a well known textile family of industrialists, belonged to the first Indian generation of architects of the postcolonial era. They were born in the years 1910-20, the same generation as Doshi and Correa. However, the Sarabhais distinguished themselves among the others to be extraordinary skillful in interweaving a wide net of national and international relations with the most famous architects and artists of the moment which led to fruitful cultural exchanges for all parties involved. The Indian young generation had the opportunity to work and relate to Western modern masters in a unique dialogue from which the evolution of postcolonial Indian architecture arose. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">I would like to emphasize the active role of the young Indian architects who invited their masters to India in order to establish deep connections that would have brought to representative buildings to their city.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The decades 1940-60 are the historical context, when the most important political figures were Prime Minister Nehru and Gandhi. We know that the Sarabhai family was particularly connected to both Nehru and also Gandhi who used to live in an <em aid:cstyle="italic">ashram</em> in this city just across the river, not far from the Sarabhai house. Especially the women of this family, such as Mridula, Gira’s older sister, and Anasuya, Gira’s aunt, were deeply involved in the struggle for Independence in close contact with Gandhi. On the other hand, Vikram Sarabhai, Gautam’s young brother, a scientist with a doctorate in Physics at the University of Cambridge, was in close contact with Nehru for the foundation of new Institutes of research in the city of Ahmedabad<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>, which was crucial for the country’s development pursued by both. All the Sarabhai members, extraordinarily brilliant and erudite entrepreneurs, invested in the field of scientific research and education to build and raise a new modern nation. In early 1947, Vikram patronized two institutes of scientific research, the Physical Research Laboratory (PRL) and an Institute related to the textile industries (ATIRA), both designed by the young Indian architect Kanvinde who had just returned from his studies with Gropius at MIT. Vikram was also decisive for the foundation of IIM in the city of Ahmedabad instead of Mumbay where it had initially been planned. This project was commissioned to Louis Kahn thanks to the newborn National Institute of Design (NID) by Gira and Gautam Sarabhai. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The Sarabhais founded and sponsored numerous other schools in their city, such as the montessorian Schreys School and the Darpana Academy of Performing Arts. Therefore, they played a key role in founding new buildings for education which became the testing ground of a new architectural language (fig. 1). </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Thus, in the years 1940-60, Ahmedabad became the beating heart of ideas, experiments and encounters that had no equal in India. For this reason, it can be considered the cradle of postcolonial Indian architecture. Among the most famous projects of these years, born of the cultural exchange between the masters and the young generation, there are the Gandhi Memorial Museum by Correa, the School of Architecture by Doshi, and the National Institute of Design (NID) by Gira and Gautam Sarabhai. These buildings can easily match the works realized in Ahmedabad by Le Corbusier and Kahn. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Let’s focus on the architects of the Sarabhai family, Gira and Gautam, and proceed in chronological order.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the first years of the 1940s, Gira and Gautam Sarabhai along with some other members of the family moved to New York to boost the Calico market, one of the most important textile industries of India. Once they arrived in the USA, Gira and Gautam planned to search for an American architect who had already been working for big industrialists. Hence, they met the Kaufmann family and connected with F. Ll. Wright in order to have both a working experience in his studio in Taliesin West and to design together a Calico shop for the city of Ahmedabad. Therefore, Gira Sarabhai moved to Scottsdale, Arizona, to work with the master. The intense exchange of letters between Gira and Gautam gives evidence that the Calico Mills Store was the result of their program and ideas together with Wright’s expertise and creativity. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Unfortunately, the multistory Calico store, which was supposed to be placed in the city center of Ahmedabad, was never realized. Designed on seven levels, the avant-garde shop would have included a catwalk for fashion shows, a large screen for projecting images, an art bookshop, a restaurant and an observation roof with garden, and even a system of loudspeakers to play music on all levels. As a result, it should not have been a simple store, but a sophisticated boutique where fashion, art and architecture should have blended in a unique space. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The drawings of the building show the cantilevered terraces with lots of nature, and the use of <em aid:cstyle="italic">textile blocks</em> in the facade probably to adapt to the hot climate but also to make the front appear embroidered like the Calico textiles. Unfortunately, the municipality never approved this project that required a great amount of iron which lacked in India. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Nevertheless, Wright’s lesson had been learned and translated into the subsequent projects the Sarabhais developed. For example, in the Calico Administrative Office<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p> nature played a very important architectural role as reflected in the use of the surrounding gardens outside as well as inside, with small water basins in multiple levels with slight differences in height on the ground floor which are treated with stones and pebbles, and even brick walls that seem to draw a texture similar to embroidered textiles. Also in the design of the Calico Mills, the influence of Wright is clear. In a picture of an interior published in a Calico pamphlet<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p> we can see “dendriform” pillars that recall those of Johnson Wax Building, which are the same columns admired by Le Corbusier who sketched them in his <em aid:cstyle="italic">Carnets</em> when he arrived in Ahmedabad in 1951<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">From a very early age, Gira and Gautam collaborated with a great number of western artists and architects and this attitude had been advantageous from several points of view: for the Calico industries, for the modernization of the city and even professionally for Gira and Gautam as architects. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">When they were in the USA, they most likely met also Le Corbusier for the first time, and with him they remained in touch. Then, some years later they invited him to Ahmedabad to design a Museum and a villa for Manorama Sarabhai. We can infer that from the exchange of letters kept at the Fondation Le Corbusier, since the summer 1950 Gira was thankful to Le Corbusier for the book he sent her<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">6</p>. Moreover, Le Corbusier’s high esteem and confidence towards Gira emerges from their long exchange of letters as well as his admiration for all the members of the Sarabhai family who were very passionate about art and architecture. Maybe this was the reason why Le Corbusier accepted all the works in this city. Gira and Gautam learned a lot from him, and his teaching is visible in their subsequent main project, the NID. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Gira and Gautam’s projects are the synthesis between their design ability and manufacturing capacity, and their understanding of modern architecture learned directly from the Masters. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Since the early ‘50s, Gautam, a mathematician and investigator of new forms and materials, became aware of the geodetic domes by Buckminster Fuller in the USA, and along with his sister Gira, decided to realize a small traveling and demountable Calico shop with the aim to display fabrics, do fashion shows, and promote the Calico items all over India. As early as 1956, Gautam started to experiment with the construction of small geodesic domes<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">7</p>. The encounter with Fuller allegedly took place in in Bombay in April 1958 when also the designers Charles and Ray Eames where in India to study the foundation of the first Institute of Design in the country<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">8</p>. On that occasion they developed together an itinerant Calico shop, called “Calicloth dome” with the shape of a geodesic dome, 100 feet in diameter, with a tubular structure and fabric that provided covering. This framework, then dismantled, had been captured in one of Charles Eames’ pictures stored at the Library of Congress<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">9</p>. In the same year, Gautam erected a second geodesic dome in Delhi without Fuller’s help. This dome too was 100 feet in diameter, and it was considered a better variant from a technical point of view. In a picture kept by Gautam and sent to Charles Eames, he wrote that he was proud to be able to use less pipe and fabric and to have managed a structure faster to assemble and disassemble<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">10</p>. Therefore, at the end of 1958, two traveling geodesic domes, “Cali-cloth Dome”, hit the road from Delhi and from Bombay to promote the Calico items with the slogan <em aid:cstyle="italic">fashion comes to town</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">11</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">At the end of this experience, Gautam and Gira decided to realize a permanent shop in the city center of Ahmedabad in the same plot where Wright’s store should have been built.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Therefore, the Sarabhais designed a two-story shop: a basement constituted by a big hall without pillars in the center, but using truss girders (the first space of this kind realized in India), and a first floor covered by a geodesic dome of 50 feet in diameter supported by 5 poles with a very thin wooden shell overlaid by copper<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">12</p>. Gautam succeeded in reducing the thickness of the wood components as well as the iron structure with the aim to use as little material as possible. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Therefore, they managed to adapt the form of the Fuller geodesic dome in a smart and elegant way with less expensive materials. Finally, the white deep lettering “Cali-Shop” fixed in vertical on a lateral wall, with a font designed by photographer and graphic designer Ernst Scheidegger at the invitation of Gira, represented a finishing modern touch. In the ‘90s, the shop was abandoned and in 1997 the dome collapsed after a storm. A legacy of their clever work has been lost (fig. 2).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">It is curious to notice that in the same year, when the Sarabhais encountered Fuller in India, he had just been hired by the Indian Government to realize a traveling geodesic dome that would have displayed all over India the exhibition <em aid:cstyle="italic">Design Today in America and Europe</em>, which had been organized by MoMA<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">13</p> in New York in order to show the best western home design in the main cities of India and stimulate an initiation of this kind of industry in the country. Was it a mere coincidence?</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Obviously not.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In fact, the capable entrepreneurs of the Sarabhai family, always ready to promote their Calico brand, were at the same time dedicated to study the evolution of Indian handcrafts into modern design, and also to preserve the traditional craft work especially in the textile field. At this point, we should move forward to another chapter of the Sarabhais history, the one that sees their commitment to study the local heritage and craft.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In 1948, as soon as Gira and Gautam came back from the States, they designed the first Museum dedicated to Indian textile arts, The Calico Museum of Textiles,  which was inaugurated by Nehru in February 1949<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">14</p>. Unfortunately, this architecture has been destroyed too, nevertheless, from the few images published in the magazines of those years, we can see that it was a cutting-edge Museum with a modern facade with well balanced vertical and horizontal lines, big luminous lettering, and a unique attention to the layout and display of the items. Not only the Museum exhibited the most precious fabrics but it also promoted the research and the protection of those Indian ancient traditions<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">15</p>. To this purpose, Gira got in touch with the main experts in the textile field and started a collaboration with the Victoria&amp;Albert Museum in London, as well as the Ulm and Basel Schools. The Calico Museum of Textiles (1948-49), one of the first building realized in Ahmedabad by Gira and Gautam, turned out to be the seminal project for the birth of industrial design, and a catalyst for new encounters. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In fact, thanks to this Museum, in 1955 the Sarabhais were employed by the MoMA (New York) to showcase their traditional cloths in the exhibition <em aid:cstyle="italic">Textile and Ornamental Art of India</em> in order to promote Indian arts and crafts in the States<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">16</p>. Therefore, thanks to the Calico Museum and the MoMA, the Sarabhais started a new incredible adventure aimed to study in depth and defend Indian traditional handcrafts. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In 1955, the Sarabhais for the first time got in touch with the designers Charles and Ray Eames, which marked the beginning of a deep and everlasting friendship that led to the foundation and construction of the first National Institute of Design (NID) in Ahmedabad including its cultural projects. The dialogue between the four actors was remarkable for all of them. The Eameses were interested in Indian spirituality, colors and tradition, and also in the impact of technology on them. The Sarabhais received support and good advice on the new Institute of Design, and in turn they offered great hospitality and their deep knowledge of Indian culture. All the letters I have found in the Library of Congress Archive demonstrate the intense exchange of ideas related to NID foundation as well as the important exchange of gifts such as film, chairs, toys, textile and also sincere mutual esteem. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Let’s summarize the long history that led to the design of NID. After their first encounter with the Sarabhais in 1955, only in 1958 the Eameses were appointed by the Indian Government to travel to India and study handicraft. The result was <em aid:cstyle="italic">The India Report</em>, a significant text in which the Eameses wrote the cultural project of the first Design School in India, its goals, the relationship between students and teachers, the <em aid:cstyle="italic">learning by doing</em> methodology and even the features of the building. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">It follows that NID was not a simple school but rather an institution for education, research and practice at the service of the Nation with production laboratories useful to society<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">17</p>. This cultural agenda made NID unique in the national and international panorama. Interestingly, the Eameses were not the only advisors of NID foundation. Other designers were also consulted such as Ernst Scheidegger, Vilhelm Wohlert, and  even Gio Ponti. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">After six years of gestation, in 1961 the Institute was finally founded in Ahmedabad, and in the absence of a proper building, it was based on the last floor of Le Corbusier’s Museum of Art, a landmark also commissioned by the Sarabhai family. In the following years, Gira and Gautam Sarabhai conceived one of their most significant projects: the NID headquarters. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The building was the result of a study that aimed to combine spatial flexibility to contemporary construction methods in consideration of local material, craftsman’s skills, and a desire for innovation. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">NID is a compact building, three stories high, in which modularity is clear due to its unit structure. 
Set opposite Le Corbusier’s Museum, just like this one, it is made of bricks and concrete <em aid:cstyle="italic">pilotis</em> that form a structural squared grid to guarantee security in case of river floods, which generates a free, multifunctional ground floor sheltered from the sun and the rain. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">As we can see from the coverage plan (fig. 3), only a portion of the project has been realized (the one in gray color). The Institute could have been enlarged by adding modules like in a <em aid:cstyle="italic">mat-building</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">18</p>. The ground floor is versatile and autonomous with few walls and slight difference in levels, areas with fountains, white pebbled gardens and filtered light that recall Wright’s design (figs. 4-5). The first floor is the main level with double height laboratories. The modular structural unit that is repeated in the complex is 12.3 x 12.3 m, with three pillars per side, three floors high, a slab on the first floor and a shell roof. Similar to Indian pavilions, this unit allowed for a quick construction and at the same time experimented with the use of different materials for the shells, from ferrocement to bricks and concrete, with only the last one completely made of bricks. Gautam’s aim was to reduce the use of iron and concrete and to realize at least one shell in bricks. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Ultimately, considering that Gira and Gautam Sarabhai invited the best professors as consultants, and the most talented International masters to teach young Indian students and professors, we can deduce that NID became a laboratory of Indian excellence in design, art and architecture in the city of Ahmedabad, which developed into the cradle of postcolonial architecture. Hence, NID was not a mere school of design, but also an Institute of research at the service of the Nation, and this is why the Government commissioned NID to perform many assignments to such as the exhibition <em aid:cstyle="italic">Nehru his life and his India</em> in 1965, which was realized by the Sarabhais, the Eameses and their students. In this cultural exchange between East and West at NID, we also find the renowned IIM project by Louis Kahn who was invited by the Department of Architecture to design IIM together with NID students and young architects of the city of Ahmedabad such as Doshi, Raje and Kapadia. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Another interesting building they designed in Ahmedabad is the B.M. Institute of Mental Health (1963-64), which in 1977 was enlarged with the help of the German engineer Frei Otto, who was also invited to teach at NID. Gautam and Otto tested a very thin ferrocement roof with an elegant fascinating curved shape. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In conclusion, in the quest for an international network of contacts, Gira and Gautam and the whole Sarabhai family were brilliant in securing the best figures in a miraculous network of relationships in the United States, Italy, France and Switzerland. They managed to coordinate different views of a new India that was simultaneously cutting-edge and rooted in ancient tradition. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Thanks to their different love for all the arts and to the new Institute of Design that needed partnership with open-minded masters, they called renowned artists such as Calder, Noguchi, Cage, Rauschenberg and Cartier-Bresson. There is a long list of guests who arrived to Ahmedabad invited by the Sarabhais, even scientists such as Homi Bhabha and C.V. Raman, and politicians like Maulana Azad and Sarojini Naidu, philosophers and educators such as Rabindranath Tagore, Maria Montessori and many other intellectuals. In their house, called the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Retreat</em>, surrounded by an idyllic nature on the outskirts of the chaotic city, peace and creativity must have been particularly inspiring since every guests was grateful for the hospitality, exchange of ideas and even presents. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">I would like to conclude by mentioning Alexander Calder’s art. He too was invited by Gira Sarabhai in 1955 to work at the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Retreat</em> in a creative advantageous exchange for both. Calder realized eleven <em aid:cstyle="italic">mobiles</em> and donated them to the Sarabhai family. Among these, one called <em aid:cstyle="italic">Happy Family</em> really impressed me. It is a <em aid:cstyle="italic">mobile</em> with eight white hanging circles that represent the eight children of Ambalal Sarabhai, the father, who is probably represented by the red figure, and Saraladevi, the mother, most likely the yellow star or the sun. It is a representation of the Sarabhai family, a group of unique incredibly charismatic visionaries enlightened like this star, united in the modernization of their Nation and leaning forward like this aerial sculpture, and also particularly bright and happy as in the title of Calder’s work.</p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Alessandrini_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. The Sarabhais, patrons and architects</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>    
    <Image href="File:///Alessandrini_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. *Cali-shop*. (© Elisa Alessandrini, 2009)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Alessandrini_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. National Institute of Design coverage plan drawn by the author. The portion realized is in grey</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Alessandrini_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. National Institute of Design ground floor. (© Elisa Alessandrini, 2011)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Alessandrini_img_05.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 5. National Institute of Design ground floor. (© Elisa Alessandrini, 2011)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: Alessandrini (2012).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: In 1954, they together inaugurated the new complex building of Physical Research Laboratory in Ahmedabad, founded in 1947 and operative in the historical premises of the Sarabhai House, called <em aid:cstyle="italic">Retreat</em>.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: <em aid:cstyle="italic">Calico pamphlet</em> (n.d., presumably 1961, p. 66-67), designed by Ernst Scheidegger, concept by Gira Sarabhai, spiral binding, picture of Administrative Office Building in Baroda or Mumbai. Ernst Scheidegger showed me this pamphlet when I met him in his home in Zurich, August 2011. There is another Calico pamphlet, comparable to this one, I found in Ahmedabad in 2010 with similar pictures: <em aid:cstyle="italic">Calico since 1880</em> (n.d., presumably 1980) designed by Shilpi Advertising Limited.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: <em aid:cstyle="italic">Calico pamphlet</em> (n.d., presumably 1961, p. 13 and p. 26), interior of a Calico Spinning Department.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: Le Corbusier. (1951), E23-678, Fondation Le Corbusier (from now on FLC), Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">6</p>: Sarabhai, G. (1950, July 13). [Letter to Le Corbusier]. Correspondance (R3-2-355), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">7</p>: Sarabhai (1968, p. 72-75).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">8</p>: Neuhart, J., Neuhart, M., Eames, R. (1989, p. 232-233).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">9</p>: Eames, C. (1980, June 15). [birthday card to Buckminster Fuller with pictures he took, including his geodesic dome in Bombay in 1958]. Work of Charles and Ray Eames, Library of Congress, Washington DC, US.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">10</p>: Sarabhai, G. (1958, November 15). [Letter to Charles Eames]. Work of Charles and Ray Eames, unprocessed files consulted by the author in October 2011, Library of Congress, Washington DC, US. In the letter Gautam wrote to Charles Eames: “Dome 2: Here is a photograph of the new dome we built – it has the same diameter at the base as the first one which you saw (100 feet), but uses an easier constructional technique, the total length of pipe used it half that of Dome 1 and the number of intersections a third. The area of the fabric is reduced by 30%. It takes only half as long to erect and dismantle as the first one”.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">11</p>: <em aid:cstyle="italic">Calico pamphlet</em> (n.d, 1961?, p. 49).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">12</p>: Cadot (2004, p. 131-139).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">13</p>: Drexler (1958).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">14</p>: Goetz (1949).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">15</p>: In doing so, the Sarabhai put also their Calico industry at the peak of a secular Indian tradition. See: Williamson (2016).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">16</p>: Wheeler (1956).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">17</p>: Sarabhai and Sarabhai (1969).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">18</p>: Alessandrini (2011, p. 799-807).</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Alessandrini, E. (2011). National Institute of Design: un’architettura moderna nell’India postcoloniale. In <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Proceedings 1st International Congress Architectural Design between Teaching and Research</em>. (799–807). PolibaPress.</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Alessandrini, E. (2012). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Ahmedabad. Laboratorio di architettura moderna. Il National Institute of Design (1961-68) fra contatti internazionali ed echi della tradizione</em> [phdthesis]. Alma Mater Studiorum - Università di Bologna. https://doi.org/10.6092/unibo/amsdottorato/4715</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Cadot, P. (2004). Calico Textile Shop, the Doomed Dome, India. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Docomomo Journal</em> (13), 131–139</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Drextler, A. (Ed.). (1958). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Design Today in America and Europe</em>. The Museum of Modern Art</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Goetz, H. (1949). Calico Museum of Textiles at Ahmedabad. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>MARG</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>, 3</em>(4), 57–61</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Neuhart, J., Neuhart, M., &amp; Eames, R. (1989). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Eames Design. The Work of the Office of Charles and Ray Eames. Harry N. Abrams</em>. Harry N. Abrams Inc. Publishers</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Sarabhai, G., &amp; Scheidegger, E. (1961). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Calico Pamphlet</em></voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Sarabhai, G. (1968). Calicloth Dome. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>L’Architecture d’Aujourd’hui</em> (141), 72–75</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Sarabhai, G., &amp; Sarabhai, G. (1969). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>National Institute of Design. Documentation 1964-69</em>. NID Publication</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Shilpi Advertising Limited. (1980). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Calico since 1880</em>. The Ahmedabad Manufacturing and Calico Printing Co</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Wheeler, M. (1956). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Textile and Ornaments of India</em>. The Museum of Modern Art</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Williamson, D. (2016). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Modern Architecture and Capitalist Patronage in Ahmedabad, India 1947-1969</em> [phdthesis]. New York University</voce>
</root>