<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">14 The restoration of Villa La Saracena</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Paolo Verdeschi</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Architect</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening"><em aid:cstyle="italic">“Since it will be necessary to discuss how to remedy the defects of the buildings, it is essential to clarify which and of what nature are the anomalies that the hands of men can correct; just as the efficacy of the remedies indicated by doctors mainly depends on their knowledge of the disease”</em>. (L. B. Alberti, <em aid:cstyle="italic">De Re Aedificatoria</em>, Book X - Restoration of the buildings)</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Between the 1930s and the late 1970s, in Italy the theme of housing played a leading role in architectural debate and produced diverse articulations and highly original characteristics with respect to Rationalism and other European movements. This is the milieu of villa La Saracena, considered one of the masterpieces by the architect Luigi Moretti (1906-1973). Built between 1955 and 1957, the villa is situated in Capo Linaro along the Tyrrhenian Coast, at the end of the town of Santa Marinella, a summer holiday destination for the Roman bourgeoisie during the 1950s thanks to its position only a few kilometers from the capital. In 1954, the journalist from the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Corriere della Sera</em> newspaper Francesco Malgieri asked Luigi Moretti to design and build a villa in Santa Marinella for his daughter, Luciana Pignatelli Cortes D’Aragona, “<em aid:cstyle="italic">as if it were his own home</em>”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>. The villa was intended to be a vacation home for the entire family, which moved there in 1958. That same year, the villa hosted the baptism of Diego Pignatelli Cortes D’Aragona who, as we will see later, together with his sister Fabrizia, would provide very important information during the restoration of the villa. Moretti imagined the Saracena as a building fully immersed in its surroundings, closed toward the street and open toward the sea. The house is “soft, at times bare, dry, with cuts and fractures instead of openings”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>. The design of the villa marked the beginnings of the final, <em aid:cstyle="italic">expressionist</em> phase of Moretti’s work. Leaving Rationalism behind, his studies of the Baroque took shape; geometric regularity gave way to open forms as the modulation of curvilinear surfaces announced new spatialities. The Saracena, a “jealous house”, “a house that speaks of a desire for a different life”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>, was among the projects dearest to Moretti but, as he himself lamented, it failed to be understood once complete. Letters from this period demonstrate how it was certainly the project he sponsored over all others in architectural publications and reviews. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Throughout the 1970s, the villa was owned by only two other families, aside from Francesco Malgieri who, in the meantime, also commissioned Moretti to design villa La Califfa. While the owners maintained the original conditions of the house and its furnishings, the few interventions they carried out were poorly executed, including the demolition of deteriorated elements, such as the final part of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">veletta</em> (a solid horizontal band above the strip windows) and the canopy on the seaside elevation, reintegrated with damaging negligence. Fortunately, all were easily reversible.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The study of a building and its author are propaedeutic to the restoration of Modern architecture. During this process, the architect-restorer becomes a historian, intent on tracking down all technical and formal information in order to develop a project and begin restoration works, returning to the role of a design architect and supervisor of works. At the Saracena, the architect was also a <em aid:cstyle="italic">detective</em> and, at the end of the restoration, as I will explain later, the study was returned to a historian, in this specific case Professor Annalisa Viati Navone, author of the volume <em aid:cstyle="italic">La Saracena di Luigi Moretti fra suggestioni mediterranee, barocche e informali</em> (2012) one of the most important texts for this restoration.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The year was 1979, and I was a recent graduate working with Alessandro Anselmi on the publication of a selection of his projects. At this time, we drafted with <em aid:cstyle="italic">Rapidograph</em> technical pens, with which I maintained a conflictual relationship, when CAD still belonged to the future. Alessandro was working on the international competition for <em aid:cstyle="italic">Les Halles</em> and, as I watched him tracing his first sketches of the spiral of this project inspired by the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Encyclopedie</em>, I asked him about his method. He hastily answered: “You <em aid:cstyle="italic">gotta</em> think in architecture, it’s like translating into English, those who speak English well already think in English, they don’t translate”.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In reality, to design an architect requires an initial stimulus, a theme born from a set of information, from the memory of other projects and from automatisms of the mind. While they may even be illogical but creative and, when elaborated, synthesized and considered globally and without a hierarchy, they allow for everything to be translated into architecture. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">I believe this process can be compared to what Rilke writes about the birth of a verse. All of this, together with the identification of an idea that generates multiple compositions, materializes in drawing. Almost forty years later, while confronting the restoration of the Villa La Saracena designed by Luigi Moretti, these words came back to me. As it has evolved culturally over the course of time, the concept of restoration has developed and varied in its theories, techniques and legislative references. However, one thing has remained fixed in this complex system of interactions: the architect continues to represent the synthesis between culture and technique required by a restoration work. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The restoration of Modern architecture means thinking architecturally – in its broadest meaning – about the work of architecture we are about to care for. Restoring to maintain its efficiency, to make it once again legible and usable as intended by its designer, to rediscover the language expressed in its forms of spaces – be they interior or exterior – its materials, its colors, its furnishings. The awareness and interest of the State and Associations (for example, Docomomo) in our recent architectural heritage grows day by day, and there is a consequent increase in the need for architects who are prepared for this work, together with more streamlined procedures and financing. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The method for approaching the restoration of modern architecture lies in the direct wake of conservative restoration. Thus, there is a fundamental relationship among the archive, the building and the process of restoration that unfolds through the examination of original drawings and technical-building solutions retraced among these documents. The study of drawings is the first tool of reasoning in an investigation of composition and technique on multiple levels. I think of Mario Ridolfi, of Carlo Scarpa, and obviously of Luigi Moretti, who lived at the same time. The latter, in an interview in <em aid:cstyle="italic">Didattica del disegno</em>, in 1970, stated: “To the young architect we must teach drawing as the faculty of representing something real, imagining the world of transformation of computers, opening up new windows”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p>. By reading graphic texts we can comprehend the development of the hypotheses and paths of design, and manage to visualize – today we would refer to <em aid:cstyle="italic">work in progress</em> – the choices leading up to the final one. Notes on materials and indications about building were often added to drawings confirming a solution or explaining the need for a variation. Original project drawings can now often be found in archival funds, some consultable online. Writings, technical reports, correspondence to the trade to comprehend in detail the drawing of a project at various scales, are a precious support when <em aid:cstyle="italic">reasoning</em> about the final form of a project. There are many other tools of investigation, technologically trustworthy, such as chemical analyses, stratigraphic studies of materials and systems of structural investigation. However, the greatest assistance in understanding a project is offered by photography. Fundamental contributions include those of Cartoni, Casali, Galliano, Valabrega and others. As a drawing is complete when it cancels the idea, photography cancels the drawing but returns to the initial idea (fig.1). Photographs of architecture, captured during and at the end of construction, freeze it in its original time and transmit it as a real and indelible image to collective memory, pulling it out of the dimension of drawing that still remains a precious operating manual for the finished work. This image, transmitted by publications, by archival research or even some chance photographs in a family album, is perhaps the most important aspect to be recovered in a restoration work. The architect Arrigo Rudi claimed that the photographer needed to capture the mental image he had, as well as his own way of observing. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the field of restoration of modern architecture – in the acquisition of data – it is also very important to interview people who may have been involved in a specific project. Comparing what they have to say can often reveal certainties about decisions taken. The restoration of villa La Saracena began in 2016. The perception I had was that of standing before a beautiful vintage sailboat, fixed in the history of hundreds of regattas, though missing a few pieces, from the masts to the shell plating of the parts above water, to details such as the rubbing strakes or the bollards (fig. 2). To get her seaworthy again, they needed to be substituted. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Works began with corrections to the waterproofing layer on all of the roofs, at the time near collapse. After the survey of the decay phenomena, works progressed according to a program of intervention: distinguishability, minimum intervention, potential reversibility, respect for authenticity and original materials, physical-chemical compatibility of added elements and the aesthetic and historical recognition of the work. In the case of villa La Saracena these principles were adopted by associating the type of intervention with the various parts of the building to be restored. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">Conservation works</strong></p>
<ul aid:pstyle="ul">  Detached external plaster;
external windows and shutters;
consolidation of the internal paving;
restoration of the kitchen furnishings. 
</ul>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><strong aid:cstyle="bold">Restoration of destroyed elements in accordance with the original project</strong></p>
<ul aid:pstyle="ul">Substitution of the bearing structure of the windows and the valance boxes of the living room-promenade;
reconstruction of the valance boxes (cfr. original project and historical photographs by A. Cartoni, ACS);
replacement of all living room windows (cfr. original project and historical photographs by A. Cartoni, ACS);
reconstruction of the pergola on the seaside (cfr. original project and historical photographs by A. Cartoni, ACS);
reintegration of the original colors (source: former owners and historical photographs by G. Canali, AP).
restoration of lost elements in accordance with the principle of <em aid:cstyle="italic">verisimilitude</em>.
</ul>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">I would like to speak briefly about the reconstruction of the canopy positioned at the end of the living room. This very important architectural element, perhaps a reference to the rigging of a ship, poetically terminated and completed the villa by projecting it toward the sea. This construction collapsed after only a few years as it had not been built to withstand the aggressiveness of the elements and, more significantly, the wind that blows across Capo Linaro. The in-depth researches did not find out any construction drawings or photographs that could offer information about the connection of the beams to the structure, nor the detail of the cables used to suspend them.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In original drawings, this canopy-pergola appears in the fourth version on the ground floor. In section it is present in three sketches lacking any dimensions or indications about materials. Furthermore, what remained of the fixing points offered no reliable indications of the original anchoring detail. In this case, restoration was based on the criteria of <em aid:cstyle="italic">verisimilitude</em> gleaned from existing photographs. The beams were dimensioned after a series of comparisons and overlaps of scaled historical photographs. The connection to the structure and the cables were redesigned, once again based on verisimilitude, supported by historical photographs and by structural requirements. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">One interesting aspect of the restoration works was the discovery of the total lack of any building permit for the final project – the fifth designed by Luigi Moretti – which led to a complicated bureaucratic process to regularize the building and obtain various authorizations and a proper permit. However, the most important surprise sparked by this restoration, given the existence of only black and white photographs by Vasari and Cartoni, was the discovery of the original colors beneath the layers of paint applied over the years. In the half basement we discovered that walls, ceilings and even the exterior wall containing the entry door had been painted pink, a color found in minimum traces also on the column at the start of the ramp to the garage. On the ground floor we identified two other hues of pink. The first, more tenuous, covered the entire inner wall below the windows, while the exterior part was painted a more intense pink; the same color was also found on the wall at the entrance, which I would define a hinge with the promenade. The handrail of the stair revealed a coral color. The last color discovered was a light green, on the supports of the hinges of the gate-sculpture designed by Claire Falkenstein at the entrance to the large seaside cave. The <em aid:cstyle="italic">desire</em> for color present in the villa is evident, and the perception that the use of white was not the result of a reconsideration was strong, given the colors designed and found in the villa. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The furnishings were designed by Moretti specifically for La Saracena: the blue kitchen cabinets made by <em aid:cstyle="italic">formica</em>, the pink, sage green, orange and mustard yellow sofas, the red velvet decorations around the doors, the clothes hangers and the round windows in colored glass, the light yellow paving in various hues in the living room with floral decorations by Grisotti and intensely colored ceramic tiles. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Moreover, in 1950 Moretti wrote an essay in the review <em aid:cstyle="italic">Spazio</em> on colors in Venice<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>, and many of his previous and later works use strong colors. Red is a recurring color: the <em aid:cstyle="italic">highlights</em> on the mixed-use building in Corso Italia 13 in Milan and on the two BNL (Banca Nazionale del Lavoro) buildings in Piazzale Flaminio in Rome. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">During the renovation works carried out in an apartment in Casa del Girasole, I noted an orange color on a column, below the paint layer, while the marble paving and some of the bathroom tiles tended to be pink. The handrail of the stairs at the former GIL in Piacenza was red, while the handrail of the stairs and the doors at villa La Califfa were orange. Despite having no certain proof, and with a certain reluctance, I was forced to cover these colors with a new white layer. Then, after almost four years of work, I received the first confirmation of my beliefs. Prince Diego Pignatelli Cortes D’Aragona, the son of the first owners I had unsuccessfully searched for, while he was passing through Rome and stimulated by publications on the restoration of the villa La Saracena, came to visit me. He confirmed all of the colors that had been discovered. His sister, Fabrizia Pignatelli, later confirmed the <em aid:cstyle="italic">aqua</em> green of Falkenstein’s gate and the coral red of the handrail. The study of the colors was complicated by the second owner of the villa, who, tracked down after the visit by Diego Pignatelli, confirmed everything except the pink color on the external wall. I remembered a black and white photograph, the outcome of an online research by my colleague and collaborator, the architect Valerio Mancini, in the Iuav Archivio Progetti - Fund Giorgio Casali, in which he noted a small difference in the coloring between the valance boxes and the wall below. This was followed by a patient research that found four-color photographs taken by Giorgio Canali in 1964 at villa La Saracena for <em aid:cstyle="italic">Domus</em> n. 419<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">6</p>, never published and forgotten by all. The result was that the external walls under the valance boxes were pink. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Following these discoveries, Annalisa Viati Navone wrote a very interesting essay, almost a continuation of the aforementioned volume, titled <em aid:cstyle="italic">Qualche riflessione sul rapporto fra Storia e Restauro Architettura a rischio in Italia e in Francia</em> (being printed, 2022), from which I quote: </p>
<blockquote><p aid:pstyle="Blockquote">“A restoration work is thus a master class in the history of the construction, as well as the design, of a building, and often a starting point for a historical-critical reading and interpretation, and reconsiderations of the original restoration project […] as we question whether Moretti imagined a polychrome color scheme for the internal and external elevations of the gallery? What spatial and visual effects did he wish to provoke? And whether he adopted this color scheme in dialogue (or perhaps in opposition?) to the use of white? […] Most importantly: what was Moretti’s position on the use of color in architecture?”.</p></blockquote>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">At this point I could claim that the architect-restorer is not responsible for studying the reasons for the use of color, but simply to restore them, when their presence is certain. However, here the osmosis between the historian and the architect-restorer continues. The owner of the villa La Saracena, convinced of the necessity to restore the original colors, authorized a series of stratigraphic tests (fig. 3) to better understand the succession of colors over time. The results of these studies arrived after the essay by Annalisa Viati Navone had been written. The most plausible hypothesis, in my opinion, is that the original color was perhaps a pale pink, and that the two successive layers are a result of maintenance work by later owners, who failed to replicate the original color. Nevertheless, the hypothesis by Viati Navone according to witch different colors were utilized inside and outside the villa, due to the refraction of the bright sun, remains valid. Further stratigraphic samples and archival studies are required to answer this question. It is now ascertained that villa La Saracena, always imagined completely white, it had actually colored surfaces in different shades of pink, both in the internal and the external facades of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">promenade</em>.
<em aid:cstyle="italic">Living</em> the architectural restoration means carrying out the restoration work according the original use of the building: it is the best way to preserve a private home. It also means the daily monitoring of the state of the building, its regular maintenance and the avoidance of expensive interventions. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Today villa La Saracena, as well as being the summer residence of the owner’s large family, is open to the public with organized visits and often used for events (fig. 4). </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following"><strong aid:cstyle="bold"><em aid:cstyle="italic">Post Scriptum</em></strong>: An unexpected photo of yesterday, at sunset, where a soft pink penetrates through the windows in the villa La Saracena, is my irrational and emotional explanation of that unusual color (fig. 5). Architecture is also made up of poetic elements that are transformed into matter. Few people have this gift and I would like to imagine that I do.</p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Verdeschi_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. Villa La Saracena, picture by A. Cartoni, 1962-63. (© Moretti-Magnifico Archive)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Verdeschi_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. Fig. 2 Villa La Saracena before the restoration works, 2016. (© Paolo Verdeschi)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Verdeschi_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. Stratigraphic analysis of external coatings. (© Paolo Verdeschi)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Verdeschi_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. Villa La Saracena after the restoration works, 2020. (© Paolo Verdeschi)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Verdeschi_img_05.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 5. Sunset from the villa, 2022. (© Paolo Verdeschi)</figcaption>
</figure>
    
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: Ponti (1964, p. 14). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: Moretti, L. [Presentation text of the project, unpublished typescript]. Archivio Moretti-Magnifico (from now on AMM), Rome, Italy.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Moretti, L. [Presentation text of the project, unpublished typescript]. AMM, Rome, Italy.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: De Fiore (1970, p. 60).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: Moretti (1950, p. 33).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">6</p>: Ponti (1964, pp. 14-19). See also: Fund G. Casali, Iuav Archivio Progetti, Venice, Italy.</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>De Fiore, G. (1970). Conoscenza uguale disegno, interview with Luigi Moretti by Gaspare De Fiore. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Didattica del disegno</em> (2), 52– 63</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Moretti, L. (1950). Colore di Venezia. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Spazio</em>, 33–39</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Ponti, G. (1964). Tre architetture di Luigi Moretti. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Domus</em> (419), 14–19</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Viati Navone, A. (2012). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>La Saracena di Luigi Moretti fra suggestioni mediterranee, barocche e informali</em>. Mendrisio Academy Press; Silvana Editoriale</voce>
</root>