<root xmlns:aid="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/4.0/" xmlns:aid5="http://ns.adobe.com/AdobeInDesign/5.0/"><h1 aid:pstyle="H1">03 Between Modernity and Tradition. Le Corbusier’s Villa Sarabhai</h1>
<h4 aid:pstyle="autore-capitolo">Maria Bonaiti</h4>
<h5 aid:pstyle="autore-affiliazione">Università Iuav di Venezia</h5>
<p aid:pstyle="p-opening">When Le Corbusier arrived in Ahmedabad in March 1951, he was far from imagining that in this city, just north of Mumbai, he would give form to his most enigmatic masterpieces: a museum (Sanskar Kendra, 1951-57), the Millowners’ Association Building (1951-57) and two villas (Villa Shodhan, 1951-57 and Villa Sarabhai, 1951-56).</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first">These buildings have seldom been investigated in a historiographical perspective and have remained on the margins of the main events of contemporary architecture. Probably this is because they remain in the shadow of the more publicized and outstanding venture that engaged Le Corbusier starting from 1951 in the construction of Chandigarh, the newly founded capital of the State of Punjab<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">1</p>. Villa Sarabhai, the subject of this discussion, is particularly difficult to access since it is located inside the large property of the Sarabhai family in the exclusive residential area of Shahibag, a few kilometers north of the old town. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Manorama Sarabhai, the client, who had a strong personality and was a member of one of the most powerful families in Ahmedabad, played a leading role in the narrative of the design and construction of the villa. The Sarabhais belonged to the entrepreneurial elite of the city, whose fortune was linked to the cotton textile industry. They were part of an enlightened, cultured bourgeoisie committed to promoting and supporting industrial activity without forgetting the cultural specificity of their country. The awareness of the potential of an economic growth aimed at taking India towards modernity, without sacrificing the value of tradition, was typical and at the same time the most controversial aspect that characterized the entrepreneurial class of Ahmedabad to which Manorama belonged<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">2</p>. Widow of Suhrid Sarabhai, mother of two children, and curious about contemporary Western art, Manorama commissioned her house from Le Corbusier in November 1951 on the occasion of his second visit to Ahmedabad<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">3</p>. From the very first meetings with the architect, Manorama emerged as a demanding client committed to designing a home that would accommodate the rhythms of life and deep-rooted customs while imposing herself as a vigilant guardian of tradition. Le Corbusier returned to Ahmedabad the following March bringing with him the first design proposals. At the Fondation Le Corbusier two drawings with annotated corrections that were made just after that crucial meeting with the client are preserved<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">4</p>. This documentation is useful for understanding the particular nature of the relationship that tied Le Corbusier to Manorama, who guided with a firm hand the various phases of the design of the villa whose solutions were the result of a close, and at times exhausting, debate between architect and client<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">5</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Nearly hidden in the lush tropical vegetation, the house presents forms that are assimilated to the local cultural context. Still it distinguishes itself from the type of Shodhan house – “the reincarnation of Villa Savoye turned upside down”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">6</p>– and its sculptural monumentality. Crossing the park of the estate, a service block consisting of a garage, servants’ quarters and kitchen, delimits the access area to the house. The main body of the villa is marked by a sequence of brick vaults set on oversized reinforced concrete beams and brick walls. Load bearing parallel walls are interrupted by various sized openings which allow the creation of a continuous spatial system. A two bay space separates the two units that make up villa Sarabhai and connects the front of the house to the internal garden where a refreshing small swimming pool is located and the villa opens with ample verandas. While the sequence of the vaults is concealed in the solution of the elevations, the interiors display a series of rooms permeable to air and light where space is the real protagonist of the composition (fig. 1). Heavy wooden doors, perforated by regular geometric openings, close the rooms towards the garden in the hottest hours, but when the evening approaches, the doors open again to let in the air and the view. Therefore, the verandas become suggestive thresholds of shade. By alternating simple brickwork solutions and white or brightly colored plastered partitions – in blue, green, red and yellow – the internal walls of the villa resonate with the texture of the surfaces of the vaults in exposed bricks, and with the black stone slabs of the flooring. The polychromy of the domestic spaces is balanced by the austerity of the external walls whose construction stands out for the primitive brutalism of the workmanship of materials such as brick and exposed reinforced concrete. This is a recurring characteristic of Le Corbusier’s latest works, but it achieves a particular strength in what was built in Ahmedabad. The elevations of Villa Sarabhai appear measured by the modules of metal formwork – which use was widespread in Ahmedabad – that generate rough surfaces which reverberate with the exposed bricks (fig. 2). These are used almost with tactile pleasure in the partitions that separate verandas, loggias and internal rooms. A similar materiality matches the expressive force of plastic inserts with an unprecedented primitivism – real <em aid:cstyle="italic">objects trouvés</em> – such as the oversized gutter that marks the entrance to the villa, the gutter spouts that give rhythm to the elevations and the steep staircase leading to the swimming pool slide. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Completed in 1956 and recognized as the most <em aid:cstyle="italic">Indian</em> of the architectures realized by Le Corbusier in Ahmedabad, Villa Sarabhai poses significant interpretative questions, the answers to which are probably to be sought in the set of circumstances intrinsic to the design and construction of the villa. In fact, the house designed by Le Corbusier for Manorama is problematically located within the architect’s production, and even though it echoes contemporary works, it reveals significant deviations. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">When considering the model proposed for Villa Sarabhai, it is possible to trace clear lines of continuity with what Le Corbusier designed up to that moment. Vaulted roofings are in fact found, between the thirties and forties, in a succession of solutions for Mediterranean dwellings, from the agricultural estate Peyrissac at Cherchell in Algeria to the complex Roq et Rob at Roquebrune-Cap Martin. Moreover, particular affinities are found in the Maisons Jaoul, whose construction preceded by only a few months what was then developed in India, and anticipated the solution of the Catalan vault<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">7</p>. If the overall structure of Villa Sarabhai appears consistent with the contemporary work of Le Corbusier, at the same time we can observe a significant <em aid:cstyle="italic">cross-fertilization</em> with specifically local solutions. As documented in the correspondence, it was Manorama who suggested continuous modifications and adjustments, and directed the architect in defining the details of spaces adjusted to accommodate a fashion suitable to the Indian lifestyle. And this is an aspect that returns to characterize different scales of the project. For example, the presence of connecting bays evokes the function performed in traditional architecture by the so-called <em aid:cstyle="italic">chowk</em>, which also distinguish the urban palace of Sarabhai. These are internal courtyards designed to ensure adequate ventilation to the rooms and at the same time they connect service and representative areas in common to the different units that comprise the private part of the house. In a similar way, the connecting rooms that separate the two units that make up Villa Sarabhai act as a hinge between the quarters of Manorama’s son and the living area in common with the quarters of the mother which develop on the upper floor<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">8</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The impression is that from the first drawings the plan of the villa takes shape sourcing different architectural references which see typical spaces of traditional architecture translated into recognizable figures of the language of Le Corbusier. The result is a real <em aid:cstyle="italic">creation of a tension</em> between different cultural models. For example, while echoing the models of the Unité d’habitation of Marseilles and of the La Tourette convent the verandas that open their front towards the garden appear completely transfigured in Manorama’s house. In fact, the loggias stand out as real threshold spaces – places of transition between inside and outside conceived to protect from the extremes of the weather and allow, at the same time, the circulation of air and light. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Space and its free flow between the rooms of the house is actually the protagonist of Villa Sarabhai, which is described as a “meandering house”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">9</p> by Balkrishna Doshi, one of the most attentive witnesses of Le Corbusier’s encounter with India. The space, he recalled, “flows simultaneously in different directions”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">10</p> and reveals an unprecedented relationship between inside and outside. Le Corbusier’s ability to modulate the spaces of Villa Sarabhai may be considered an original reinterpretation of traditional Indian architecture, which he observed with curiosity during his many stays in India as documented in the pages of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Carnets</em><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">11</p>. In fact, since his first Indian passages he scrupulously took note of the impressions he acquired by the architectural landscape that was revealed by what he saw. What impressed him was precisely the lack of solid walls to define the facades of the houses which were marked rather by a sequence of deep verandas and porches. The succession of loggias, which gives rhythm to the elevations of Villa Sarabhai, betrays the tension with which Le Corbusier redesigned known elements of his vocabulary adapting them to the site. A close observation of the villa at different scales, from the plan to the architectural details, allows us to recognize in the <em aid:cstyle="italic">cross-fertilazation</em> the principle that distinguishes the design. Even the solution of the garden roof, conceived to offer shelter from the summer heat in the hot monsoon nights, reflects modes typical of traditional architecture to conform to the customs of life of which Manorama was the vigilant guardian. And so it is the roof-terrace, a true manifesto of Le Corbusier’s architecture, which in Ahmedabad is transformed into a new space as the result of a process of adaptation of forms typical of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">civilisation machiniste</em> to ways of life assimilated from the local culture. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the attempt to understand the actual role played by Le Corbusier during the construction works and the intentions placed into the <em aid:cstyle="italic">cross-fertlized</em> solutions of which the architecture is a document, an essential source is constituted by the correspondence from the worksite between Ahmedabad and the Parisian studio, that was exchanged almost weekly. This was made possible by the presence in Ahmedabad of Jean-Louis Véret, a young French architect selected by Le Corbusier to follow the Indian worksites<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">12</p>. Véret arrived in Ahmedabad on June 7, 1953, and remained there until January 1955 when he was replaced by a then very young Doshi. In his first assignment as director of works, Véret sought a ceaseless recounting with Paris and the correspondence became an irreplaceable tool in directing the various phases of construction. Véret’s main interlocutors were Le Corbusier and two of the firm’s collaborators, Jacques Michel and Balkrishna Doshi<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">13</p>. In most cases the letters were accompanied by explanatory notes and quick sketches that literally guided Véret through the realization of the building, such as the composition of the formwork of the beams, the details for their correct construction, and the description of the executive techniques suitable for the installation of the brick walls. However, the inevitable time lag between sending the requests to Paris and the arrival of the answers was in some cases the cause of misunderstandings causing Véret’s great frustration. One example is the design of the formwork of the beams that was not approved by Le Corbusier but already in place when the information from the studio in rue de Sèvres arrived in Ahmedabad, which led to the extreme decision to demolish “three beams and the corresponding exterior wall”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">14</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">The detailed analysis of the correspondence has provided the understanding of the crucial role played by the worksite of the Maisons Jaoul which was started in Paris some months before the one in Ahmedabad<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">15</p>. In particular, it is the Catalan vaulted solution of Villa Sarabhai that recognizes in the Maisons Jaoul its own specific model as once again documented by the correspondence which was particularly frequent during the construction of the roof<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">16</p>. The Parisian worksite, followed among others by Michel and Doshi, was mentioned several times as an example. For instance, the arrangement of the electrical system and ventilation as well as the arrangement of the internal beams and the solution of the laying of the bricks. In this regard, the correspondence reveals how the irregular and imperfect masonry that distinguishes Villa Sarabhai was not at all the spontaneous outcome of the construction practices of local craftsmen, but rather the result of precise instructions carefully issued by the studio<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">17</p>.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">All things considered, the impression is that the Maisons Jaoul was deemed as a sort of real laboratory where Le Corbusier and his collaborators experimented with single design solutions which were then recommended to the more difficult to access Indian site. As mentioned, this happened at different scales of the project, from the vaults to the ceramic coverings, leaving very little spontaneity or accidentality in the Manorama house, which on the contrary took shape with the same care and artifices found in the most famous Parisian houses.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the light of what has been reconstructed so far, how should we look at Villa Sarabhai? How can we interpret that clear expression for the “taste for the rustic”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">18</p> as in the Maisons Jaoul, and which appears to take shape independently of geography and building inclinations?<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">19</p></p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Like the Maisons Jaoul, Villa Sarabhai can be interpreted as a manifestation of the new brutalist aesthetics that ran through Le Corbusier’s work from the forties onward taking over from the “polished and cellophanized”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">20</p> forms of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">civilisation machiniste</em>. This explains the care given to the detailed plastic solutions as well as the poetics of materials that characterize the spaces of the Indian “small house”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">21</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">However, the real narrative of the building process shows how the house of Manorama cannot be interpreted in the same way as one of the many Mediterranean villas of Le Corbusier. It is not to be considered a copy of what was more comfortably built in Paris. On the contrary, in spite of the affinities and even the repetitions of motifs and solutions which can be considered at the origin of the supervision of the building site, Villa Sarabhai is the expression of a slow process of traditional assimilation which forces the formal experimentation started in Paris.</p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In this regard, another valuable source for delineating the events of the villa are the photographs of the worksite taken by Véret between 1954 and the end of 1955<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">22</p>. There are more than 200 photographs today kept in the Véret archives that document on a monthly basis the progress of work in the various worksites of the buildings designed by Le Corbusier in Ahmedabad. This material, mostly unpublished, allows a close observation of the buildings during their making. Some photos of Villa Sarabhai caught significant dissimilarities between what had been built and what was indicated in the plans. The main differences concern the service nucleus of the villa consisting of the kitchen block and the garage. The rooms of the latter, for example, appear rotated by 90° with respect to what was indicated in the plans published in the pages of the <em aid:cstyle="italic">Œuvre Complète</em>, where the solution presents a succession of bays parallel to those of the main house. This was a modification already traced by Véret in a sketch dated July 7, 1953 and later confirmed by a drawing dated December 26, 1953<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">23</p>. This discordance can be interpreted as the extreme manifestation of a principle of variation which pervades the narrative of the villa both in its design phases and in its construction as a result of exhausting negotiations between architect and client. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">That process did not cease with the end of the works when Le Corbusier had no longer any control. Indeed, the villa experienced continuous and progressive adaptations to life starting from the fans placed under the vaults at the end of the construction works – to the architect’s total disappointment – to the addition of copper overhangs to the gutter spouts, whose brutal plasticity characterizes today the elevations of the house. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Regardless of the metamorphoses that the work underwent once it was immersed in the passage of time, from the earliest stages of design Villa Sarabhai became a document of the openness of Le Corbusier’s work to a multiplicity of cultural influences, so far neglected in the name of laws whose universal value came into sharp crisis in particular in his Indian work. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">Signs of unprecedented openness are the friendships developed by Le Corbusier during the months when he was engaged in the construction of Villa Sarabhai. Just to list a few, some examples are the bond established with the Sardinian sculptor Costantino Nivola – thanks to whom he came close to the work of Bernard Rudofsky – and the deep understanding that connected him with Minnette de Silva<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">24</p>. The first woman to establish herself as an architect in Sri Lanka in the aftermath of its independence, Minnette de Silva met Le Corbusier on the occasion of the Ciam conference in Bridgewater in 1947, where the young Sri Lankan participated as a representative of the Indian group MARG<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">25</p>. The friendship with de Silva, documented by a dense correspondence, part of which is now preserved at the Fondation Le Corbusier in Paris, developed in the years when Le Corbusier was working in India, between Chandigarh and Ahmedabad<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">26</p>. In these years, thanks to Minnette de Silva, Le Corbusier experienced a further and surprising encounter with the Asian country. The relationship that connected the two architects raises the question of the complexity of being together of distant languages and worlds. On the one hand, de Silva hoped to be able to open up the contemporary debate to a cultural complexity that had been ignored until then. On the other hand, the Indian continent appeared to Le Corbusier as an opportunity to stage the crisis of an entire season of architecture, then powerless in the face of the complexity of the historical passage it was called upon to interpret. The <em aid:cstyle="italic">cross-fertilized</em> forms of Villa Sarabhai tell the story of the effort made to keep in relation what one would like to separate ensuring, as witnessed in the project documents, the resistance of a comparison that is created through differences and continuous “divides”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">27</p>. </p>
<p aid:pstyle="p-following">In the light of the above, the impression is that Villa Sarabhai is not at all like a “small house”<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber">28</p> aimed at satisfying a luxurious and geographically isolated client. Interpretable as a masterly example of Le Corbusier’s mature work, the villa represents rather a document of a crucial historical passage that took shape in Ahmedabad to narrate, together with the cultural specificity, the second half of the twentieth century and its crises.</p>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Bonaiti_img_01.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 1. Le Corbusier, villa Sarabhai, Ahmedabad, Inde, 1951-1956, interior view. (© Manuel Bougot)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Bonaiti_img_02.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 2. Le Corbusier, villa Sarabhai, Ahmedabad, Inde, 1951-1956, partial view of the front towards the inner garden. (© Carlo Fumarola)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Bonaiti_img_03.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 3. Letter from J. Michel to J. L. Véret, November 18, 1953 (P3-7-69). (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Bonaiti_img_04.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 4. Floor plan sketch of the garage and gallery (FLC 31908). (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure>
    <Image href="File:///Bonaiti_img_05.jpg"></Image><p aid:pstyle="figcaption"></p>
    <figcaption>fig. 5. Floor plan with indication for interior furniture, 1952, November 10 (FLC 6683). (© Fondation Le Corbusier / SIAE)</figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Endnotes</h2>
<p aid:pstyle="p-first"><p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">1</p>: This paper summarizes issues and topics more broadly discussed by Bonaiti (2021a). Fundamental contributions are: Serenyi (1983) and Curtis (1986). Among the most recent works that offer a peculiar interpretation of Villa Sarabhai, see in particular: Ubbelohde (2003), Suarez (2006), Masud (2010), Gargiani and Rosellini (2011, pp. 361-372) and Williamson (2016, pp. 385-412). In addition, the testimonies of Balkrishna Doshi, met by the author in his studio in Ahmedabad in February 2018, are essential: Doshi (2012a), Doshi (2012b) and Doshi (2012c). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">2</p>: On the figure of Manorama Sarabhai, on the Sarabhai family and in general on the role played by Ahmedabad’s business elite see in particular: Pandya (2002), Nanda (1991), Mehta (2005), Alessandrini (2012), Leone (2013) and Williamson (2016, pp.118-275). Also, Mrinalini Sarabhai’s autobiography (2004) is an indispensable work. As Williamson (2016) explains, architecture, with forms that balance modern universal aesthetic and local culture became a powerful “tool” in representing the “small group of textile millowners and their families, who dominated the city economically and politically” (p. 26). The role entrusted to art as a useful tool in the process of development of the city and its social fabric was recognized by the entrepreneurial class of Ahmedabad even before the arrival of Le Corbusier and it was at the origin of the birth of several cultural institutions including the Ahmedabad Textile Industry Research Association (ATIRA), directed by Vikram Sarabhai, whose building was significantly designed in 1951 by Achyut Kanvinde.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">3</p>: Le Corbusier arrived in Ahmedabad for the first time in March 1951. In fact, the architect was invited to visit Ahmedabad with the task of designing a new museum with a letter dated March 10, 1951, sent to Simla where Le Corbusier had been staying for a few days while he was engaged in the preliminary phases of the Chandigarh plan. Gautam and Gira Sarabhai, Manorama’s brother-in-laws, were among Le Corbusier’s main interlocutors in this first phase of the Indian projects. Kadri, M.B. (1951, March 10). [Letter to Le Corbusier]. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P3-4-15), Fondation Le Corbusier (from now on FLC), Paris, France. See also: Sarabhai, G. (1951, March 23). Proposal for the Municipal Museum of Ahmedabad. Musée Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1956 (P3-4-16), FLC, Paris, France. After arriving in Ahmedabad, Le Corbusier was asked to design, in addition to the new city civic center, two private villas. One, never built, was for the mayor Chinubhai Chimanbhai, the other one was for Surottam Hutheesing, and later sold to Shodhan.  In November 1951, during his second stay in Ahmedabad Le Corbusier was appointed to design, in addition to the villa for Manorama, also the new headquarters of the Millowners’ Association. See Bonaiti (2021a, pp. 11-12).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">4</p>: Le Corbusier. (1952, March 7). AMS 4400. Villa de Mrs. Manorama Sarabhai, Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1951, (6676), FLC, Paris, France; Le Corbusier. (1952, March 7). AMS 4401. Villa de Mrs. Manorama Sarabhai, Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1951, (6678), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">5</p>: When compared to other works of the same years by Le Corbusier, the project of the villa is documented by a limited number of drawings.  An indispensable tool for retracing the events of the design and construction of the villa is the correspondence, particularly rich and detailed, between the site and the Parisian studio, and between Le Corbusier and Manorama Sarabhai. See in particular: Sarabhai, villa-Ahmedabad (Inde), 1951, P3-5 (153-309) and P3-7 (1-237), FLC, Paris, France; Shodhan, villa-Ahmedabad (Inde), 1951, P3-5 (1-152), FLC, Paris, France; Correspondance, Sarabhai Gira, R3-2 (331-335), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">6</p>: Doshi (2012a, p. 16).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">7</p>: See in particular: Maniaque (2005). On the use of brick vaults on the designs and works of Le Corbusier see also: Serenyi (1965), von Moos (1971), Kartik (2007), Papillaut (2011, pp. 190-196), Bonaiti (2021a, pp. 15-18) and Bonaiti (2021b).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">8</p>: As Williamson (2016) explains: “Le Corbusier essentially updated the chowk for the suburbs, not open vertically like a traditional chowk, but open longitudinally to take advantage of the breeze and views of the secluded landscape” (p. 410). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">9</p>: Doshi (2012a, p. 14).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">10</p>: Doshi (2012a) concluded: “Very different from the Jaoul houses [...] This house purposefully denies its own existence. It is indescribable in terms of spaces. It is like a sponge, porous toward the garden” (p. 14).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">11</p>: Le Corbusier (1950-1954, E18-343 and E21bis-497). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">12</p>: Since July 1953, Véret was simultaneously following the construction of all the buildings designed by Le Corbusier, dealing on a daily basis with economic, bureaucratic and technical problems. For the overall role played by Véret in Ahmedabad, see: Bonaiti (2021a) and Rampazzo (2021). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">13</p>: As is well known, Le Corbusier used to entrust each project to one or more collaborators, who he delegated for keeping contacts with clients and companies, granting them varying degrees of autonomy. In this regard, see in particular: Loach (1992) and Maniaque (2005, p. 70). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">14</p>: Véret, J.L. (1953, October 15). [Letter to Michel]. Sarabhai, villa-Ahmedabad (Inde), 1951 (P3-5-196), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">15</p>: Maniaque (2005).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">16</p>: Michel, J. (1953, November 18). [Letter to Véret]. Villa Shodhan, villa Sarabhai, palais des filateurs- Ahmedabad (Inde), 1951-1954 (P3-7-69), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">17</p>: Bonaiti (2021a, pp. 29-31).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">18</p>: Sottsass (2017, p. 148).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">19</p>: An attentive observer of Le Corbusier’s work is James Stirling (1955), who in a fundamental essay published in “Architectural Review” recognizes the similarities between the Maisons Jaoul and the Indian architectural context emphasizing with rare lucidity the profound difference that separates these works from the villas of the twenties (Bonaiti, 2021a, pp. 16-18).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">20</p>: Sottsass (2017, p. 148).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">21</p>: Sarabhai, M. (1952, February 13). [Letter to Le Corbusier]. Sarabhai, villa-Ahmedabad (Inde), 1951 (P3-5-246), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">22</p>: Fund Véret-SIAF/Cité de l’architecture et du patrimonie/Archives d’architecture du XXe siècle, Paris, France. Thanks to Bénédicte Gandini for reporting the Fund. The photographic collections are dated July 1953, February/March 1954, April 1954, August 1954, October 1954, November 1954, January 1955.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">23</p>: The drawings are respectively: Le Corbusier. (1953, July 7). AMS 4508 Revision-Garage. Villa de Mrs. Manorama Sarabhai, Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1951 (31909), FLC, Paris, France; Le Corbusier (1953, December 26). Plan de garage and Kitchen. Villa de Mrs. Manorama Sarabhai, Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1951 (6723), FLC, Paris, France. There is a further sketch – AMS 4508 Revision-Garage/Gallery, Villa de Mrs. Manorama Sarabhai, Ahmedabad-(Inde), 1951, (31908) FLC, Paris, France – undated and presumably earlier than the July 7 drawing, which shows the same changes indicating them as “approved by LC”. Together with the rotation of the garage bays, drawings FLC 31908 and FLC 31909 report for the first time the connecting passage between the house and the kitchen with brick masonry, as it will then be actually built. In a letter to Le Corbusier, dated July 9, 1953, presumably referring to sketch FLC 31909, Véret wrote: “Vous receveret aussi les dernières modifications pour le garage. La place de l’escalier d’acces au toit reste à fixer”. A survey of the garage and some areas of the villa is currently underway.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">24</p>: Bonaiti (2021a, pp. 32-40).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">25</p>: On the figure of Minnete de Silva her autobiography is fundamental: de Silva (1998). See also: Dissanayake (1982), Lee and Chakraborty (2012), Siddiqi (2017) and Akter (2018). 
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">26</p>: Correspondance, Silva Minnette de, R3-4 (2-70), FLC, Paris, France.
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">27</p>: Jullien (2016).
<p aid:cstyle="notesNumber-end">28</p>: Sarabhai, M. (1952, February 13). [Letter to Le Corbusier]. Sarabhai, villa-Ahmedabad (Inde), 1951 (P3-5-246), FLC, Paris, France.</p>

<h2 aid:pstyle="bibliography-title">Bibliografia</h2>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Akhter, A. (2018). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Modernism and Identity in the Indian Subcontinent: A Sketch of Minnette de Silva and her Works</em> [phdthesis]. University of Cincinnati</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Alessandrini, E. (2012). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Ahmedabad. Laboratorio di architettura moderna. Il National Institute of Design (1961-68) fra contatti internazionali ed echi della tradizione</em> [phdthesis]. Alma Mater Studiorum - Università di Bologna. https://doi.org/10.6092/unibo/amsdottorato/4715</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Bonaiti, M. (2021a). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier in India. Villa Sarabhai, Ahmedabad, 1951-1956</em>. Electa</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Bonaiti, M. (2021b). Tema e variazioni. Un laboratorio di architettura in India. Le Corbusier, Balkrishna Doshi, Louis I. Kahn. In F. Lenzo (Ed.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>&#34;Per avermi sognato un gran tesoro&#34;, Studies in Honor of Giovanna Curcio</em> (pp. 19–24). Campisano editore</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Curtis, W. J. R. (1986). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier: Ideas and Form</em>. Phaidon</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>De Silva, M. (1998). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Minnette de Silva: The Life and Work of an Asian Woman Architect</em> (A. de Vos, &amp; S. Sirivardana, Ed.). Smart Media Productions</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Dissanayake, E. (1982). Minnette de Silva: Pioneer of Modern Architecture in Ceylon. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Orientations</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>, 08</em>(13), 40–51</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Doshi, B. V. V. (2012). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier and Louis I. Kahn. The Acrobat and the Yogi of Architecture</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Doshi, B. V. (2012b). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier. The Indian Incarnation</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Doshi, B. V. (2012c). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier’s Work: A Personal Reading</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Gargiani, R., &amp; Rosellini, A. (2011). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier: Béton Brut and Ineffable Space, 1940-1965</em>. EPFL Press</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Jullien, F. (2016). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Il n&#39;y a pas d&#39;identité culturelle</em>. Édition de L’Herne</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Kartik, K. (2007). Story of the Monol: Le Corbusier’s Vaulted Structures. In  (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Celebrating Chandigarh</em> (pp. 403–410). Jaspreet Takhar Editor</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Le Corbusier. (1981). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Carnets 2, 1950-1954</em>. Electa</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Lee, R., &amp; James-Chakraborty, K. (2012). Marg Magazine: A Tryst with Architectural Modernity. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>ABE Journal</em> (1). https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.4000/abe.623</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Leone, G. (2013). Ahmedabad. In M. Biraghi, &amp; A. Ferlenga (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Architettura del Novecento</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>: Vol. 2</em> (pp. 7–16). Einaudi</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Loach, J. (1992). L’atelier de Le Corbusier. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Monuments historiques</em> (180), 49–52</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Maniaque, C. (2005). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier et les maisons Jaoul: projets et fabrique</em>. Picard</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Masud, R. (2010). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Language Spoken Around the World: Lessons from Le Corbusier</em> [master’s thesis]. Georgia Institute of Technology</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Mehta, M. (2005). Gandhi and Ahmedabad, 1915-20. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Economic and Political Weekly</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>, 40</em>(4), 291–299</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Moos, S. v. (1971). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier: l&#39;architecte et son mythe</em>. Horizons de France</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Nanda, V. (1991). Urbanism, Tradition and Continuity in Ahmedabad. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Mimar</em> (38), 26–36</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Pandya, Y. (2002). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>The Ahmedabad Chronicle, Imprints of a Millennium</em>. Vastu-Shilpa Foundation</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Papillault, R. (2011). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Chandigarh et Le Corbusier: création d&#39;une ville en Inde, 1950-1965</em>. Éd. Poiesis-AERA</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Rampazzo, A. (2021). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Ahmedabad e Parigi. Come Le Corbusier costruì villa Sarabhai</em>. Electa</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Sarabhai, M. (2004). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Voice of the Heart: An Autobiography</em>. HarperCollins India</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Serenyi, P. (1965). Le Corbusier&#39;s Changing Attitude toward Form. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>The Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>, 24</em>(1), 15–23</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Serenyi, P. (1983). Timeless but of Its Time: Le Corbusier&#39;s Architecture in India. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Perspecta</em> (20), 91–118</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Siddiqi, A. I. (2017). Crafting the Archive: Minnette De Silva, Architecture, and History. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>The Journal of Architecture</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>, 22</em>(8), 1299–1336</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Sottsass, E. (2017). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Per qualcuno può essere lo spazio</em>. Adelphi</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Stirling, J. (1955). From Garches to Jaoul: Le Corbusier as Domestic Architect in 1927 and 1953. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>The Architectural Review</em> (118), 145–151</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Suarez, M. C. (2006). La Villa Sarabhai de Le Corbusier. In  (Eds.), <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Le Corbusier plans 1950-1951: de l’idée au projet</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>: Vol. 10</em> (pp. DVD). </voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Ubbelohde, M. S. (2003). The dance of a summer day: Le Corbusier&#39;s Sarabhai house in Ahmedabad, India. <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Traditional Dwellings and Settlements Review</em><em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>, 14</em>(2), 65–80</voce>
<voce aid:pstyle='bibliography-entry'>Williamson, D. (2016). <em aid:cstyle='corsivo'>Modern Architecture and Capitalist Patronage in Ahmedabad, India 1947-1969</em> [phdthesis]. New York University</voce>
</root>